<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Janua divorum, or, The lives and histories of the heathen gods, goddesses &amp; demi-gods with divine and moral observations upon their most remarkable actions, adorned with 25 copper cuts proper to each deity, and put into verse / by Robert Whitcombe.</title>
            <author>Whitcombe, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33590</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523979</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1559:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Janua divorum, or, The lives and histories of the heathen gods, goddesses &amp; demi-gods with divine and moral observations upon their most remarkable actions, adorned with 25 copper cuts proper to each deity, and put into verse / by Robert Whitcombe.</title>
                  <author>Whitcombe, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 144 p., 25 leaves of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Downing for Francis Kirkman and are to be sold by most booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mythology, Classical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>title surrounded by images of (clockwise from top center) a globe, Diana, Jupiter, Mercury, Venus, Mars, Saturn, and Apollo</figDesc>
                  <p>IANUA DIVORUM or THE-LIVES-AND Histories of the HEATHEN Gods &amp; Goddesses</p>
                  <p>Printed for Francis Kirkman</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:2"/>
            <p>JANVA DIVORVM: OR THE LIVES and HISTORIES OF
<list>
                  <item>The HEATHEN GODS,</item>
                  <item>The GODDESSES, &amp;</item>
                  <item>The DEMI-GODS.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With Divine and Moral Obſervations upon their moſt remarkable Actions,</p>
            <p>Adorned with 25 Copper Cuts proper to each Deity, and put into Verſe.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT WHITCOMBE.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hom.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Downing</hi> for <hi>Francis Kirkman,</hi> and are to be ſold by moſt Bookſellers, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="alternative_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:3"/>
            <p>JANVA DIVORVM: OR THE LIVES and HISTORIES OF
<list>
                  <item>The HEATHEN GODS,</item>
                  <item>The GODDESSES, &amp;</item>
                  <item>The DEMI-GODS.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With Divine and Moral Obſervations upon their moſt remarkable Actions,</p>
            <p>Adorned with 25 Copper Cuts proper to each Deity, and put into Verſe.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT WHITCOMBE.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hom.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Kirkman,</hi> and are to be ſold by moſt Bookſellers, 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:4"/>
            <head>TO THE GENEROUS AND ACCOMPLISHT ROBERT CHENEY Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I had finiſht this ſmall <hi>Poem,</hi> I threw my laviſh eyes with heedful care a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the World in queſt of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, equally accompliſht with Knowledg and Candour, that he might be as able to judg, as willing to excuſe, the trips and failings of my Virgin Muſe. I had not bin long in this ſearch, when your tall
<pb facs="tcp:99965:5"/>Worth, like the <hi>Hebrew</hi> King, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtript the dwarfiſh Crowd, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it ſelf ſo obviouſly to my View, that I muſt have bin as blind in not diſcerning it, as unjuſt in not preferring it before others. So that Sir, like the <hi>Roman</hi> Gallant, it was your own perfumes, I mean the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural endowments, and envy'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirements of your wealthy mind, which alone have betray'd you: Had a lazy merrit ſtill ſuffer'd you with the drowſie Herd, to wallow in the common Puddle, like them, you might yet have ſlumber'd away your life in a bruitiſh obſcurity; and when age and ſucceſſion had puſht you into immortality, you need not have undergone the wrack of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:99965:5"/>your name ſever'd from your Body, but both might have layn quietly together, huddl'd up, and forgotten in the common duſt.</p>
            <p>But you Sir, by accumulating new virtues to thoſe of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> have run though a more noble, yet a more dangerous fate: For as by this means you have purchaſed an immortal reputation, ſo you have laid your ſelf open and obnoxious to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes, or rather perſecutions, not only of the ingenious, but of meer pretenders to ingenuity alſo; who ſo fit to Patronize the more accurate works of the beſt Authors, or to incourage the more incorrect indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the meaner, as your ſelf?
<pb facs="tcp:99965:6"/>who by a double tenure of Birth, and acquirements, may juſtly lay claim to thoſe ſcatterd <hi>Dividuums,</hi> which go to the compoſition of a compleat Gentleman: For as indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Nature ſeem'd to take a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care to ennoble your Blood, in deriving you from an Ancient Family, ſo you have ſhown as great a Circumſpection, in deporting your ſelf as a worthy ſtem of ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a Stock: For beſides thoſe Hereditary Virtues of Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Clemency, Affability and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which have bin the conſtant Concomitants of your renowned Progenitors, and ſo deſcend to you, like your Eſtate, by Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; your Nature love to inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity,
<pb facs="tcp:99965:6"/>as it adapted you in your youth to a Literate Education, ſo it hath prompted you ſince to a large proficiency in all the <hi>Sciences,</hi> which being ſeaſon'd with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary experience of a Genteel and Generous Converſation, has render'd you no leſs admirable, then acceptable to all the Lovers of Wit or Learning.</p>
            <p>It was theſe Glittering Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments which lighted the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Gods</hi> to take Sanctuary under the ſecure umbrage of your happy protection, where they hope for a more certain immortality then they could expect from the minute Reputation of the inconſiderable Author. I cannot commend to
<pb facs="tcp:99965:7"/>you their Garb, whether you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them either in Verſe or Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader</hi> will more fully inform you of the misfortune that happened to them in their Rigging. Only thus much I ſhall ſay for my ſelf, that were I aſſur'd they were Deckt in all the Gayeſt habiliments of Poeſie, I could not be prouder of ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a Compoſition, then I am of any opportunity wherein I may ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble and Devoted Servant, ROB. WHITCOMBE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:7"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:8"/>
            <head>TO THE ILLUSTRIOUS Madam ELLEN GUIN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HE who has ſo much arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance as to make his Addreſs to a Perſon of your Ladiſhips Eminence, ought alſo to have ſo much humility, as to acknowledg
<pb facs="tcp:99965:9"/>that he derives a greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from the <hi>Dedication,</hi> than he can expect from the <hi>Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> of the moſt perfect Poem; your Favour is more creditable than Ingenuity it ſelf, and an Author need not fear the harſh attaques of Time, and Oblivion, whoſe Works have the Honor to wear you in their Frontiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece. Next to the Ambition of being known to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip, this conſideration was the greateſt inducement that led me to this boldneſs; or as I think, I may rather term it
<pb facs="tcp:99965:9"/>Ambition, ſince the minuteſt of your incomparable Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions could never make ſo ſwift an incurſion into my thoughts, as not to find them ſufficiently prepar'd with a Reverence, and Adoration agreeable to ſo glorious a Reception. I knew that tho Curious Nature had extended her endeavors in the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your delicate Body, injoyn'd both it and every Limb about you to an exact Symitry, and pleaſing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion: Tho ſhe had been laviſh of her Allurements in
<pb facs="tcp:99965:10"/>wantonly ſtrewing them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your Wealthy Face, and to compleat the Fabrick, had enobled it with that brisk air and graceful meen, which certainly ſhe has given you a Patent for, ſince none could ever acquire it but your Self, yet you could not be content with this her bounty, or think your Self perfect with the additional Bleſſings of Liberal Fate; you never rated your Self by your Grandure, or took the Dimentions of your worth as others do, by the gilded Coach, gaudie Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
<pb facs="tcp:99965:10"/>and ſnorting Six—Theſe are trifles incident to the moſt empty Darlings of Impartial Fate. But you are more nobly attended with an illuſtrious Troop of Sublime Thoughts, and fair Idea's which tacitly invading your Great Mind, fill it with that Satisfaction &amp; Delight, which none but a Soul as large as your own, is capable to conceive.</p>
            <p>It was this brave Elevation above the unthinking Croud; which induc'd me amongſt the reſt of your Admirers to
<pb facs="tcp:99965:11"/>think ſuch extraordinary parts worthy of more than a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon adoration, and therefore I have preſum'd to bring the HEATHEN GODS to do you Homage; they lye proſtrate at your feet, intreating your acceptance, and proteſt they ſhall live longer and happier under your Protection, in theſe poor Robes, than they can expect to do under any others, tho adorn'd with all the gayeſt Habilements of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> I, conſcious to their Infirmities, quarrelled at their Ambition for imploring ſo
<pb facs="tcp:99965:11"/>Judicious a Patroneſs; but they would hear of no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial: replying, that as you had Judgment, you had Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor likewiſe; and were more addicted to forgive than cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Apollo</hi> told me, that in you only he ſhould meet with his Primitive Wiſdom. <hi>Mercury</hi> with his Priſtine Wit. <hi>Juno</hi> with her old Soveraignty or greatneſs of Mind. <hi>Venus</hi> with her delicate Beauty. And <hi>Alcides</hi> with his Godlike Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and brave Spirit. And in ſhort, they affirm'd, that all thoſe Noble Qualifications
<pb facs="tcp:99965:12"/>for which they were formerly Deify'd, were only Concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in your Self, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humbly deſired the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of your Patronage, tho Preſented by ſo mean a Hand as that of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble and Devoted Servant <hi>ROBERT WHITCOMBE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:12"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Remember the Incomparable Author of <hi>PARTHENISSA,</hi> tells us in one of his <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> that for a long time he had an unuſual averſneſs to Reading, till being call'd upon occaſion into <hi>France,</hi> and converſing there with the accompliſh'd Ladies of thoſe times, he found it as abſolutely neceſſary to be skill'd in <hi>Romance,</hi> as in any other part of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation whatſoever: Whereupon he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Books, and what Proficiency he has made therein, is beſt known by thoſe Excellent <hi>Poems</hi> wherewith he has ſince oblig'd the World at ſo large a Rate, that it will be her greateſt Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="tcp:99965:13"/>to plead Poverty, ſince ſhe is not able to render him a Requital. That a Competent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Laws and Grounds of <hi>Poeſie</hi> in general is as abſolutely requiſit amongſt the Engliſh-Gentry now, as that of <hi>Romance</hi> only was among the French then, is ſo eaſie a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, that he who has ventur'd but as far as <hi>Charing-Croſs;</hi> or attempted to come within the perfume of a <hi>Courtier,</hi> can deſide it on the Affirmative. 'Tis thought as neceſſary to the Complement of a Courtier, as the knowledg of the Compaſs to the Compoſition of a Seaman; neither Man nor Woman can ſafely Sail in the Courts dangerous Ocean without it, unleſs they are reſolved to expoſe themſelves to thoſe Impetuous Storms of Scorn and Neglect, which Augmented by Envy and Intereſt, will imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately hurry them into one of thoſe Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Gulphs, <hi>Ruine</hi> or <hi>Diſgrace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How neceſſary the Knowledg of the Lives and Hiſtories of the <hi>Heathen Gods</hi> will be to thoſe Ingenious Spirits, who deſign to make an
<pb facs="tcp:99965:13"/>inſpection into this Noble <hi>Science,</hi> will moſt evidently appear if we but turn our heads over our ſhoulders, to look back into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of <hi>Poeſie;</hi> where we ſhall find <hi>Homer</hi> ſo inquiſitive after their Offices and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that at length he is able to give us an account of both their Nature and Affections, and to compleat his Poem, was forc'd to divide them into almoſt as many Sects and Factions as we have now in <hi>England.</hi> There was no Battel but ſome <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Goddeſs</hi> was partial in the event. And ſince by the ſevere Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates of Imperious Fate, <hi>Troy</hi> was to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd, it was no ſmall Comfort unto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining Glory of the defeated <hi>Trojans,</hi> that their Deities rather than their Armies were overcome in the Contest. Lofty <hi>Virgil</hi> lays hold of the ſame aſſiſtance, and that <hi>Italian Shake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphear, Ovid,</hi> Tho miraculouſly throng'd with thoſe Poetical Bleſſings, <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> durſt not hazard his Reputation on their Bottoms; but diſcreetly laid the ſteady founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:99965:14"/>of his Immortal Poem on the ſame Baſis, and cemented it with the like Ligaments as his Two famous Predeceſſors had done before.</p>
            <p>So that the queſtion will not be ſo much whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the knowledg of the <hi>Heathen Gods</hi> be neceſſary to Poeſie, as why I attempted their Lives in Verſe, ſince they were ſo excellently Written in Proſe. The truth is, I muſt needs ſubmit to the Learning of ſeveral Authors who have writ of this Subject, I only pretend to be a gleaner in their wealthy fields, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Wheat in my little Mow ows its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal to their labours. I began this ſmall Piece for my own Satisfaction; But (I know not how) ſome of the ſheets being ſcatter'd abroad, at laſt came to a Stationers hand, who was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to think them worthy of Publick View, and had intended to adorn them with all Copper Cuts, like thoſe of <hi>Venus, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Diana;</hi> but being prevented by a tedious fit of ſickneſs, they were forc'd to take up with ſuch as you ſee. I can ſay little as to the Book, and only thus
<pb facs="tcp:99965:14"/>much for my ſelf, that it was writ in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey about <hi>18</hi> Months ago, and has ever ſince lain in the Printers hands, who by reaſon of my abſence, has miſplaced ſeveral of the Hiſtories, and not being acquainted with my hand, has like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made many groſs Errors, ſome whereof he has directed you to in the Errata, and the rest leaves to the Correction of the Judicious <hi>Reader.</hi> I might farther excuſe my Circumlocutions, or large Exordiums, which I make many times to take up more room than the Hiſtories themſelves; which I know is contrary to Art, and can only ſay, I was in moſt places forc't to it, for being by Reaſon of the Sculptures oblig'd to make every Hiſtory almoſt equal in number of Lines, I thought it to ſupply ſomeof thoſe Nigardly <hi>Stories,</hi> (which I might have compriz'd in half a Page) with uſeful Obſervations, which naturally ariſing from the moſt remarkable Actions of that Deity treat of, will I hope prove more grateful to any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntelligent Reader, than an accumulated bundle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f invented Fables, which I muſt otherwiſe have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lapt in their room.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:15"/>
            <p>But all theſe Apologies with many others, which I might reaſonably add, could not have prevail'd with me to appear in Print, had I not conſidered that there are many excellent Wits of both Sexes, whom cruel Cuſtom or incroaching Buſineſs has debar'd the benefit of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Tongues, to whom I thought this ſmall Poem illuſtrated with Cuts proper to every God and Goddeſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might not be altogether inſignificant, nor any thing the leſs acceptable becauſe in Verſe, whoſe Chiming Periods ſeem at once to ſtrike both the Fancies and Memories of the illiterate. To whom, if this Contributes any aſſiſtance, it has effected the intention of Thy loving Friend.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:15"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:16"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>SATVRNE.</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99965:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Saturn.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen the great Fabrick of the world was wrought,</l>
                  <l>And all things newly ſtarted out of Nought.</l>
                  <l>Ran into form, and made a goodly ſhow,</l>
                  <l>None could immagin whence they came, or how.</l>
                  <l>Sudden th' appear'd, and pleaſing to the Eie,</l>
                  <l>As gaudy Rainbows in a Cloudy Skie;</l>
                  <l>Form'd, as 'tis thought, by ſome Superior Good,</l>
                  <l>Who the firſt Elements well underſtood;</l>
                  <l>Knew their compoſures, and with Artful hand,</l>
                  <l>Made 'em obedient to his lowd Command.</l>
                  <l>The which down hither, he ſo neatly hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>That in their fall, they dropt into a World.</l>
                  <l>Within whoſe ſpacious Confines there was none</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Coelus</hi> found to Rule the Empty Throne;</l>
                  <l>Who as he walk'd his Boundleſs Empire, ſpide</l>
                  <l>The Goddeſs <hi>Terra,</hi> whom he took for Bride.</l>
                  <l>Out of whoſe Firtil Womb, he ſoon begot</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tytan</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> Gods of wondrous Note,</l>
                  <l>And Monſtrous <hi>Cyclops,</hi> Born but with one Eie</l>
                  <l>Amidſt their Front; at which Deformitie</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99965:17"/>
                  <l>The Throbing Breaſt of <hi>Coelus</hi> did ſo ſwell,</l>
                  <l>That Furiouſly he hurl'd them down to Hell;</l>
                  <l>Condemn'd them there, Eternally to Fry,</l>
                  <l>In forming bolts for <hi>Jove</hi>'s Artillery:</l>
                  <l>Which diſmal News, when it approacht the Ears</l>
                  <l>Of Virtuous <hi>Terra,</hi> ſet her all in Tears;</l>
                  <l>Who ſoon that Paſſion for a Nobler Chang'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſtead of Sighing, ſought to be Reveng'd</l>
                  <l>Of her too cruel Husband. Straight ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>To both her Sons, to whom ſhe does Diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>Their Fathers horrid Fact at ſuch a rate,</l>
                  <l>As gave them cauſe to fear Reſembling Fate.</l>
                  <l>Adventerous <hi>Saturn</hi> had no ſooner heard</l>
                  <l>The Impious Story, but without regard</l>
                  <l>To filial Duty, or that Reverent fear</l>
                  <l>Which Children to their Parents ought to bear,</l>
                  <l>With his keen Syth to <hi>Coelus</hi> ſtraight he flies,</l>
                  <l>And Cruelly cuts off his Privities:</l>
                  <l>Commits them to the foaming Sea for Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Where yet they found a favourable Womb,</l>
                  <l>Ingendring with that froth, from which Dame <hi>Venus</hi> ſprung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The mighty Emp'ror of the VVorld thus Dead,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tytan</hi> as Elder brother ſhould ſucceed;</l>
                  <l>But him, his Mother, and his Siſter too,</l>
                  <l>Slyly perſwaded to Reſign his Due</l>
                  <l>(For Life) to <hi>Saturn,</hi> who aſcends the Throne</l>
                  <l>He was to hold, on this Condition,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99965:17"/>
                  <l>VVhat ever Children Male, Saturn ſhould have</l>
                  <l>By his <hi>Sybelle,</hi> none of them muſt Live,</l>
                  <l>That ſo no Heirs might poſſibly ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Tytans</hi> Linage Reign when he was Dead.</l>
                  <l>The Bloody contract thus agreed upon,</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Saturns</hi> VViſe, <hi>Sybelle,</hi> was far gon</l>
                  <l>In anxious Travel of a Luſty Boy,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſoon as Born, his Father did Deſtroy</l>
                  <l>VVith open Mouth, tearing it Limb from Limb,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Cannibal</hi> appear'd a Saint to him.</l>
                  <l>The new Congealed Fleſh, like Gravy run</l>
                  <l>Out of both ſides his Mouth, and ere he had done,</l>
                  <l>The offended Blood, be ſmeer'd his Graceleſs Cheeks,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſtopt his Ears againſt the Infants Shrieks</l>
                  <l>And ſpotleſs Innocence, which might have mov'd</l>
                  <l>A Tygar to repent his Rage, and Lov'd.</l>
                  <l>The griev'd <hi>Sybelle,</hi> mightily diſmay'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſee that all her Sons muſt be deſtroy'd,</l>
                  <l>By virtuous Subtilty, reſolved to ſtrive</l>
                  <l>The beſt ſhe could to keep an Heir a Live,</l>
                  <l>VVhich thus ſhe brought to paſs, within a while,</l>
                  <l>VVith forward ſwins her VVomb began to ſwell;</l>
                  <l>Her time expir'd, and ſhe did ſafely Bear</l>
                  <l>Two Luſty Babes, <hi>Juno</hi> and <hi>Jupiter;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The firſt a Female, was to Saturn ſent,</l>
                  <l>VVho nothing Jealous of the good event,</l>
                  <l>VVas well content, and certainly Believ'd</l>
                  <l>That ſhe was all his VVife had then Conceiv'd.</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99965:18"/>
                  <l>To <hi>Curetes</hi> or <hi>Corybantes</hi> care,</l>
                  <l>She recommends the helpleſs <hi>Jupiter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To Nurſe him privately, and ſo to Free</l>
                  <l>Him from his Fathers Bloody Crueltie.</l>
                  <l>Divers more Sons did fruitful <hi>Terra</hi> bear,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Lives ſhe Ranſom'd with reſembling Care,</l>
                  <l>Inventing Tinking Games, of happy noyſe</l>
                  <l>VVhich drowned both her little Infants voyce,</l>
                  <l>And ſtopt their Fathers Rage, and fil'd their Mothers Joyes.</l>
                  <l>In this ſoft Calm of ſtate, began that Age</l>
                  <l>VVhich all the Pens of Poets did engage</l>
                  <l>To Celebrate. That Golden Age, when Man,</l>
                  <l>Stranger to waſting Grief and fretful pain,</l>
                  <l>In cool green ſhades, made up a bleſt aboad,</l>
                  <l>Rich as a Miſer, happy as a God.</l>
                  <l>Ere ſimple Nature was by art Debaucht,</l>
                  <l>Or Luxury his Inclination reacht,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt homely Plenty with ſharp appetite,</l>
                  <l>Imparted ſatisfaction and delight:</l>
                  <l>His food was ſuch as Nature did impart,</l>
                  <l>Ere with the vitious eating grew an Art,</l>
                  <l>And Chaſt cold Springs did kindly ſquench his Thirſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich by no Fevouriſh ſurfeit was increaſt.</l>
                  <l>VVhen only needful things he aim'd to know,</l>
                  <l>And calm content ſet ſimpering on his Brow.</l>
                  <l>Theſe were the bleſſings of wiſe <hi>Saturns</hi> Days,</l>
                  <l>To which ſucceeding Ages gave ſuch prays.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99965:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturn,</hi> the God of time, whoſe mighty hand</l>
                  <l>An endleſs Serpent graſping did command;</l>
                  <l>VVho her ſharp Tail into her mouth did Twine,</l>
                  <l>As a fit Emblem of Reverting Time.</l>
                  <l>Years end in Years, and Seaſons ſteal upon us</l>
                  <l>At unawares, <hi>In ceſe virtitur Annus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen Creeping time with man-like years had fil'd</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whom <hi>Saturn</hi> would have Kil'd,</l>
                  <l>And giv'n him VVit and Courage, ſuch a ſtore,</l>
                  <l>As did forbid his ſilence any more.</l>
                  <l>VVherefore, when he had heard the full deſign,</l>
                  <l>How his own Father ſought to Murther him;</l>
                  <l>Studying by all his Cunning to prevent</l>
                  <l>That horrid Death which to himſelf was meant,</l>
                  <l>From Heaven, by force, he made his Father fly</l>
                  <l>To ſeek a Reſidence in <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:19"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>IUPITER.</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99965:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Jupiter.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SAturn</hi> thus Vanquiſht, <hi>Jupiter</hi> his Son,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt himſelf and's Brethren ſhar'd his Throne.</l>
                  <l>Heav'n to himſelf he kept; the VVaters he</l>
                  <l>Commits to's Brother <hi>Neptunes</hi> Sov'raigntie;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt to his Brother <hi>(Pluto</hi>'s) Lot it fell</l>
                  <l>To Rule the large Dominions of Hell.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Jupiter</hi> had ſcarcely warm'd his Throne,</l>
                  <l>But an Inteſtine Dangerous War begun</l>
                  <l>To Reel his Title, for the angry Earth</l>
                  <l>Seeing her Sons, the <hi>Titans</hi> bruis'd to Death;</l>
                  <l>Brought forth ſtrange Monſters of a Hideous hew,</l>
                  <l>Mighty in ſtrength, and terrible to veiw:</l>
                  <l>Which horrid Army, ſhe forthwith commands</l>
                  <l>To Randeſvouz in the <hi>Theſsalean</hi> ſtrands,</l>
                  <l>Amidſt the fair <hi>Plegrean</hi> Fields; where ſhe</l>
                  <l>Points them the likelyeſt way to Victorie.</l>
                  <l>Hills upon Hills, and Rocks on Rocks they throw,</l>
                  <l>Mountains and Trees, and all they found below</l>
                  <l>That great or bulky ſeem'd, thereby to Raiſe</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Piramid,</hi> whoſe head might reach the Skyes.</l>
                  <l>From whence they meant to brave the Gods, and then</l>
                  <l>To hurl their Emp'rour to Earth agen.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99965:20"/>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt, who threatened Heaven thus,</l>
                  <l>Were ſtout <hi>Aegeon</hi> and <hi>Enceladus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With brave <hi>Bryarius,</hi> and more than theſe,</l>
                  <l>All born with full a hundred Hands a Piece;</l>
                  <l>Which in hard Service, every one did Joyn</l>
                  <l>Towards th' accompliſhing the bold deſign.</l>
                  <l>The vaſt <hi>Sicilian Typhon,</hi> who could ſtand</l>
                  <l>With's Feet on the Earth, and ſcratch the Sky with's Hand,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe outſtretcht Arms, could all the world Controul,</l>
                  <l>And touch at once the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Southern</hi> Pole:</l>
                  <l>Half Man, half Serpent too, he did appear,</l>
                  <l>(As did the moſt of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe Monſters there,)</l>
                  <l>A ſcortching Breath from out his Body came,</l>
                  <l>And Fiery Belches Flaſhing into Flame;</l>
                  <l>Guilded with ſo much horror, that the fright</l>
                  <l>Caus'd ſome young Gods to make a ſhameful flight;</l>
                  <l>VVho daſtardly to wealthy <hi>Aegypt</hi> ran</l>
                  <l>Aſſuming there ſome Leek or Onyan's Name:</l>
                  <l>Cauſing by ſo unworthy a Diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſond <hi>Egyptians</hi> to <hi>Idolatrize.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſtill the Seidge bold <hi>Jupiter</hi> withſtands,</l>
                  <l>Hurling great Thunderbolts from his dire hands;</l>
                  <l>VVhich thick as Hailſtones, on the Gyants Lighted,</l>
                  <l>VVho at ſo ſtrange Artillery affrighted;</l>
                  <l>No longer durſt the Heav'nly force engage,</l>
                  <l>But took their heels, and baſely fled the Siedge.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill his anger on theſe Monſters fell,</l>
                  <l>VVhich overtook them ſending ſome to Hell;</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99965:20"/>
                  <l>Others by hideous Death's to end he brought,</l>
                  <l>Loading their Graves with mighty <hi>Aetna</hi>'s weight,</l>
                  <l>That they as endleſs Monuments might Lye,</l>
                  <l>And tell his Fame to long Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Gyants thus diſtroy'd, that very year,</l>
                  <l>The Heavenly Thief <hi>Prometheus</hi> did appear,</l>
                  <l>VVho taking Earth and VVater, then began</l>
                  <l>To Form and ſhape the Hapleſs Creature Man;</l>
                  <l>VVhom he endow'd with an Immortal Soul</l>
                  <l>Of Heavenly fire, which he from thence had ſtole.</l>
                  <l>VVhen all the powerful <hi>Jupiter</hi> enrag'd,</l>
                  <l>Sends to his Uncle <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan,</hi> and engag'd</l>
                  <l>Him upon honour, not to let this paſs;</l>
                  <l>So that a mighty Chain provided was</l>
                  <l>To bind him to mount <hi>Caucacus</hi> for ever,</l>
                  <l>And deathleſs Vultures to Devour his Liver;</l>
                  <l>Which every Night encreaſt, that ſo the pain</l>
                  <l>By them next day might be renew'd again:</l>
                  <l>But valliant <hi>Hercules</hi> diſturb'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>Him tortur'd thus for's Ingenuitie,</l>
                  <l>With pearleſs ſtrength, plucks of the weighty Chain,</l>
                  <l>And freed him from Impriſonment and pain.</l>
                  <l>Whereat great <hi>Jupiter</hi> incenſ'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſo ſoon at Libertie,</l>
                  <l>VVhom he a ſad and endleſs Hell deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>He recontracts the fury of his mind,</l>
                  <l>Doubles his Rage, and with a frowning Brow,</l>
                  <l>And fiery Eyes, begins to ſtudy how</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99965:21"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prometheus</hi> his pain he might ſo change,</l>
                  <l>As to Inflict on him a worſe Revenge.</l>
                  <l>And therefore to the fair <hi>Pandora</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>As the moſt likely fatal inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>To work the black reſolves of his vext mind,</l>
                  <l>(Beauty corrupted, is to vice moſt kind.)</l>
                  <l>To her he calls, and haſtily Commands,</l>
                  <l>To take into her fair and beauteous hands,</l>
                  <l>A falal Box of Deadly Poyſons, which</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Epemetheus</hi> as a Preſent Rich,</l>
                  <l>And ſent from Gods, ſhe muſt deliver to him,</l>
                  <l>VVho hoping ſome great rarity therein,</l>
                  <l>Haſtily open'd it, at which there flew,</l>
                  <l>A Neſt of Evils and diſſeaſes too;</l>
                  <l>VVho expeditiouſly themſelves diſperſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſadly tainted all the Univerſe.</l>
                  <l>Thus Fame and Triumph ſeemed every where,</l>
                  <l>To weight upon victorious <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who having cruſht the Gyants, and ſubdu'd</l>
                  <l>Rebellious Mortals; ſofter eaſe perſu'd.</l>
                  <l>VVarm Luxury began to make her Neſt</l>
                  <l>In the Meridian of his Royal breaſt;</l>
                  <l>And Love and Luſt, blow'd up ſuch glowing fires,</l>
                  <l>As prompted him to eaſe—thoſe lew'd deſires.</l>
                  <l>To virtue now he had but ſmall regard,</l>
                  <l>VVhen Inceſt but a little Sin appear'd.</l>
                  <l>His Native Siſter <hi>June</hi> he did VVed,</l>
                  <l>And forc'd her to his rude Inceſtious Bed.</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99965:21"/>
                  <l>Then <hi>Tros</hi>'s Son, young <hi>Ganimedes,</hi> he</l>
                  <l>Did force to an unknown Debaucherie.</l>
                  <l>The fair <hi>Europa,</hi> ſhe from whoſe bright fame,</l>
                  <l>The beſt part of the World has ta'ne its Name,</l>
                  <l>VVas the next victin to his raging Luſt.</l>
                  <l>By reaſon of whoſe virtue, he was forc'd</l>
                  <l>To change his Godlike, for a Beaſtlike ſhape,</l>
                  <l>VVherein by force he did that wicked Rape.</l>
                  <l>The next was <hi>Dena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in her braſen Tower,</l>
                  <l>VVherein he got and rain'd a golden ſhow'r,</l>
                  <l>VVhich lighted on ſuch animated Earth,</l>
                  <l>As gave renowned <hi>Perſeus</hi> happy birth.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Jupiter</hi> before his laſt retreat,</l>
                  <l>VVas grown to men as infamous as great.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:22"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>MARS.</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99965:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Mars.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Long adeiw to all the Sweets of Eaſe,</l>
                  <l>To all the pleaſing ſofts of downy Peace;</l>
                  <l>To all my ſilent ſighs and lonely grief,</l>
                  <l>VVhich to my Labouring mind have brought Relief;</l>
                  <l>VVhen all my ſtartled friends, my help did fly,</l>
                  <l>Fearing th' infection of my miſery;</l>
                  <l>And every frowning ſtorm, Heav'n Combin'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſtorm the requiems of my happy mind.</l>
                  <l>Farewel each ſilent ſpring, and ſhady grove,</l>
                  <l>Ye kind repeaters of my ſlighted Love;</l>
                  <l>How oft have you a temperate Solſtice made</l>
                  <l>For my reception, ſweetly ſtain'd with ſhade:</l>
                  <l>VVhere 'neath the umbrage of ſome willow, I,</l>
                  <l>Melted to Tears, and breath'd into a ſigh:</l>
                  <l>To beautious <hi>Sylvia</hi> for a Smile did ſue,</l>
                  <l>VVhen your kind. Eccho nimbly anſwers, doe.</l>
                  <l>But ſhe, ah cruel ſhe! with ſcornful Eye</l>
                  <l>And frowning Brow, commanded me to Dye</l>
                  <l>Farewel my Study, where I us'd to find,</l>
                  <l>Jems to inrich my ſoon exhauſted mind,</l>
                  <l>VVhich without th' aſſiſtance of that wealthy ore,</l>
                  <l>VVould ſoon turn Bankrupt, and indite no more.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99965:23"/>
                  <l>Glutted with pleaſure, often have I read,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſweet communications of the Dead;</l>
                  <l>With ſuch delight, and Rapſody of Mind,</l>
                  <l>With thoughts ſo ſettled, and a Soul ſublim'd,</l>
                  <l>That grief nor Care, withal their ſubleſt Art,</l>
                  <l>Could find no Room nor Lodging in my heart.</l>
                  <l>Contentment Raign'd, and during its ſhort ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Lockt up the Door, and kept it ſelf the Key.</l>
                  <l>The Lib'ral Sciences, like various Diſhes</l>
                  <l>Beſieg'd me round, and pleas'd my higheſt wiſhes.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes I did my hungry Stomach try,</l>
                  <l>With the firſt courſe of ſound Phyloſophy:</l>
                  <l>The ſtrong'ſt and ſolid'ſt Viends to ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>The light <hi>Mercurial</hi> Junkets of the Brain.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes my thoughts were much ſublimer giv'n,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrove to trace the Motions of the Heav'n;</l>
                  <l>Where I beheld each Planet in Seat</l>
                  <l>Regent, was King, and Carved human fate.</l>
                  <l>Then with a curious, but declined Eye,</l>
                  <l>I read the ſmall <hi>Aenigma</hi>'s of the Sky.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes to look, my Fancy did incline,</l>
                  <l>In the dark backward, and abiſs of time;</l>
                  <l>Where it ſolac'd me infin'tely to learn,</l>
                  <l>The Humour of the world e're I was born.</l>
                  <l>But then I muſt confeſs, I griev'd to know</l>
                  <l>How wiſe men then were, and how fooliſh now.</l>
                  <l>Then like a Laden <hi>Bee,</hi> I'de homeward flie.</l>
                  <l>To my own Native Study, Poeſie:</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99965:23"/>
                  <l>And wind up all in Meaſure and in Form,</l>
                  <l>Which I from other Sciences did Learn.</l>
                  <l>This was the buſineſs of my Eaſe, but now</l>
                  <l>Such downy thoughts, alas, I muſt forego,</l>
                  <l>And nought but thoſe of fighting, noys of Drum,</l>
                  <l>And claſhing Swords, muſt in my Phanſie come;</l>
                  <l>The Trumpets Clangor, and the warlike fife,</l>
                  <l>The deſperate Souldier, prodigal of Life,</l>
                  <l>Conjoyned Battles, which incorporate ſeem,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Choruſt</hi> with ditmal groans of dying Men,</l>
                  <l>Are thoughts moſt fit for him, who dares to be</l>
                  <l>So bould, brave <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> as write thy Hiſtorie.</l>
                  <l>Thou Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi>'s bed,</l>
                  <l>Who in the warlike <hi>Northern</hi> Climes waſt bred;</l>
                  <l>Taught by wild Furious Lyons, how to Dare,</l>
                  <l>And how to ſuffer, by the Ruged Bear.</l>
                  <l>On whom a <hi>Northern</hi> blaſt no more Prevails,</l>
                  <l>That does on us warm <hi>Zypherus</hi> gentle Gales.</l>
                  <l>About the world thou undiſturb'd wouldſt go,</l>
                  <l>When all the Earth was mantled up in Snow;</l>
                  <l>And Fierceſt Tygars from their Dens didſt Chace,</l>
                  <l>VVho to thy hotter Fury ſoon gave place,</l>
                  <l>Leaving thee their, warm Coverts for to be,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Magazin</hi> to hold thy Arms and thee.</l>
                  <l>This thy prodigious valour, when 'twas hurld,</l>
                  <l>B'officious ſame, to this our Southern world;</l>
                  <l>Made Jealous <hi>Jupiter</hi> a fraid to fee,</l>
                  <l>Thus threatning ſtem of his own Proginie.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99965:24"/>
                  <l>Born on triumphant Charriot, thou didſt Ride,</l>
                  <l>With frightful Sprights, attending at thy ſide:</l>
                  <l>Clamour, Contention, and thin Meagre fear,</l>
                  <l>Dreſt in their proper garbs, thy Servants were.</l>
                  <l>Terror and apprehenſion too, with long</l>
                  <l>And griſly locks, went ſtalking in the throng</l>
                  <l>Before the loud tongu'd fame in gaudy Cloaths,</l>
                  <l>(Stuck full of Eyes, as Orenges with Cloves.)</l>
                  <l>In Antick garb, as Ancient Poets ſay,</l>
                  <l>Sat as Poſtilian all thy flower ſtrow'd way.</l>
                  <l>In this Heroick poſture didſt thou come,</l>
                  <l>Diſplaying Colours, ſtriding on a Drum,</l>
                  <l>Halbeart in hand, and trunchion on thy hip,</l>
                  <l>With Fair <hi>Bellona,</hi> flouriſhing her whip.</l>
                  <l>When Limping <hi>Vulcans</hi> light new Married Dame,</l>
                  <l>Came to intrap thee with her wanton Flame.</l>
                  <l>And now ye Sons of <hi>War,</hi> ſome of ye do,</l>
                  <l>Tell me what all your mighty ſtrength can do?</l>
                  <l>You who have watcht a Siedge both day and night,</l>
                  <l>Till your Numb'd Limbs have Frozen where you ſit:</l>
                  <l>You who can Laugh, when th' <hi>Ominous</hi> Canon bauls,</l>
                  <l>And crouds of Souldiers to <hi>Elizium</hi> calls.</l>
                  <l>You, in whoſe countenance no change appears,</l>
                  <l>Though whiſtling <hi>Bullets</hi> fly about your Ears.</l>
                  <l>Or you, who from a <hi>Rampter</hi> dare to expoſe</l>
                  <l>Your Selves and Friends amongſt your deadly Foes;</l>
                  <l>Tell me how meanly ſhould you theſe things prize,</l>
                  <l>VVho have no Armour 'gainſt a womans Eyes.</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99965:24"/>
                  <l>Behold and ſee your all-commanding <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The mighty Stickler in the Roman VVars:</l>
                  <l>He who did all their Enemies Reſiſt,</l>
                  <l>And dealt out Crowns to whom, and where he liſt.</l>
                  <l>VVhen he beholds fair <hi>Venus</hi> on his Knee,</l>
                  <l>Poorly Intreating his Captivitie:</l>
                  <l>Changing the Title due to Martial Cares,</l>
                  <l>For a Common Souldier in Venerial VVars.</l>
                  <l>The comming Goddeſs preſently was won,</l>
                  <l>And freely grants an aſſignation;</l>
                  <l>VVhich prively, without the leaſt regard</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe two Cumbitants, was over heard</l>
                  <l>By Yellow <hi>Vulcan,</hi> who a Net prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>VVherein the Naked Lovers were inſnar'd.</l>
                  <l>Juſt in the time of Action, all the Gods</l>
                  <l>At News hereof came from their bright Aboads,</l>
                  <l>To ſee 'em both in Loves Imbraces Ly,</l>
                  <l>Expos'd to view, and bar'd from Liberty;</l>
                  <l>Some Laught, ſome Bluſht, ſome gave him heavy Doom,</l>
                  <l>But others Smil'd, and wiſht 'um in his Room.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:25"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>APOLLO.</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99965:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Apollo.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LUxurious <hi>Jupiter</hi> at length bring Cloyd,</l>
                  <l>With th' nauceous pleaſures of a Marriage Bed;</l>
                  <l>His wanton Eyes on fair <hi>Latona</hi> plac'd,</l>
                  <l>(A ruddy Nimph with wondrous Beauty grac'd.)</l>
                  <l>Her he affected, and with pain he ſtrove,</l>
                  <l>To let her know the greatneſs of his Love.</l>
                  <l>The Pretty Nimph, as other Maidens do,</l>
                  <l>At firſt reply'd the uſual anſwer—No.</l>
                  <l>But when the God-like Lover preſt her home,</l>
                  <l>Like full ripe Fruit, ſhe gently tumbel'd Down;</l>
                  <l>And with encloſed Eyes, that bliſs enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>Which 'gainſt her Conſcience ſhe ſo long deny'd.</l>
                  <l>But their Imbraces could not be ſo cloſe,</l>
                  <l>But Jealous <hi>Juno</hi> heard the Echoing Noys,</l>
                  <l>Which through the Mouth of Pratling Gods was ſent.</l>
                  <l>So Loud, it ſounded through the Continent.</l>
                  <l>By grand experience Marry'd Folks may Gheſs,</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Juno</hi> brook't her Rivals happineſs.</l>
                  <l>When ſhe was told, her Husband did confer</l>
                  <l>On Fair <hi>Latona,</hi> what was due to her.</l>
                  <l>Great Gods! Methinks I hear her tear and Fling,</l>
                  <l>And Swear ſo loud, ſhe makes the Heaven's Ring;</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99965:26"/>
                  <l>Upbraided <hi>Jupiter</hi> with th' horrid Sin,</l>
                  <l>And threatning ſhe will do as much for him.</l>
                  <l>Then on a ſudden, into ſilence change,</l>
                  <l>With bended Brows contriving this revenge.</l>
                  <l>The Serpent <hi>Python</hi> which in former time,</l>
                  <l>Sprang from the fam'd <hi>Deucaleans</hi> Muddy ſlime.</l>
                  <l>Him ſhe engaged by her ſtrict command,</l>
                  <l>To drive <hi>Latona</hi> from that fertil Land,</l>
                  <l>And Brib'd the Earth, to let her have no room</l>
                  <l>In all the world, but <hi>Delos</hi> for her home;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Delos</hi> which might as well have ſerv'd her for a Tomb.</l>
                  <l>Had not kind <hi>Neptune</hi> for <hi>Latona</hi>'s ſake,</l>
                  <l>Both fixt and rais'd it bove the briniſh Lake</l>
                  <l>VVherein it ſunk. There as ſhe walkt a while,</l>
                  <l>Admiring at th'uninhabited Iſle,</l>
                  <l>She chanc'd to find a ſpreading Palmtree Leaf,</l>
                  <l>(The ſheet which caught the burden of her Grief,)</l>
                  <l>VVhereon her body was no ſooner layd,</l>
                  <l>But out alaſs! In vain for help ſhe cry'd:</l>
                  <l>No friendly Mid-wife to her Groans was near,</l>
                  <l>There was no Husband, nor kind Neighbours there,</l>
                  <l>Nor none to pitty with a wiſhing Tear.</l>
                  <l>But by and by a recompence appear'd</l>
                  <l>For all her pains, when two fair Twins ſhe heard.</l>
                  <l>VVith Infant ſhrieks, endeav'ring to bemone,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe throws and Pangs which ſhe had undergone;</l>
                  <l>Theſe were <hi>Diana</hi> and <hi>Apollo.</hi> He</l>
                  <l>Soon as Arriv'd at full Maturitie,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99965:26"/>
                  <l>Remembring <hi>Pythons</hi> Rudeneſs to his Mother,</l>
                  <l>No longer could his Noble Vengeance Smother:</l>
                  <l>VVith Bow and Quiver to that VVood he hy'd,</l>
                  <l>Where Monſtrous <hi>Typhon</hi> Cuſtom'd to reſide;</l>
                  <l>VVho made a ſtrong reſiſtance but in vain,</l>
                  <l>For all the Gods the Quarrel did maintain.</l>
                  <l>And Heaven it ſelf with an unus'd delight,</l>
                  <l>Eccho'd, go <hi>Paean</hi> all the time of Fight.</l>
                  <l>Hartning <hi>Apollo,</hi> who to let him know</l>
                  <l>The ſtrength and ſureneſs of his well bent Bow,</l>
                  <l>From out his Quiver took that fatal Dart,</l>
                  <l>VVhich forc'd its Lodging in the Monſters heart.</l>
                  <l>Thus fell great <hi>Typhon,</hi> and this VVar b'ing done,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> Marry'd, and begot a Son,</l>
                  <l>Named him <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> whom he</l>
                  <l>Committed to the <hi>Centaurs</hi> Coſtodie.</l>
                  <l>I'th helpful Art of Phyſick to be train'd;</l>
                  <l>VVhere in ſuch ſtrange Proficiency he gain'd,</l>
                  <l>That both by all at home, and thoſe abroad,</l>
                  <l>That were Phyſitians, he was thought a God.</l>
                  <l>Him <hi>Jove</hi> with Thunderbolts deſtroy'd, becauſe</l>
                  <l>He from the Dead, <hi>Hypolitus</hi> did raiſe;</l>
                  <l>VVhom by his Charriot horſes <hi>Jove</hi> had will'd,</l>
                  <l>Firſt to be drag'd about, and after Kil'd.</l>
                  <l>Enrag'd <hi>Apollo</hi> on the Cyclops flew,</l>
                  <l>VVhom cauſe they made thoſe Thunderbolts, he ſlew.</l>
                  <l>Leaving great <hi>Jupiter</hi> at Forge, no hands</l>
                  <l>To work him bolts, to ſerve his dire commands.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99965:27"/>
                  <l>The mighty Grandfather enrag'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>His Servants thus deſtroy'd, reſolv'd to be</l>
                  <l>Reveng'd, for the affront his Son had giv'n,</l>
                  <l>Whom for a time he Baniſh'd out of Heav'n;</l>
                  <l>Forc'd him ſeek a Living 'mongſt the Rocks,</l>
                  <l>And afterward to feed <hi>Admeta</hi>'s Flocks;</l>
                  <l>In which imploy, ſo bravely he behav'd</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, that all the Neighbouring Shepherds crav'd</l>
                  <l>His Pleaſing friendſhip. Graceful was his Men,</l>
                  <l>Softer then Down his words, his thoughts ſublime,</l>
                  <l>Which in Extemp'ry Eclogues came ſo free,</l>
                  <l>Gods might have Patroniz'd his Poetrie;</l>
                  <l>And barren ſtrands before their Heav'n Eſteem,</l>
                  <l>So that they might have been but prais'd by him.</l>
                  <l>The Ruſtick Shepherds who did rudely roar,</l>
                  <l>By him reclaim'd were, and would baul no more;</l>
                  <l>But practiſing his ſweet Authentick Notes,</l>
                  <l>Unpriſon'd Muſick from their Warbling Throats.</l>
                  <l>To ev'ry Ode, he ſet a Tune a part,</l>
                  <l>On purpoſe to betray ſome Virgins heart;</l>
                  <l>Who as ſhe trickt up to have caught his come,</l>
                  <l>Without her own was forc'd 't go ſighing home.</l>
                  <l>So much reſpect the Nimphs and Shepherds ow'd,</l>
                  <l>That as a God, to him they Kneel'd and Bow'd;</l>
                  <l>To him they ſung, and did each other prize,</l>
                  <l>According as their Notes came neareſt his:</l>
                  <l>But yet for all <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Wiſdom, he</l>
                  <l>Could find no fence 'gainſt Loves Artillerie:</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99965:27"/>
                  <l>The Charming Beauties of fair <hi>Daphne</hi>'s eyes,</l>
                  <l>For all his Godhead did his heart ſurprize:</l>
                  <l>Her looks at once ſo modeſt and ſo fair,</l>
                  <l>As if ſhe bid him hope, and then diſpair.</l>
                  <l>This Nimph <hi>Apollo</hi> courted—but in Vain,</l>
                  <l>A Vicious thought ſhe would not entertain:</l>
                  <l>But with ſevere corrections did remove,</l>
                  <l>The urgent Motions of his luſtful Love;</l>
                  <l>At whoſe neglect diſdain'd <hi>Apollo</hi> Mourn'd,</l>
                  <l>And to a Lawrel the fair Maid transform'd:</l>
                  <l>Which done, his time b'ing out, which he ſhould ſtay</l>
                  <l>On Earth, to Heav'n he made his haſty way:</l>
                  <l>From whence each day he doth thoſe beams diſperſe,</l>
                  <l>Which guild the ſurface of our Univerſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:28"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>NEPTUNE</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99965:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Neptune.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>When from the ſumit of ſome towring Rock,</l>
                  <l>Down to thoſe ſurges which thou mak'ſt, I look.</l>
                  <l>Behold th' enraged Ocean fret and foam,</l>
                  <l>And hear her Roar at thy too cruel doom.</l>
                  <l>See waves encounter waves at ſuch a rate,</l>
                  <l>I fear'd their Blows would reach me as I ſate.</l>
                  <l>Then caſting down my diſcontented Eye,</l>
                  <l>The very intrels of deep <hi>Hell</hi> I ſpy,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe dark Bottom by and by ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Such Clouds of waves as threatn'd all the Skys.</l>
                  <l>And Rools of Floods in true gradations ſent,</l>
                  <l>To fall a Deluge on the Continent.</l>
                  <l>Ah Mighty <hi>Neptune</hi> (to my ſelf ſaid I)</l>
                  <l>How 'unfit am I to write thy Hiſtory.</l>
                  <l>When thou ſo lowdly thy own fame doſt raiſe,</l>
                  <l>The humble Poets Drowned in the Noyſe.</l>
                  <l>Yet, though to write thy prays I will not try,</l>
                  <l>I'l give the world thy Geonalogy.</l>
                  <l>To the Immortal Seed of <hi>Saturn,</hi> thou,</l>
                  <l>Thy Watry Kingdom, and thy Life doſt owe.</l>
                  <l>For when thy Father with Paternal care</l>
                  <l>Diſtributed the Earth, the Sea, and Air,</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99965:29"/>
                  <l>Amongſt his Sons, it was his great deſign,</l>
                  <l>That all the watry Empire ſhould be thine;</l>
                  <l>He put a Trydent in thy Princely hand,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew inſtead of Scepter, thy command;</l>
                  <l>And for a Chariot, a vaſt Shell he gave,</l>
                  <l>Pluckt off the Liquid back of ſome rude wave;</l>
                  <l>Thy Coach-Horſes, Sea Monſters were, and Whales,</l>
                  <l>VVhich drew thee gently as ſoft VVeſtern Gales;</l>
                  <l>VVhen they come Sliding o're a Calmy Sea,</l>
                  <l>And leave no frowns nor wrinckles in their way.</l>
                  <l>Thy VVife <hi>Amphytrite</hi> (whoſe ſpreading breadth,</l>
                  <l>Gave her that name becauſe ſhe loves the Earth.)</l>
                  <l>With watry Armes which ſhe does round diſperſe,</l>
                  <l>And bravely ſearches all the Univerſe.</l>
                  <l>Her thou didſt Love, and to thy bed prefer,</l>
                  <l>(The which thou ow'ſt a friendly Dolphin for.</l>
                  <l>VVho on his back did kindly ſave her Life,</l>
                  <l>And gave her to thee for a Virtuous VVife.</l>
                  <l>VVhich Dolphin after to the Skies was born,</l>
                  <l>And turn'd into a Star near <hi>Capricorn.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>After this the rumour of thy Name abroad</l>
                  <l>Did fly, and thou wert thought a mighty God</l>
                  <l>By wretched heathens, who amazed ſtood,</l>
                  <l>To ſee how ſtill thou bind'ſt the Rav'nous Flood;</l>
                  <l>VVhich when by winds into contention born,</l>
                  <l>Thou check'ſt, and mad'ſt it ſorry for the Storm:</l>
                  <l>Nor this alone did'ſt thou, but much beſide,</l>
                  <l>Thou taught'ſt ſucceeding Mankind how to Ride;</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99965:29"/>
                  <l>Striking the Teeming Earth with ſuch a force,</l>
                  <l>That at thy pleaſure out there Leapt a horſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich thou couldſt Check and Curb, command with Eaſe,</l>
                  <l>And make obedient as the calmy Seas.</l>
                  <l>This thou didſt do, and from the Earth didſt bring,</l>
                  <l>A ſtately Steed at <hi>Athens</hi> Chriſtening:</l>
                  <l>VVhen great <hi>Minerva</hi> and thy ſelf did ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſhould that Famous Citys Title give;</l>
                  <l>Then thou wer't mighty <hi>Neptune;</hi> but alaſs,</l>
                  <l>Thy growing fame ſuſtain'd a ſad decreaſe;</l>
                  <l>VVhen thou, too proud of thy vaſt pow'r, didſt raiſe</l>
                  <l>A hear'd of lean Sectarians, to blaze</l>
                  <l>Abroad the vices of great <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To whoſe great pow'r thou didſt thy own prefer,</l>
                  <l>But found'ſt thy ſelf deceiv'd, when after driv'n,</l>
                  <l>By his Victorious Army out of Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>And forc'd on Earth a wandring Life to live,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the barren woods, where thou didſt ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>VVith anxious labour and with ſweaty brow,</l>
                  <l>For lives neceſſities (as we do now)</l>
                  <l>At length no longer able to Endure,</l>
                  <l>The faint ſubſiſtance there thou didſt procure.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Lemadon</hi> thou took'ſt thy haſty way,</l>
                  <l>In hopes to help him build renowned <hi>Troy:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But he reſponding thy deſire with ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>To lonely woods again thou didſt return,</l>
                  <l>And there in after times begat'ſt a Race</l>
                  <l>Of Monſtrous Trytons, only Men I'th Face:</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99965:30"/>
                  <l>But from the Girdle downward, to the Toe,</l>
                  <l>Were perfect Dolphins, theſe were wont to go</l>
                  <l>With certain ſhells, which made a pleaſant ſound</l>
                  <l>Before him, as he walkt the Wood a round.</l>
                  <l>But in ſucceeding time, when Infant <hi>Room,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had heard that <hi>Neptune</hi> to their world was come;</l>
                  <l>And well conſidering all their Care and Coſt</l>
                  <l>To Build that City, threatned to be loſt,</l>
                  <l>For want of that fair Sex which Chiefly be,</l>
                  <l>The Ground or baſis of Poſteritie.</l>
                  <l>They went to <hi>Neptune,</hi> and to him complain'd</l>
                  <l>Of that ſtrange Famin they had long ſuſtain'd;</l>
                  <l>Told him their caſe, how they were like to be</l>
                  <l>For want of <hi>Heirs,</hi> forgot to Memorie.</l>
                  <l>To let 'em know he once had been a God,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neptune</hi> return'd their homage with a Nod;</l>
                  <l>And when within himſelf had paus'd a while,</l>
                  <l>Return them this as ſacred Oracle.</l>
                  <l>To the <hi>Sabinian</hi> Plains, your Roman games</l>
                  <l>Will eaſily entice the <hi>Sabine</hi> Dames.</l>
                  <l>Who with their Daughters Joyfully will come,</l>
                  <l>To ſee brave Actions by the <hi>Romans</hi> done.</l>
                  <l>Then in the midſt or Centre of your Mirth,</l>
                  <l>When you have ſeen a now of young ones forth.</l>
                  <l>See that each <hi>Roman</hi> on the <hi>Sabines</hi> Runs,</l>
                  <l>Seaſe them for VVives, and ſo beget ye Sons.</l>
                  <l>After from's billows <hi>London Neptune</hi> ſpide,</l>
                  <l>Brought proudly thither by a high Spring-tide.</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99965:30"/>
                  <l>As through a floating VVood he ſtear'd along,</l>
                  <l>And Dancing Caſtles cluſter'd in a throng.</l>
                  <l>VVhen he beheld a mighty bridg give Law</l>
                  <l>Unto his ſurges, and their fury Aw.</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſuch a ſhelf of Cataracts did roar,</l>
                  <l>As if the Thames with Nice had chang'd her Shoar.</l>
                  <l>VVhen he ſuch Maſſy walls, with Tow'rs did Eye,</l>
                  <l>Such Poſts, ſuch Irons, on his back to lye.</l>
                  <l>VVhen the <hi>Caerulian</hi> God theſe things ſurvey'd,</l>
                  <l>He ſhook his Trydent, and Aſtoniſht ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Let the whole Earth now all her wonders Count,</l>
                  <l>This Bridg of wonders is the Paramount.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:31"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>MERCURIE</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99965:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Mercury.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OFt has my pondering Muſe with labouring thought</l>
                  <l>Urg'd me to write, when to my view was brought</l>
                  <l>The Drifts and Errors of miſtaken men,</l>
                  <l>VVho to the common Herd would <hi>Cato</hi>'s ſeem:</l>
                  <l>But to the learn'd and wiſe are nothing leſs,</l>
                  <l>Then Retrograders from true happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Oft in an uncooth <hi>Grove,</hi> from clamour free,</l>
                  <l>None but my Muſe to bare me Companie,</l>
                  <l>I've worn out Ev'nings as I ſighing ſat,</l>
                  <l>Thinking on all the various hits of Fate:</l>
                  <l>Revolving in my mind with no ſmall grief,</l>
                  <l>The irkſome fooleries of humane life.</l>
                  <l>Ah! give me Pen, ſaid I, for now I'm forc'd</l>
                  <l>To write, or elſe my labouring Soul will burſt.</l>
                  <l>Theſe thoughts the conclave of my mind ſo fill,</l>
                  <l>That nothing can unlade it but my Quill:</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a Rapture, and in ſuch a ſtrain,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Mercurie</hi> let me thy Fame proclaim.</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99965:32"/>
                  <l>Thou moſt renowned God, as well for birth,</l>
                  <l>As Ingennitie; whoſe ſacred worth,</l>
                  <l>And great eſteem, the other Gods declare,</l>
                  <l>By thoſe great Offices which they confer</l>
                  <l>On the great <hi>Atlas</hi> Grand-Child, when vaſt bones,</l>
                  <l>Cover'd with Moſs, and cruſted o're with ſtones.</l>
                  <l>Up to a mighty bulk do ſhouldering riſe,</l>
                  <l>And bare the ponderous burden of the Skys.</l>
                  <l>He with one only Daughter being bleſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maia</hi> by name, who as ſhe took her Reſt,</l>
                  <l>Slumbring on top of Mount <hi>Cylene</hi>'s hill,</l>
                  <l>Perceiv'd her Royal VVomb begin to fill.</l>
                  <l>Her body Barniſh, ſo that out of hand,</l>
                  <l>VVith thy great birth ſhe bleſt th' <hi>Arcadean</hi> Land.</l>
                  <l>The Morning of thy Life in ſilence waſted,</l>
                  <l>Thy forward genius to Diſcretion haſted;</l>
                  <l>VVhich the diſcerning Heav'ns did ſo prefer,</l>
                  <l>They all proclaim'd thee their Embaſſador.</l>
                  <l>VVings to thy tender hands and heels they tyd,</l>
                  <l>That thou at their commands might'ſt ſwiftly glide</l>
                  <l>Through Liquid Floods, or cut the ſofter Air,</l>
                  <l>And in a trice to Heav'n again Repair,</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99965:32"/>
                  <l>Leaving no ſign or Trach behind the ſeen,</l>
                  <l>How thou had'ſt gon, or whither thou hadſt been.</l>
                  <l>A pair of Serpents which did peace portend,</l>
                  <l>Twiſting about a Rod held in thy hand;</l>
                  <l>By their ſo mild imbraces did proclaim,</l>
                  <l>That unity which thou wouldſt fain maintain.</l>
                  <l>Nor doſt thou only Sea and Air inſeſt,</l>
                  <l>But mak'ſt thy way to every humane breſt;</l>
                  <l>Which thou imploy'ſt in chalking out new draughts</l>
                  <l>Of freſh <hi>Idea</hi>'s, and of unborn thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Which by thy inquiſition there doſt find,</l>
                  <l>Lodg'd in ſome duskiſh corner of the mind.</l>
                  <l>Theſe thou inform, and Method put'ſt together,</l>
                  <l>Till well conceiv'd, thou mak'ſt the Tongue deliver.</l>
                  <l>But when th' immortal Soul of Man grows weary,</l>
                  <l>And in the body will no longer tarry,</l>
                  <l>It was thy Office <hi>(Mercury!)</hi> to come</l>
                  <l>And hand her kindly to <hi>Elyzium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where when the Soul in Melancholy Groves,</l>
                  <l>(The dark retriments of deceaſed Loves)</l>
                  <l>Had wearied out a year or two in plaint</l>
                  <l>Of its obſcurity, and cloſe reſtraint.</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99965:33"/>
                  <l>Thou like a mighty all-commanding God,</l>
                  <l>By vertue of thy never failing Rod,</l>
                  <l>VVouldſt beckon from that <hi>Hypocondriack</hi> Bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And force 'em to a <hi>Metempſucoſis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The jolly Deities in former time,</l>
                  <l>Rais'd by the Spirits of <hi>Ambroſian</hi> Wine;</l>
                  <l>And ſprightly <hi>Necter</hi> at a Feaſt brought forth,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe to cellebrate ſome Goddeſs birth;</l>
                  <l>With which, in rouſing bouls, they wou'd Confound</l>
                  <l>Their ſences, till they thought the Heav'ns turn'd roun</l>
                  <l>Then like ſome Bloated <hi>Bully,</hi> who hath ſat</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Bacchus</hi> gets poſſeſſion of his Pate:</l>
                  <l>And Landlord like, with an Ejective Writ,</l>
                  <l>Turns out the little Rubbiſh of his VVit;</l>
                  <l>Placing ſuch ſumes inſtead, as naught diſpence,</l>
                  <l>But thoſe curſt Plagues deſire and Impotence.</l>
                  <l>Frought with them both, he tumbles up and down,</l>
                  <l>Swears he will Hector all the trembling Town;</l>
                  <l>Spare neither Man nor VVoman he can catch,</l>
                  <l>Nor leave his VVench for Cunſtable nor VVatch.</l>
                  <l>But if they oppoſe ſuch Airy ſreaks as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt the brains of wandring Deities.</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99965:33"/>
                  <l>VVhen warm'd with VVine from Heav'n they us'd to Rove</l>
                  <l>To Cool themſelves in ſome <hi>Terenian</hi> Grove.</l>
                  <l>Bleſt by the happy Furniture of Beautious Maids,</l>
                  <l>VVho with loud Shrieks invoke their Shepherds Aids,</l>
                  <l>But all in vain, each <hi>God</hi> his Love will Feaſt</l>
                  <l>In his own ſhape, or for that Love turn beaſt.</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Bird,</hi> or <hi>Tree,</hi> or golden ſhow'r,</l>
                  <l>Or any thing to reap the Virgins Flow'r.</l>
                  <l>Once when the wanton <hi>Gods</hi> had revel'd thus,</l>
                  <l>They needs would go to viſit <hi>Tantalus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whoſe empty board</l>
                  <l>A well becoming Feaſt could not afford</l>
                  <l>For ſuch unuſual Strangers, wherefore he,</l>
                  <l>Urg'd thereto by meer neceſſitie,</l>
                  <l>VVith hands inhumane, caus'd his Son to bleed,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Limbs b'ing neatly Haſht and Fygazeed;</l>
                  <l>In mighty Diſhes to the board were brought</l>
                  <l>By him, who kindly all the <hi>Gods</hi> beſought</l>
                  <l>I' accept that little Treat, which humbly ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>In part, the ſign of his Large gratitude.</l>
                  <l>Th' inraged Deities affronted all,</l>
                  <l>To ſee an Act ſo Dam'd unnatural.</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99965:34"/>
                  <l>Firſt lay'd their heads together, to invent</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Tantolus</hi> befiting Puniſhment;</l>
                  <l>And then intreated <hi>Mercury</hi> to go</l>
                  <l>Down to the dwellings of the Dead below.</l>
                  <l>The Soul of Murder'd <hi>Pelops</hi> to Redeem,</l>
                  <l>And inſtantly to bring him back to them.</l>
                  <l>Which Mighty <hi>Mercury</hi> alone could do,</l>
                  <l>Who adventrouſly among the Damned flew;</l>
                  <l>And by his power, regain'd that Soul from Hell,</l>
                  <l>Which otherwiſe had been impoſſible.</l>
                  <l>Thus, or through Heav'n or Hell, where e're he wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>This mighty God was ſtill Omnipotent.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:34"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:35"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>DIANA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99965:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Diana.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Chaſt <hi>Diana</hi> as before was ſed,</l>
                  <l>Was the Fair Iſſue of <hi>Latona</hi>'s Bed.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Jupiter</hi> enrag'd at's ſcolding wife,</l>
                  <l>Left her to lead a rambling Bully's Life.</l>
                  <l>Meeting bechance this fair complying Mai'd,</l>
                  <l>VVhom eaſily he to his Bed betray'd.</l>
                  <l>VVith Heav'nly Seed he fil'd her until'd VVomb,</l>
                  <l>From which in 10 Moneths time <hi>Diana</hi> ſprung.</l>
                  <l>The Glittering <hi>Morning</hi> of whoſe Age was ſpent</l>
                  <l>In rural Sports; whereby a calm content</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe enjoy'd in that ſerene retreat,</l>
                  <l>She might have gueſt the tortures of the Great.</l>
                  <l>But after ſhe to Riper Years was grown,</l>
                  <l>And fil'd the world with her deſerv'd renown.</l>
                  <l>VVhich kindly added to her infant Name,</l>
                  <l>A trine of Titles to Enhance her Fame.</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99965:36"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luna</hi> thy cal'd her as belong'd to Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>But hear on Earth another Name was giv'n.</l>
                  <l>[Fair <hi>Cynthia</hi>] who amongſt the woods did dwell,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Proſerpina</hi> when ſhe went to Hell.</l>
                  <l>Calm was the Seria's of her happy Life,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt freed from greatneſs, void of Care and Strife</l>
                  <l>And fell ambition; 'bout the Groves ſhe walkt,</l>
                  <l>And oft of <hi>Heav'n,</hi> and oft of <hi>Love</hi> ſhe talkt.</l>
                  <l>To a fair Train of 60. Virgins ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Had to attend her in that privacie;</l>
                  <l>VVho every one officiouſly did wait</l>
                  <l>On her ſoft words, as th' Oracle of fate.</l>
                  <l>With Bow in hand, and Quiver by her ſide,</l>
                  <l>She walkt Commandreſs of that Beautious Tribe,</l>
                  <l>Beating each Thicket as they March'd to find,</l>
                  <l>A game proportion'd to her Noble Mind.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes a Royal Stag they gently Rouſe,</l>
                  <l>As he was browſing in his ſhady houſe;</l>
                  <l>VVho unacquainted with ſuch beauteous Foes,</l>
                  <l>Stretches and looks about him as he goes;</l>
                  <l>At length being Charm'd—Stands gazing at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt by her Treacherous Dart he falls and Dyes.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99965:36"/>
                  <l>A ſilly Pheaſant next (perhaps) they Pearch</l>
                  <l>On an adjacent Tree within their Reach;</l>
                  <l>Who from his ſecure bough does leering ſpy,</l>
                  <l>Unuſual Glories in <hi>Dyana</hi>'s Eye;</l>
                  <l>Gazing with ſuch intentneſs as did ſeem,</l>
                  <l>He aim'd at her direct as ſhe at him;</l>
                  <l>Till by an Arrow from her Fatal Sheath,</l>
                  <l>She ſends him tidings of untimely Death.</l>
                  <l>Who not unkindly does the Meſſage greet,</l>
                  <l>But trembling falls obedient at her feet.</l>
                  <l>The Timerous Hare at Melancholy Quat,</l>
                  <l>From her fair hands receiv'd unhappy Fate.</l>
                  <l>And Paſſant Birds ſo ſuddenly do dye</l>
                  <l>By her ſwift ſhaft, t'would puzle one to ſpy</l>
                  <l>VVhether her Arrow kil'd them, or her Eye.</l>
                  <l>In fine, ſhe was the only Goddeſs of the VVood,</l>
                  <l>VVho Hunting, Hawking, Shooting underſtood:</l>
                  <l>But yet ſo modeſt, careful, and ſo Shy,</l>
                  <l>To keep unblemiſht her Virginity.</l>
                  <l>That bold <hi>Acteon,</hi> as he gazing ſtood,</l>
                  <l>To ſee her <hi>Bathing</hi> in a Neighbouring Flood;</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt lib'rally without reſerve or fear,</l>
                  <l>She openly expos'd her <hi>Beauties</hi> there</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99965:37"/>
                  <l>So long, till caſting up her Curious Eye,</l>
                  <l>Upon a Neighbouring bank, ſhe might Eſpy</l>
                  <l>The Raſh beholder of her Stoln receſs,</l>
                  <l>VVho for that rude intrution of his,</l>
                  <l>She chang'd into a Stags Similitude,</l>
                  <l>VVhom his miſtaken Dogs with haſt Perſu'd.</l>
                  <l>Through buſhes, brambles, over hills and downs,</l>
                  <l>Through watry Thickets, &amp; Damp Marſhy Grounds</l>
                  <l>Deaf to his Noys, though Name by Name he calls,</l>
                  <l>Each heedleſs Hound who minds not what he bauls;</l>
                  <l>But eagerly their wearyed game perſue,</l>
                  <l>On whom o're tane, ſo furiouſly they flew</l>
                  <l>VVith open Mouth, tearing him Limb from Limb,</l>
                  <l>That there the ſad ſpectator might have ſeen,</l>
                  <l>By a Revenge ſo cruel and ſo Strickt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhe on poor <hi>Acteon</hi> did Inflict,</l>
                  <l>That nothing was ſo pretious or ſo dear,</l>
                  <l>As an unſpoted Modeſty to her.</l>
                  <l>Admireing <hi>Epheſus</hi> had hardly heard</l>
                  <l>The rumour of her Fame, but up they rear'd</l>
                  <l>A Stately Temple, where with Rev'rence ſhe</l>
                  <l>VVas to be worſhipt as their Deitie.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99965:37"/>
                  <l>No Beardleſs Prieſts, her Grandure cou'd ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>But Antient, Grave, Religious, and Wiſe;</l>
                  <l>Such whoſe deportments and aſpects might be</l>
                  <l>A grace to Burniſh her Divinitie.</l>
                  <l>Nor common Sacrifice would ſerve the turn,</l>
                  <l>But humane Fleſh muſt on her Alters burn.</l>
                  <l>I fear <hi>Precarious Scythians</hi> meant to have</l>
                  <l>The mighty Boons which they were us'd to crave.</l>
                  <l>A helpleſs Greek fal'n on the <hi>Scythian</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Cut into Quarters, Pickel'd in his Gore.</l>
                  <l>The humble <hi>Tauris</hi> muſt ſurely bring,</l>
                  <l>If they would pleaſe her with an offering.</l>
                  <l>Of which a fam'd Hiſtorian has writ,</l>
                  <l>A pleaſant ſtory full of <hi>Blood</hi> and wit.</l>
                  <l>When wild <hi>Oreſtes</hi> had his Mother kild,</l>
                  <l>The Act his Conſcience with ſuch horror fil'd,</l>
                  <l>That he grew reſtleſs, and diſpair'd to find</l>
                  <l>Means to aſwage the terror of his mind:</l>
                  <l>But b'ing adviz'd by own who lov'd him well,</l>
                  <l>To go ask Councel of the Oracle.</l>
                  <l>It ſtraight commanded, he ſhould <hi>Greece</hi> forſake,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Scythia Taurica</hi> with ſpeed attacque;</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99965:38"/>
                  <l>Where near the Shore, in an adjacent Wood,</l>
                  <l>The Famous Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> ſtood;</l>
                  <l>In it her Statue, which if he by ſlight,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt all lay ſlumbring in the Armes of Night,</l>
                  <l>Could but convey unto the <hi>Greecian</hi>-ſhore,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Lunacie</hi> ſhould trouble him no more.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oreſtes</hi> Ships, and reacht the <hi>Scythian</hi> Land,</l>
                  <l>Where he had ſcarcely quit him of the Sand;</l>
                  <l>But he was Seas'd on by a Crew of Spyes,</l>
                  <l>And brought to <hi>Taurica</hi> for Sacrifice:</l>
                  <l>And that ſame Night before he was to dye,</l>
                  <l>Put into <hi>Ephigenias</hi> Cuſtody.</l>
                  <l>The Prieſts of <hi>Diana,</hi> whoſe looſe Eye,</l>
                  <l>Beholding bound <hi>Oreſtes</hi> Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>The true proportion of each brawny Limb,</l>
                  <l>His ſpreading Shoulders and Majeſtick Meen—</l>
                  <l>She him within her ſelf began to prize,</l>
                  <l>Fitter for Loves, than <hi>D'ana</hi>'s Sacrifice;</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſoon as the accute <hi>Oreſtes</hi> knew,</l>
                  <l>He got both Mayden-head and Statue too.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:38"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:39"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>VENUS</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99965:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Venus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>When impious <hi>Saturn</hi> harbour'd in his Breaſt</l>
                  <l>A Jealoſie of being diſpoſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of th' long'd for Glory of his Fathers Crown,</l>
                  <l>By the Intruſion of another Son.</l>
                  <l>VVith Graceleſs Syth he to his Father ran,</l>
                  <l>And rob'd him of that part which term'd him Man.</l>
                  <l>VVhich when diſſected from his body, he</l>
                  <l>Careleſly flung into the Foaming Sea.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Neptune</hi> viewing, with indulgent Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Strove to preſerve the ſacred Privaties.</l>
                  <l>VVhich firſt he Mantled in a bed of Foam,</l>
                  <l>VVhere agitating VVaves were us'd to come;</l>
                  <l>And by their Active Motion heat beget,</l>
                  <l>Theſe when with drops of Viril blood they met,</l>
                  <l>Comixt and Curdl'd, then congeal'd to form,</l>
                  <l>And afterwards enliven'd by a Storm;</l>
                  <l>VVhich from it's Neſt the Beautious ſubſtance tore</l>
                  <l>And left an Amorous <hi>Venus</hi> on the Shore;</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99965:40"/>
                  <l>VVhoſe pearleſs Charms did neighbouring Shepherds move</l>
                  <l>VVith Flow'rs to Crown her Deitie of Love;</l>
                  <l>To whom each Evening every Nymph reſorts,</l>
                  <l>As the ſole Goddeſs of their wanton Sports.</l>
                  <l>And if at any time, ſhe chanc'd to be</l>
                  <l>Too Laviſh in her Shepherds Companie,</l>
                  <l>Offer'd in ſacrifice a Letcherous Dove,</l>
                  <l>Serv'd to attone the rudeneſs of her Love.</l>
                  <l>Drawn by Lacivious Birds, in Chariot ſhe</l>
                  <l>Tryumphant Rod through famous <hi>Chythere:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſtately <hi>Amathus,</hi> which ſhe inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To wanton Sports and Levity of mind,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Paphos</hi> and the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Iſſands rung,</l>
                  <l>VVith lowd Encomiums to Fair <hi>Venus</hi> Sung;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe boundleſs beauties often did ſurprize</l>
                  <l>The Guardleſs Souls of Curious Deities.</l>
                  <l>VVho as they prying came her <hi>Beams</hi> to ſpy,</l>
                  <l>Their hearts were intercepted by her Eye.</l>
                  <l>But as to other Gods, whoſe wiſer Care,</l>
                  <l>Did court her Smiles, ſhe was not ſo ſevere:</l>
                  <l>For when plump <hi>Bacchus</hi> was to <hi>India</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>In his Return from that rich Continent.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:99965:40"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> hot Love could brook no longer ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But up ſhe got and met him half the way;</l>
                  <l>Compos'd a Garland of the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Roſe,</l>
                  <l>VVherewith ſhe kindly Crown'd his ſtruting <hi>Brows;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Kiſt her Plump Cheeks, and with ſoft ſighs did move</l>
                  <l>The Jolly <hi>God,</hi> by wanton ſigns, to Love —</l>
                  <l>He who no dull ingratitude did know,</l>
                  <l>(As in this kind few <hi>Bacchanalians</hi> do)</l>
                  <l>In juſt requital of ſo kind a deed,</l>
                  <l>Impregnated her Womb with Heav'nly Seed;</l>
                  <l>VVhich jealous <hi>Juno</hi> then in heat of Youth,</l>
                  <l>Thinking all loſt that fell beſides her Mouth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bewitch'd,</hi> before it any ſhape did know,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt it was Curdling into <hi>Embrio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That with contempt ſhe might the Parents ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>VVhen the ill ſhap'd <hi>Pryapus</hi> was <hi>Born;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhoſe crooked form put <hi>Venus</hi> in a fright,</l>
                  <l>VVho baniſht him for ever from her ſight.</l>
                  <l>Scarce was ſhe from this ponderous burden freed,</l>
                  <l>But with another <hi>God</hi> ſhe had agreed.</l>
                  <l>Who by her Captivating beams was led,</l>
                  <l>To ſeek the Pleaſures of her happy bed.</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99965:41"/>
                  <l>The wanton <hi>Intrigue</hi> did ſo well ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>That from their cloſe imbraces did proceed</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Hymenaeus,</hi> who did after prove</l>
                  <l>The only God of <hi>Conjugated</hi> Love.</l>
                  <l>The graces were her Daughters too, whom ſhe</l>
                  <l>Always enjoyn'd to keep her Companie:</l>
                  <l>And Hood-winckt <hi>Cupid,</hi> who could never ſee,</l>
                  <l>The dire affects of his Artillerie.</l>
                  <l>That little Boy with wings upon his back,</l>
                  <l>And Quiver by his ſide, which ne're did lack,</l>
                  <l>Show'rs of burning Arrows to enflame,</l>
                  <l>VVith rageing Love, the hearts wherein they came.</l>
                  <l>This wanton Youth by Poets too is ſed,</l>
                  <l>To be oblieg'd for Life to <hi>Venus</hi>'s bed:</l>
                  <l>And bold <hi>Aeneas</hi> he, whoſe pious Care,</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Trojon</hi> flames did old <hi>Anchyſes</hi> bear</l>
                  <l>Upon his back, whilſt in his Face were ſent,</l>
                  <l>Affrontive flaſhes every ſtep he went.</l>
                  <l>He of whoſe Virtue Lofty <hi>Virgil</hi> Sung</l>
                  <l>So Low'd, that all the VVorld has Rung</l>
                  <l>VVith the Inchanting Noyſe of his ſweet Fame,</l>
                  <l>VVhich into every petty Iſland came;</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99965:41"/>
                  <l>And ne're will be extinguiſht, till the VVorld,</l>
                  <l>Into its firſt obſcurity be hurl'd.</l>
                  <l>He who in all this fame and ſplendour Liv'd,</l>
                  <l>Owns from fair <hi>Venus</hi> bed to be deriv'd.</l>
                  <l>Thus looſely <hi>Venus</hi> Liv'd, Ranging abroad,</l>
                  <l>Free to th' imbraces of each willing God;</l>
                  <l>VVho in her Armes were frequently delighted,</l>
                  <l>So oft that ſhe at length by all was ſlighted.</l>
                  <l>Excepting <hi>Vulcan,</hi> who durſt never be</l>
                  <l>So impudent, to prove her Levitie.</l>
                  <l>This baſhful homely God, had often ſed,</l>
                  <l>He could have wiſht her in his ſooty <hi>Bed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thither had invited her, but that</l>
                  <l>His Limping Leg was it ſhe mutter'd at</l>
                  <l>So oft to other Gods, that he diſpair'd</l>
                  <l>Of having any light Petition heard.</l>
                  <l>VVherefore one ev'ning as from Hell he came,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sweating,</hi> and <hi>Panting, Collowy</hi> and <hi>Lame:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thinking to cool him on the <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>He ſaw bright <hi>Venus,</hi> whom he did implore.</l>
                  <l>(After had made from her a ſmall retreat,</l>
                  <l>To cleer his grymed Chops of foot and ſweat,)</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99965:42"/>
                  <l>At once to ſave his Longing and his Life,</l>
                  <l>By a ſubmiſſion to become his Wife.</l>
                  <l>The crafty Beauty, conſcious ſhe had been</l>
                  <l>Too light to keep the other Gods Eſteem.</l>
                  <l>Like a declining Harlot, ſtrove to engage</l>
                  <l>A Fond admirer of her wrinckled Age,</l>
                  <l>Admitted ſilly <hi>Vulcan</hi> to her Bed,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeking for a long loſt Maiden-Head,</l>
                  <l>Was loaded ſo by other Gods with Scorns,</l>
                  <l>That all the Heav'ns Echo'd <hi>Vulcans</hi> Horns.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:42"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:43"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>PERSEUS</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99965:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Perſeus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen Men, from <hi>Oracles,</hi> the News did bring</l>
                  <l>To Fam'd <hi>Acriſius, Argos</hi> wealthy King;</l>
                  <l>That to a Child his Daughter ſhould give breath,</l>
                  <l>VVho afterward muſt cauſe her Fathers Death:</l>
                  <l>In hopes that rigorous Fortune to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Which Heav'n had threatn'd by a Grand-childs hand;</l>
                  <l>The Young Preſaged Mother, (who as yet,</l>
                  <l>With Man in warm imbraces had not met,</l>
                  <l>Nor the delights of Lovers ever ſought,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs by Proxy of a Dream or thought—)</l>
                  <l>Was by her Fathers harſh Commiſſion ſent</l>
                  <l>To a Tow'r of <hi>Braſs</hi> for cloſe impriſonment;</l>
                  <l>There from the ſight of Man or Child confin'd,</l>
                  <l>To calm the Billows of his fearful mind.</l>
                  <l>Where, by the way, the Reader may behold,</l>
                  <l>How vainly man conteſt with <hi>Heav'n</hi> do's hold!</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99965:44"/>
                  <l>VVhat little pains it takes to undermine</l>
                  <l>The ſhallow projects of our deep'ſt Deſign!</l>
                  <l>What matters all our Plots and Cares, alas!</l>
                  <l>What ſignifies a Tow'r of Maſſy Braſs?</l>
                  <l>Tho mighty <hi>Alps</hi> ſhould to thoſe Walls condence,</l>
                  <l>They'd ſeem but <hi>Nets</hi> to piercing <hi>Providence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which does through Pores, as ſwift as Maſhes fly,</l>
                  <l>Till it attains it's wiſht Ubiquity.</l>
                  <l>Reſembling Recreation we procure,</l>
                  <l>Pond'ring the Reaſons of the Men ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Who ſit in their contrivances ſo cloſe,</l>
                  <l>As if no other Fate could interpoſe:</l>
                  <l>Whom oft we ſee by that ſame <hi>Clue</hi> th'ave ſpun,</l>
                  <l>Run tumbling head-long to the fate they'd ſhun!</l>
                  <l>Thus by his care, <hi>Acriſius</hi> did but fly</l>
                  <l>The nearer way, to meet his deſtiny;</l>
                  <l>Which like a Thief perhaps, had by him paſt,</l>
                  <l>But that it Judg'd the Booty by its haſt.</l>
                  <l>For mighty <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whoſe tender Ear</l>
                  <l>VVas always open to a Virgins Pray'r;</l>
                  <l>Could by his high Prerogative invade</l>
                  <l>The ſad complaints which Fair <hi>Danae</hi> made.</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99965:44"/>
                  <l>He heard her Sigh, and ſaw her weep and vex,</l>
                  <l>To be deny'd the Freedom of her Sex.</l>
                  <l>He daily ſaw her mourn her diſmal Fate,</l>
                  <l>And heard her wiſh—ſhe knew not well for what;</l>
                  <l>But thought he could the right conſtruction find,</l>
                  <l>And ſatisfie her diſcontented Mind;</l>
                  <l>Forcing his paſſage through the Brazen Tower,</l>
                  <l>In her warm Lap he raign'd a Golden Show'r;</l>
                  <l>VVhich ten Months after ſuch rich Fruit did yield,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Perſeus</hi> ſprouted from the Milky Field:</l>
                  <l>VVhom with his Mother, grim <hi>Acriſius</hi> he</l>
                  <l>Lockt in a Cheſt, and threw into the Sea:</l>
                  <l>But wandring Fiſhermen the Cheſt retrieve,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt yet both Child and Mother were alive;</l>
                  <l>In whoſe great looks the honeſt men diſcry,</l>
                  <l>Unuſual ſigns of Sacred <hi>Majeſty:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By which they held themſelves oblig'd to bear</l>
                  <l>Them both to <hi>Seriphus</hi>'s Iſland; where</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Polydectes</hi> largely did engage</l>
                  <l>Them both, till Valiant <hi>Perſeus</hi> came to age.</l>
                  <l>VVho by brave Actions in his Youth, made known</l>
                  <l>That Glory which his riper Years did Crown.</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99965:45"/>
                  <l>His Fame too bulky for this lower world,</l>
                  <l>By Ecchoing Plaudits to the Gods was hurl'd.</l>
                  <l>VVho to divulge, they did his Deeds approve,</l>
                  <l>Sent him ſuch preſents as beſpoke their Love.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerva,</hi> cauſe ſhe would his Valour grace,</l>
                  <l>Kindly oblig'd him with her Looking-glaſs.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mercury,</hi> his liking to declare,</l>
                  <l>Gave him both plumed Wings and Semiter;</l>
                  <l>VVherewith ſo many Battles he obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>That from his Conqueſts <hi>Perſia</hi> ſo was nam'd.</l>
                  <l>His Sinuy Arm the <hi>Nereids</hi> did command,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Andromeda</hi> was Frenchiz'd by his hand.</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſtrange <hi>Sea-Monſters</hi> were deſign'd to Eat</l>
                  <l>The harmleſs Daughter for the Mothers ſake,</l>
                  <l>The horrible <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s crawling Head,</l>
                  <l>VVhere twiſting Serpents every moment bred,</l>
                  <l>VVhich who ſo lookt on, into Stones were ſhrunk.</l>
                  <l>His hand diſſected from the hideous Trunk,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Reeking Blood ingendring with the Earth,</l>
                  <l>Gave winged <hi>Pegaſus</hi> a happy Birth.</l>
                  <l>That mighty Beaſt, which with one lucky ſtrok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>The hidden fount of <hi>Hypocrene</hi> broke;</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99965:45"/>
                  <l>And after that Immortal honour won,</l>
                  <l>In his aſſiſting young <hi>Bellerophon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Againſt <hi>Chimaera;</hi> having done thoſe VVars,</l>
                  <l>He Mounts the Skies, and lodg'd amongſt the Stars.</l>
                  <l>Nor was brave <hi>Perſeus</hi> only Fam'd in VVar,</l>
                  <l>The Sciences his private hours did ſhare;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who were Learn'd, he held in near Eſteem,</l>
                  <l>And came not but with open hand to them.</l>
                  <l>He knew in populous Kingdoms Letters are</l>
                  <l>As requiſit as Inſtruments of VVar;</l>
                  <l>And that thoſe VVars ſucceſs does often Crown,</l>
                  <l>VVhich firſt are well debated by the Gown.</l>
                  <l>VVhen Conqueſt to a Nation Peace does give,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Learning tells the People how to live:</l>
                  <l>VVarns them that Valour which their Foe withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Not to Experience in Domeſtick Blood;</l>
                  <l>But to their callings each Mans Arms reſign</l>
                  <l>As quietly, as no ſuch thing had been.</l>
                  <l>Theſe and more noble Notions did procure</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perſeus</hi> ſo much to favour Literature,</l>
                  <l>That on that celebrated mountains Brow,</l>
                  <l>To which the proudeſt Poets rev'rence owe.</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99965:46"/>
                  <l>[Immortal <hi>Helicon] Perſeus</hi> Erected</l>
                  <l>A famous School, where Youth was well inſtructed</l>
                  <l>In all that Learning which the Gen'rous find</l>
                  <l>Fit to accompliſh an Heroick Mind:</l>
                  <l>For which brave Action (worthy endleſs Praiſe)</l>
                  <l>Antient Poets rais'd him to the Skies.</l>
                  <l>So their Succeſſors would ingrateful be</l>
                  <l>Not to applaud him to Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:46"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:47"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>PAN.</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99965:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Pan.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YE <hi>Hural Gods,</hi> who 'mongſt the Fields reſort,</l>
                  <l>And wiſely ſhun the Buſle of the Court;</l>
                  <l>VVhere dwindled Parts, with diſcontents lie mute,</l>
                  <l>Under the luſtre of a Gaudy ſhute:</l>
                  <l>VVhere words obliging, and ſmiles forc't (to pleaſe)</l>
                  <l>Are but the treacherous minds <hi>Antipodes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And cringes, by <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> proclaim,</l>
                  <l>VVhat you requeſt, you are not like t' obtain.</l>
                  <l>VVhere, though the <hi>Peacock</hi> Treats you with a ſmile,</l>
                  <l>Read but his mind, there's <hi>Dam ye</hi> all the while.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Why does this Credulous half-witted Bubble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With's vain Petition give me thus much trouble.)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>You</hi> the noys of <hi>Courts</hi> diſcreetly ſhun,</l>
                  <l>You hate the <hi>Hums</hi>—and <hi>Buzes</hi>—of the <hi>Town.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere buſy men, like Bees together crowd,</l>
                  <l>And in their Convocations baul ſo loud.</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99965:48"/>
                  <l>(Each ſilly Speaker, fond of what he ſays,)</l>
                  <l>That all the Muſicks drowned in the noiſe.</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt you in gaudy <hi>Lawns</hi> and gilded Fields,</l>
                  <l>Enjoy that ſimple good which Nature yields;</l>
                  <l>Pure and unmixt as it at firſt does come</l>
                  <l>From the vaſt Treas'ry of her Teeming VVomb.</l>
                  <l>As are your Meats, ſo are your Paſtimes free</l>
                  <l>From the ſtrong tatch of Arts Debauchery.</l>
                  <l>The luſt of honour fell Ambition here,</l>
                  <l>Does only in dim Metaphors appear.</l>
                  <l>Pride and Revenge, and ſofter Luxury,</l>
                  <l>Corroding ſorrow, and that Gloomy Fry.</l>
                  <l>Of other Paſſions which infeſt the mind</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe to dangerous greatneſs are inclin'd;</l>
                  <l>To Nymphs and Satyrs, and Field Gods are known,</l>
                  <l>Only by Tracks of Dark Tradition.</l>
                  <l>Their Innocence I envy, and implore</l>
                  <l>From all their Genius's a luſty ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of ſprightly wit, that I thereby may be</l>
                  <l>Aptly accompliſht to diſcourſe of thee</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Pan!</hi> The Fields and VVoods ſole <hi>Emperor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Give me at leaſt a <hi>Sidneys</hi> Soul or more</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99965:48"/>
                  <l>That in an untrod path my Muſe may fly,</l>
                  <l>To give thy Story Immortality.</l>
                  <l>Thou Grand-child to great <hi>Jupiters</hi> ſtrong Brain,</l>
                  <l>From whence thy Father <hi>Mercury</hi> was tane;</l>
                  <l>VVho raviſht with the Beauty of a Maid,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Cruelty his Amorous Suit deny'd;</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd by Subtlety to undermine</l>
                  <l>That Fort which had withſtood Loves Diſcipline:</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſo in Martial, well as Loves affair,</l>
                  <l>VVhen the Beſieg'd unterrified appear;</l>
                  <l>Maugre the fruitleſs onſets of the Foe,</l>
                  <l>VVho from their Canons Fiery blaſts do blow</l>
                  <l>On the Imperious walls, which ſcorn to ſhake,</l>
                  <l>For all the Storms and Batteries they can make.</l>
                  <l>The wiſe Beſieger, who perceives at length,</l>
                  <l>Nothing can be accompliſht by his ſtrength.</l>
                  <l>Cloſe in his <hi>Tent</hi> ſhut up, do's Studying try,</l>
                  <l>To gain by's <hi>Wit,</hi> what <hi>Valour</hi> did deny.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes a Band of ſtouteſt Men he calls,</l>
                  <l>To bid adieu to thoſe unhappy VValls,</l>
                  <l>As if ſome greater buſineſs of import,</l>
                  <l>Call'd their aſſiſtance to a diſtant <hi>Fort.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99965:49"/>
                  <l>Theſe by his Order in a week return</l>
                  <l>VVith the Beſieged's colours, old and worn.</l>
                  <l>And by a feigned Combat with their Friends,</l>
                  <l>Shortly accompliſh their deſired Ends.</l>
                  <l>For the Beſieged, who with Seamens Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Ken at a diſtance ſigns of freſh ſupplies,</l>
                  <l>VVilling to credit what they wiſht to have,</l>
                  <l>Hope for aſſiſtance, where they find a Grave:</l>
                  <l>Haſten their Ruin, more for want of care,</l>
                  <l>Than could their Foe, with all the Toyls of war.</l>
                  <l>And thus did <hi>Mercury,</hi> by cunning Gain,</l>
                  <l>That Virgin <hi>Fort</hi> which he had Storm'd in Vain.</l>
                  <l>VVho hearing all the pleaſure which ſhe took,</l>
                  <l>VVas in attendance of her little Flock,</l>
                  <l>On which ſhe ſeem'd exceſſively to doat.</l>
                  <l>He therefore in the likeneſs of a Goat,</l>
                  <l>VVhich us'd to make a Bolſter of her Thigh,</l>
                  <l>Did do the like; and when he was ſo Nigh—</l>
                  <l>No longer able to refrain, he ran</l>
                  <l>Upon his Bliſs— and ſo begot God <hi>Pan:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So much the Fathers ſhape the Son reſum'd,</l>
                  <l>That Goatiſh Horns his hairy Temples Crown'd.</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99965:49"/>
                  <l>A Rev'rend Beard his pickit Chin adorn'd,</l>
                  <l>His Buttocks ſhaggy, and his Feet were horn'd</l>
                  <l>VVith glittering Hoofs, like <hi>Gum-work</hi> did appear,</l>
                  <l>His feet were cloven as the <hi>Devils</hi> are:</l>
                  <l>The ſtrangeneſs of his Shape made Nymphs admire,</l>
                  <l>And liſtening Satyrs from their Grots retire.</l>
                  <l>The wondering Shepheard on his Thigh ſo ſtrike</l>
                  <l>His Mutton Fiſt, and ſwear by his old <hi>Dike,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In all his Born he never ſaw the like.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Pan,</hi> as he aſſum'd his Fathers ſhape,</l>
                  <l>So did he of his VVit participate.</l>
                  <l>His form was not ſo duskiſh, but was ſeen</l>
                  <l>Through it, that glittering Soul which dwelt within,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe bleſt Effects, the Rural Sports refin'd,</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Satyrs, Nymphs,</hi> and <hi>Shepheards</hi> he inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Poeſie,</hi> the Glory of the Mind.</l>
                  <l>VVhat others with long ſtudious Toyl attain,</l>
                  <l>By Nature flow'd from his capacious Brain;</l>
                  <l>From out his Pipe Muſick diſtill'd as clear,</l>
                  <l>As if he had cond his <hi>Gamuth</hi> forty Year.</l>
                  <l>His daily Practice Judgment did impart,</l>
                  <l>And made him ſo conceited of his Art,</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99965:50"/>
                  <l>That ſwel'd with Pride, he ſo irreverend grows,</l>
                  <l>To ſnatch at Laurels on <hi>Apollo</hi>'s brows:</l>
                  <l>Dares his ſweet Harp, with <hi>Pans</hi> rude Pipe, to try</l>
                  <l>On open Stage, for <hi>Muſicks</hi> Victory.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mydas</hi> was Umpire in the grand Conteſt,</l>
                  <l>To give the Prize to him deſerv'd it beſt.</l>
                  <l>A ſilly Judge <hi>Pan</hi> knew gives moſt applauſe,</l>
                  <l>And beſt ſucceſs to a Reſembling Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſo it prov'd. Him Error did miſguide,</l>
                  <l>To bear the Laurel from <hi>Apollo</hi>'s ſide,</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Mydas</hi> as his due on <hi>Pan</hi> beſtows,</l>
                  <l>And thought he Crown'd the moſt deſerving brows.</l>
                  <l>VVhich injury <hi>Apollo</hi> ſoon repairs,</l>
                  <l>VVho to his <hi>Woodcocks Brains</hi> ſent <hi>Aſses Ears.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:50"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:51"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>BACCHUS</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99965:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Bacchus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tis not the meaneſt Title did Adorn</l>
                  <l>Renowned <hi>Thebes,</hi> that <hi>Bacchus</hi> there was born;</l>
                  <l>That Jolly <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Fame was after hurl'd</l>
                  <l>Through every corner of this Lower world.</l>
                  <l>Ne're by <hi>Oblivions</hi> cloud to be o're caſt,</l>
                  <l>So'long as <hi>Men,</hi> or <hi>Grapes,</hi> or <hi>Wines</hi> do laſt:</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Sols</hi> refulgent <hi>Beams</hi> from far appear,</l>
                  <l>Or mirth inhabits in this <hi>Hemeſphere.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So long as clambering <hi>Vines</hi> do upward thrive,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Men</hi> know how the happieſt way to live</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Bacchanalian</hi> Antidotes, to drive</l>
                  <l>From their depreſſed Souls corroding grief,</l>
                  <l>VVhich every humane Error home does preſs,</l>
                  <l>And worm-like gnaws our goard of Happineſs.</l>
                  <l>So long may <hi>Jupiter</hi> expect his Son,</l>
                  <l>Free from the Grave of dark <hi>Oblivion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99965:52"/>
                  <l>Or the more fierce Attaques of <hi>Hungry</hi> Time</l>
                  <l>Will live, and by the World be thought <hi>Divine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor need his Fair, though hapleſs <hi>Mother</hi> fear,</l>
                  <l>But by his means to be remember'd here;</l>
                  <l>Though of her <hi>Life</hi> revengeful <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> did</l>
                  <l>By craft cut off the unextended <hi>Thred.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Stories</hi> thus, <hi>Juno,</hi> who ne're at Peace</l>
                  <l>With any of her Husbands <hi>Miſtreſses,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In an old <hi>Matrons</hi> habit came diſguiz'd</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Semele,</hi> whom ſlily ſhee adviz'd</l>
                  <l>As ſhee her Intereſt or <hi>Honour</hi> priz'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſuffer <hi>Jupiters</hi> moſt cloſe Imbrace</l>
                  <l>VVhen Arm'd with Thunder, as before he was.</l>
                  <l>When firſt he enter'd <hi>Juno</hi>'s Virgins Bed,</l>
                  <l>And Crown'd his Labours with her Maiden-head,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Semele</hi> conſented to the fault,</l>
                  <l>But b'ing too weak to bare the fierce aſſault,</l>
                  <l>Was inth' Incounter by his <hi>Thunder</hi> Kil'd,</l>
                  <l>Juſt as her Virgin <hi>Womb</hi> by him was fil'd.</l>
                  <l>E're from the Boyſterous <hi>God</hi> he could retire,</l>
                  <l>(According to Vext <hi>Juno</hi>'s wiſht deſire;)</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:99965:52"/>
                  <l>But <hi>Jupiter</hi> with Tears her Death bemoan'd,</l>
                  <l>And after he a while had ſigh'd and groan'd,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch Exceſs, as did to pitty move</l>
                  <l>The other <hi>Gods</hi> for his unhappy <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He piouſly beſtow'd his <hi>God-like</hi> care,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Embroy'd Infant</hi> in her <hi>Womb</hi> to ſpare;</l>
                  <l>Which ſoon he ſever'd from its reeking Bed,</l>
                  <l>And by a deep Inciſion which he made</l>
                  <l>Into the Centre of his Brawny <hi>Thigh</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(An Artificial Matrix to the Eye)</l>
                  <l>He caus'd it there for nouriſhment to lie,</l>
                  <l>Till its Birth-time ſhould force its Libertie;</l>
                  <l>For which great <hi>Jupiter</hi> much honour gain'd,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Bacchus</hi> after was <hi>Bimater</hi> Nam'd.</l>
                  <l>Ten Moons had ſcarcely fil'd their Monthly courſe,</l>
                  <l>When thriving <hi>Bacchus</hi> by Dame Natures force,</l>
                  <l>Scorning the Priſon of his Fathers <hi>Thigh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Got ſtrength to force his ſafe Delivery.</l>
                  <l>His Youthful days in learning Arts he ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Under the wiſe and proſp'rous Government</l>
                  <l>Of grave <hi>Silenus,</hi> who with Wit ſublim'd,</l>
                  <l>Stockt and Imbelliſht his <hi>Heroick</hi> Mind.</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99965:53"/>
                  <l>Which made him prompt to Actions brave and high,</l>
                  <l>Whereby he purchas'd <hi>Immortality.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Virgin Valour 'mongſt the <hi>Indians</hi> flew,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe black ſwelling Veins he often drew <hi>Shore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hot reeking ſtreams of putrifyed <hi>Gore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which Dy'd their <hi>Seas,</hi> and ſtain'd the neighbouring</l>
                  <l>Leaving thoſe <hi>Fields</hi> wherein he Battles wone,</l>
                  <l>With bluſhing <hi>Cheeks</hi> to tell what he had done:</l>
                  <l>And Hills of breathleſs <hi>Indians</hi> heap'd on high</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Monument</hi> his Bloody Victory.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Blacks</hi> at length no longer would diſpute,</l>
                  <l>But rendr'd all his Conqueſts <hi>Abſolute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By their diſcreet Electing him to be,</l>
                  <l>There Foe no longer, but their <hi>Deity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There, <hi>Tryumph</hi> in its Infancy was ſeen,</l>
                  <l>VVhich owes its firſt Original to him:</l>
                  <l>Which he from vanquiſht <hi>Indians</hi> did procure,</l>
                  <l>As a juſt Tribute to their Conqueror.</l>
                  <l>A Royal Diadem adorn'd his brow,</l>
                  <l>And Libian <hi>Tiſhſue</hi> cover'd all below</l>
                  <l>In an Imperial Chariot where he ſate,</l>
                  <l>Were all the Rich <hi>Hibiliments</hi> of State</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99965:53"/>
                  <l>Drawn by fierce <hi>Tygars,</hi> who their rage ſuſpended,</l>
                  <l>To do him Honour till the Tryumph ended.</l>
                  <l>A Lance inſtead of Scepter fill'd his hand,</l>
                  <l>As the <hi>Monarchique</hi> ſign of his command:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Nobleſt <hi>Indians</hi> round about him throng,</l>
                  <l>To do him Honour as he Marcht along;</l>
                  <l>With ſo much Glory, and a Train ſo great,</l>
                  <l>That after <hi>Romans</hi> did but Ape his State.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſaw the <hi>Indians</hi> had beſtow'd</l>
                  <l>On him the Praiſe, and homage of a <hi>God;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Erecting ſeveral Temples to his Name,</l>
                  <l>Wherein each day were <hi>Goats</hi> and <hi>Aſses</hi> ſlain</l>
                  <l>With fiery <hi>Dragons,</hi> and the chattering <hi>Pye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>T'appeaſe (forſooth) his angry <hi>Deity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſhew him worthy of that large reſpect</l>
                  <l>To Arts and Sciences, he did direct</l>
                  <l>The ſearch and ſtudy of his curious Brain,</l>
                  <l>Wherein he did to that degree attain,</l>
                  <l>That many wholeſome Laws had thence their Riſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich curb'd and check't the Brutiſh <hi>Indians</hi> vice:</l>
                  <l>And many <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> were made</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſtant to them in their way of Trade:</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99965:54"/>
                  <l>But that which gratefuleſt acceptation found</l>
                  <l>Of all his Deeds, and all his Studies crown'd,</l>
                  <l>That which ſuch vaſt engagement did contract,</l>
                  <l>As to obliege the world in one ſole Act;</l>
                  <l>And makes the <hi>Indian,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Think all their Praiſe comes ſhort of what's his due,</l>
                  <l>VVas the Invention of the fruitful Vine,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe plotting Cluſters ſeemingly combine</l>
                  <l>To give Man (like himſelf) a Soul Divine.</l>
                  <l>To heave his fleeting Thoughts to ſuch a pitch,</l>
                  <l>As they with eaſe the Chriſtal <hi>Heav'n</hi> may reach,</l>
                  <l>And from its glittering <hi>Capital</hi> behold,</l>
                  <l>Hells dark Tranſactions through this Mask of Mould</l>
                  <l>VVhat boundleſs <hi>Ocean</hi>'s able to confine</l>
                  <l>The active thought, toſt by a ghuſt of wine?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:54"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:55"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>IUNO</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99965:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Juno.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu friendly <hi>Muſes,</hi> I'le be Judg by you,</l>
                  <l>If I have often troubled you or no,</l>
                  <l>Not but I've wanted your aſſiſtance much,</l>
                  <l>But my reſpect to you was always ſuch,</l>
                  <l>That like ſome bolder Poets of the Time,</l>
                  <l>I durſt not trouble you with ev'ry Rhime;</l>
                  <l>Your ſteep <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> I ne're ventur'd on,</l>
                  <l>Nor ever askt a drop of <hi>Hellicon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich I forbore, both in reſpect of you,</l>
                  <l>And complaiſance to better Poets too;</l>
                  <l>Nor e're could think it fit ſuch thoughts as mine</l>
                  <l>Should oft diſturb ye, <hi>You moſt Sacred Nine!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen ſuch as <hi>Dreydons,</hi> and ſweet <hi>Flatmans,</hi> be</l>
                  <l>The happy Subjects of your Privacie,</l>
                  <l>VVhat reaſon can induce, methinks I ſhou'd</l>
                  <l>Be heard or minded 'mongſt that Learned croud.</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99965:56"/>
                  <l>No <hi>Thelia,</hi> I have ſtill diſpair'd, and Vow</l>
                  <l>By all the Gods, I had not beg'd as now</l>
                  <l>Your bleſt aſſiſtance, but the Truth to tell,</l>
                  <l>This Hect'ring Goddeſs, if I write not well,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch loud Peals, I fear mine Ears will ſtorm,</l>
                  <l>That what with Scolding, and revengeful ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall account it Policy to die,</l>
                  <l>On purpoſe to evade her Cruelty:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe who could o're top great <hi>Jupiter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Heav'n, and often wore the Breeches there.</l>
                  <l>She, who the fair <hi>Latona</hi> at her will</l>
                  <l>Could cauſe confin'd in <hi>Delos</hi> floating Iſle,</l>
                  <l>And by ſome unjuſt Quarrel did ingage</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>Junior</hi> God to undergo her Rage,</l>
                  <l>Which undeſervedly upon them fell,</l>
                  <l>And made their Heav'n as Anxious as a Hell.</l>
                  <l>She, who amongſt the Gods could Cruel be,</l>
                  <l>If I offend, what will become of me?</l>
                  <l>Thus much to you in Private, but beware</l>
                  <l>(Let me beſeech ye) <hi>Juno</hi> does not hear,</l>
                  <l>Till your aſſiſtance my low Phanſie raiſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe commends, and checkles at her praiſe.</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99965:56"/>
                  <l>Heav'ns mighty Empreſs! thou, who ſtill haſt bin</l>
                  <l>To us a Goddeſs, and to Gods a Queen.</l>
                  <l>Who think it their Prerogative to be</l>
                  <l>Preferr'd, and govern'd by thy wiſe decree;</l>
                  <l>And round about thy <hi>Thrown</hi> do liſtning ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To catch th' <hi>unworded Breath</hi> of thy <hi>Command</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ere it be coin in Language; who do try</l>
                  <l>To intercept thy meaning at thy Eye;</l>
                  <l>And thy Important Buſineſs run about</l>
                  <l>So faſt, they ſtay not till thy words be out.</l>
                  <l>Thou, who with ſlackned thoughts art pleas'd, Bow</l>
                  <l>Thy mind to Rule this triffling Orb below;</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt careleſs <hi>Jupiter</hi> his ſenſes Drowns</l>
                  <l>In Luxury, which Heaven and Earth confounds.</l>
                  <l>Thou mighty Empreſs, from thy Heavenly Seat,</l>
                  <l>Art thou for us contriving humane Fate;</l>
                  <l>Which thou like Sun-beams kindly doſt diſperſe</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt the poor <hi>Inſects</hi> of this Univerſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sparta,</hi> and <hi>Argos,</hi> and <hi>Mycenae</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Gave thee theſe <hi>Appellations</hi> as thy due;</l>
                  <l>And firtil <hi>Samos,</hi> where thy Youth was ſpent</l>
                  <l>In harmleſs ſports, and decent Meriment:</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99965:57"/>
                  <l>VVhere crouds of Virgins, in a neighbouring Plain,</l>
                  <l>By ſportive ſlights thy Favour ſtrove to gain.</l>
                  <l>Some with their well ſtrung <hi>Timbrels</hi> in their hand,</l>
                  <l>In perfect time would tread the even ſtrand.</l>
                  <l>Some with a Sonnet Song to Oaten Pipe,</l>
                  <l>In well tun'd Noats, would court thy wiſht delight,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt others with more hard, but pleaſing toyl,</l>
                  <l>By well run Races, gain'd thy happy ſmile;</l>
                  <l>But the reſult of all, was, which ſhould be</l>
                  <l>To a good Husband firſt prefer'd by <hi>Thee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus did thy growing <hi>Worth,</hi> whilſt Young, preſage</l>
                  <l>The envy'd Glories of thy riper Age</l>
                  <l>For to compleat you, which great <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhoſe chance it was at firſt to ſee Thee there,</l>
                  <l>No ſooner view'd thy Majeſty and Grace,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe crouds of Beauties which adorn thy Face.</l>
                  <l>The peerleſs whiteneſs of thy Snowye skin,</l>
                  <l>Thy Nature Greatneſs, and thy Royal Meen;</l>
                  <l>But he was conquer'd by a ſtrange ſurprize,</l>
                  <l>And forc'd a Captive to thy Regal Eyes;</l>
                  <l>VVhom thou with much intreaty didſt approve,</l>
                  <l>As the only God deſerving of thy Love.</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99965:57"/>
                  <l>And in requital of his pains, ſervice Wed,</l>
                  <l>And Crownd'ſt his wiſhes with thy <hi>Maiden-head.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whoſe warm Nuptial pleaſures were deriv'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vulcan,</hi> whoſe Uglineſs his Parents griev'd.</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Hebe, Arge,</hi> and Renowned <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Heav'nly General in the Earthly Wars.</l>
                  <l>This Goddeſs <hi>Romes</hi> Protectreſs choſe to be,</l>
                  <l>But unto <hi>Thebes</hi> an utter Enemie.</l>
                  <l>VVho when <hi>Polibius</hi> out of <hi>Phocis</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>VVhere he had ign'rantly his Father ſlain;</l>
                  <l>Hoping within that Learned Town to find</l>
                  <l>Balm to aſſwage the Horrors of his mind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juno</hi> before the City Gates had rais'd</l>
                  <l>A Hideous Serpent, whoſe ſtrange Form amaz'd</l>
                  <l>The ſad Inhabitants; A Girls Face,</l>
                  <l>And a Dogs Body, did it's Form diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>VVith wings on's Back, and a fell Dragons Tail,</l>
                  <l>It did it's hapleſs Enemies aſſail.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juno</hi> had giv'n it this Injurious Pow'r,</l>
                  <l>That all thoſe Paſſengers it ſhould devour.</l>
                  <l>VVhom want of wit, diſabled to unfold</l>
                  <l>His dark <hi>Aenygma</hi> which was thus wiſe told.</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99965:58"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Creature (Mortal) I of thee muſt know,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which in the Morning on four Feet does go,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At Noon on two, but in the Evening he</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calls for another, and makes uſe of Three;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich wiſe <hi>Oedipus</hi> did throughly Scan,</l>
                  <l>And boldly anſwered, <hi>That it was a Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who in the Morning of his Age did creep</l>
                  <l>With the aſſiſtance both of Hands and Feet;</l>
                  <l>And at his Noon, or Prime, did boldly Run</l>
                  <l>By the ſupportage of his Feet alone;</l>
                  <l>But in the Evening of his Age debar'd</l>
                  <l>Of Strength, requires a Staff, which makes the third,</l>
                  <l>Which ſaid, The Serpent gave a hideous Groan,</l>
                  <l>And at that Inſtant fled the joyful Town.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:58"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:59"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>MINERVA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99965:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Minerva.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THy ſelf <hi>Minerva</hi> only I implore,</l>
                  <l>Lend me th'aſſiſtance, and I crave no more.</l>
                  <l>Thou wondrous <hi>Product</hi> of a <hi>Head Divine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Infuſe ſome <hi>Wit</hi> into theſe Brains of mine;</l>
                  <l>That all thy Acts I nobly may rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>And Sing thy Story to the Univerſe;</l>
                  <l>That all the yet unknowing World may be,</l>
                  <l>Throughly convinc'd of thy Divinity.</l>
                  <l>VVhen glorious <hi>Jupiter</hi> had rul'd the Throne</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Heav'n</hi> ſo long, that equal there were none</l>
                  <l>That durſt be ſo preſumptuous, to compare</l>
                  <l>VVith thoſe bleſt Attributes his mind did ſhare.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee him in his ſplendor ſit,</l>
                  <l>Swaying the Empires of the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Wit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe boundleſs Notions which inrich'd his mind,</l>
                  <l>VVere grown too Bulky now to be confin'd;</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99965:60"/>
                  <l>And Croſs-grain'd <hi>Juno</hi> at this time b'ing ſed,</l>
                  <l>To be unwilling to partake his Bed;</l>
                  <l>Denying him thereby the means to obtain</l>
                  <l>A God-like Heir, which after him might Reign,</l>
                  <l>He to revenge th' unkindneſs of his <hi>Queen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho then was cauſleſly unkind to him,</l>
                  <l>To limping <hi>Vulcan</hi> went (his Brain b'ing full)</l>
                  <l>Prays him with Hatchet to diſſect his Skull,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſtrange command the Sooty God obey'd,</l>
                  <l>And out there leapt a pretty Armed <hi>Maid</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Frisking about; in her right hand a Lance,</l>
                  <l>VVherewith ſhe trod the VVarlike <hi>Phirrhick</hi> Dance,</l>
                  <l>VVhich in the <hi>Trojan</hi> wars was firſt begun</l>
                  <l>By Active <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> great <hi>Achillis</hi> Son.</l>
                  <l>This Martial Nymph, who ſtrangely did appear,</l>
                  <l>VVas Nam'd <hi>Minerva,</hi> Deity of <hi>War:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>War</hi> was her Province, and ſhe took delight</l>
                  <l>To hear of Quarrels, and to ſee Men Fight;</l>
                  <l>Sought out for Battles, and where e're they were,</l>
                  <l>Beſure <hi>Minerva</hi> always would be there.</l>
                  <l>VVhen mighty <hi>Pompeys</hi> Fate was forc't to yield</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Caeſars</hi> Fortune i'th' <hi>Pharſalian</hi> Field,</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99965:60"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerva</hi> griev'd, and would have turn'd the Scale,</l>
                  <l>But that fierce <hi>Juno</hi> 'gainſt her did prevaile</l>
                  <l>With greater Pow'r, reverting the bleſt tide</l>
                  <l>Of dear bought Victory to <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſide.</l>
                  <l>So when in <hi>Latiums</hi> Bowels did appear</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Carthaginian</hi> waging Dreadful <hi>War:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerva</hi> ſaw his <hi>Valour</hi> and his <hi>Wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with her preſence daily honour'd it;</l>
                  <l>She ſmil'd to ſee the ſprightly Youth all gore</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Roman</hi> Veins, which ne're had Bled before;</l>
                  <l>And Crown'd his Acts with happy <hi>Victory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O're thoſe who ne're before were taught to fly;</l>
                  <l>She view'd his flights and Stratagems of War,</l>
                  <l>Whereby he made two <hi>Hannibals</hi> appear;</l>
                  <l>One in the Fields, retreating <hi>Romans</hi> own,</l>
                  <l>Another the <hi>Sennat</hi> Swore was in a Gown:</l>
                  <l>It gave <hi>Minerva</hi> heavenly content,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Preſent was to <hi>Carthage</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>none ſo ſimply lookt</hi> (to Heav'n ſhe Sings)</l>
                  <l>As dying <hi>Romans</hi> when they'd loſt their Rings.</l>
                  <l>She ſhook her ſides to the <hi>Dons</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(They who an Empire o're the world did own)</l>
                  <l>Confined Pris'ners in their Native Town.</l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99965:61"/>
                  <l>In fine, where Innate <hi>Valour</hi> did Reſide,</l>
                  <l>The over pour'd <hi>Minerva</hi> choſe that ſide,</l>
                  <l>And when hot <hi>Paſsion</hi> ſate in <hi>Valours</hi> place,</l>
                  <l>She did her beſt to bring it to diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>VVhen from great <hi>Jupiter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ropa</hi> fled,</l>
                  <l>(Having before by him been <hi>Raviſhed</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Griev'd <hi>Agenor,</hi> her Father, gave command</l>
                  <l>That his Son <hi>Cadmus</hi> ſeek her through the Land;</l>
                  <l>And if not there, to ſearch the world about,</l>
                  <l>On pain of Death, till he had found her out.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Cadmus,</hi> after he with pain had gone</l>
                  <l>Through many deſarts, and through Lands unknown,</l>
                  <l>VVearied with Travel, and diſpairing too</l>
                  <l>Of ever finding her he did Perſue.</l>
                  <l>Conſidering too, if he return'd again,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Death</hi> was to be the wages of his pain.</l>
                  <l>Loaded with grief, and Anxious diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Delphos</hi> famous Oracle he went,</l>
                  <l>And of the <hi>Amphibious</hi> Nymph deſir'd to know,</l>
                  <l>VVhat in this <hi>Exigent</hi> h'had beſt to do:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Oracle</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> did kindly greet,</l>
                  <l>And had h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m the next Oxe he chanc'd to meet,</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:99965:61"/>
                  <l>To ſeize him for himſelf, as Lawful Prize,</l>
                  <l>And offer to the beſt of Deities</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerva,</hi> who his Caſe beſt underſtood,</l>
                  <l>And was moſt able to adviſe his good.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cadmus</hi> obeys, and on his Journy went</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Warlike Greece,</hi> where on a ſmall aſcent,</l>
                  <l>Beneath the umbrage of a gloomy VVood,</l>
                  <l>He found the expected Beaſt which grazing ſtood.</l>
                  <l>VVhom joyful <hi>Cadmus</hi> and his Men ſurpriz'd,</l>
                  <l>And to <hi>Minerva</hi> would have Sacrific'd,</l>
                  <l>But that in order to that Pious Care</l>
                  <l>VVhich in ſuch Sacred Actions uſual are,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cadmus</hi> for water had diſmiſt his Train,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Dirc</hi>'s Fountain, where they all were ſlain</l>
                  <l>By a fierce Dragon, which was uſe to abide</l>
                  <l>In a thick <hi>Break,</hi> hard by the Forreſt ſide;</l>
                  <l>So that Young <hi>Cadmus</hi>'s ſelf was left alone,</l>
                  <l>To do the work of his Devotion.</l>
                  <l>VVith pain the Sacrifice b'ing kil'd and ended,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Cadmus</hi> courſe, <hi>Minerva</hi> was recommended,</l>
                  <l>That firſt he ſhould that dreadful Draggon flay,</l>
                  <l>And ſow his Teeth where his own dead Friends lay.</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99965:62"/>
                  <l>From which ſtrange Seed an Army ſhould ariſe</l>
                  <l>Able to guard him from his Enemies;</l>
                  <l>And likewiſe to aſſiſt him to Erect</l>
                  <l>Structures impregnable, as might protect</l>
                  <l>Him and his Companions wholly free</l>
                  <l>From his Unnat'ral Fathers harſh Decree.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Cadmus</hi> did, and with no ſmall ſurprize</l>
                  <l>To ſee an Army from the Teeth ariſe</l>
                  <l>Which Ranckt and Muſter'd, all before him ſtand</l>
                  <l>Ready to work or March, at his Command:</l>
                  <l>The Souldiers by <hi>Minerva</hi>'s wiſe advice,</l>
                  <l>Were carried to the place of Sacrifice,</l>
                  <l>(Where the Prophetick Oxes blood was ſpilt,)</l>
                  <l>On which fam'd Spot Renowned <hi>Thebes</hi> was built;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſpacious <hi>Forum</hi> to a Temple led,</l>
                  <l>Where by Learn'd <hi>Thaebans</hi> ſhe was worſhipped.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:62"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:63"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>CYBELE</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:99965:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Cybele.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu <hi>Veſtal Virgins,</hi> who do watch that Fire,</l>
                  <l>which like your Chaſtities, muſt ne're expire.</l>
                  <l>You who of Nobleſt <hi>Romans</hi> were deſcended,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>fames</hi> did <hi>rival</hi> thoſe bright <hi>Beams</hi> you tended.</l>
                  <l>Lend me a <hi>Spark,</hi> my grov'ling Muſe to raiſe</l>
                  <l>To a fit pitch, to write <hi>Cybele</hi>'s Praiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Menoes</hi> Fair Daughter, <hi>Phrygia</hi>'s mighty King,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe loud applauſe <hi>Athenian</hi> Quills did Sing,</l>
                  <l>'Till for ſome weighty Fatal cauſe, unknown,</l>
                  <l>He was ſo cruel to <hi>Cybele</hi> grown,</l>
                  <l>That Maugre all that Dearneſs, Love, and Care,</l>
                  <l>That Parents to their Children ought to bare.</l>
                  <l>Far from his Throne, amidſt a Deſart wild,</l>
                  <l>Which nought but with wild Beaſts was <hi>ſtockt</hi> &amp; <hi>fil'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Midſt bleakiſh winds, and in a place forlorn,</l>
                  <l>He left the Fair <hi>Cybele</hi> to be torn</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:99965:64"/>
                  <l>By <hi>Tygars, Panthars,</hi> or what elſe thought fit</l>
                  <l>To Bait his Stomack with that Royal bit,</l>
                  <l>VVho had no other guard for her defence</l>
                  <l>But ſwadling cloaths and Infant Innocence:</l>
                  <l>But whatſoe're we think,—thoſe Heav'nly Pow'rs,</l>
                  <l>VVho Regiſter each word and Act of ours,</l>
                  <l>VVho Rule the world, and by Experience ſee</l>
                  <l>VVhat homage 'longs to Sacred Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>Put down a Mighty blot, when they behold</l>
                  <l>VVe wave our Loyalty for droſſy Gold:</l>
                  <l>This, by this Story may be underſtood,</l>
                  <l>VVhere Brutes turn Guardians unto Royal Blood;</l>
                  <l>Renounce their Rav'nous Natures, and become</l>
                  <l>To Majeſty a ſafe <hi>Palladium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For vext <hi>Cleone</hi> had not left behind</l>
                  <l>The Child an hour, to be expos'd toth' wind,</l>
                  <l>But from a neigbouring VVood to ſeek for Prey,</l>
                  <l>A hungry Lyon made his haſty way,</l>
                  <l>Directly t'wards the place the Infant lay.</l>
                  <l>The Beaſt Surveys her with a Tayl reclin'd,</l>
                  <l>And haughty look, as tow'ring as his Mind;</l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99965:64"/>
                  <l>Then by a ſudden ſtart did ſeem to ſpy</l>
                  <l>Unuſual Greatneſs dawning in her Eye,</l>
                  <l>Which he Admir'd by Nat'ral ſimpathy.</l>
                  <l>In this Amaze, a Rav'nous Tygar comes</l>
                  <l>With open Mouth, and at the Infant Runs,</l>
                  <l>Whom doubtleſs ſhe had made her wretched Prey,</l>
                  <l>Had not the Kingly Lyon ſtopt her way;</l>
                  <l>So that each Beaſt at other b'ing inrag'd,</l>
                  <l>In a fierce Combat ſtrongly were engag'd;</l>
                  <l>Which from a far, a ſtragling Shepheard ſpies,</l>
                  <l>And whilſt they ſtrugled, ſnatch'd away the Prize.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cybele</hi>'s Beauty did the Swain ingage,</l>
                  <l>To Educate her till ſhe came to Age;</l>
                  <l>And then ſo bright ſhe ſeem'd, her Beauty cou'd</l>
                  <l>Out-ſhine the Sun, and make it ſeem a Cloud.</l>
                  <l>As Goddeſs of the Woods ſhe daily walk'd,</l>
                  <l>To whom Young Shepheards at a diſtance talk'd;</l>
                  <l>Gath'ring thoſe Roſes were moſt freſh and gay,</l>
                  <l>To ſtrew before her in her happy way;</l>
                  <l>Striving by little ſervices, to move</l>
                  <l>The Beauteous Shepheard to requite their Love:</l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:99965:65"/>
                  <l>But ſhe neglected all, till ſhe had ſeen</l>
                  <l>A ſprightful Shepheard of a graceful Meen,</l>
                  <l>To whom ſuch kindneſſes ſhe did impart,</l>
                  <l>That all immagin'd he had gain'd her heart;</l>
                  <l>And ſo its like he had, for by his Suit</l>
                  <l>He gain'd both heart and Maiden-head to boot,</l>
                  <l>At the dear purchaſe of his deareſt Life,</l>
                  <l>For whom <hi>Cybela</hi> after dy'd of Grief.</l>
                  <l>Which doleful News to <hi>Italy</hi> was brought,</l>
                  <l>When mighty <hi>Hannibal</hi> had newly Fought</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Cannae</hi>'s Battle, where the Fields he ſtrow'd</l>
                  <l>With mighty Deluges of <hi>Roman</hi> Blood;</l>
                  <l>And Poſting t'wards the trembling Capital,</l>
                  <l>Threatned both it, and all the Senats fall:</l>
                  <l>In which ſtrange Exegence, the Senate ſent</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe ſad Wars, to learn the dire Event</l>
                  <l>From fam'd <hi>Cybeles</hi> Books, where future Fate</l>
                  <l>In obſcure Characters was darkly Writ.</l>
                  <l>Which thus inform'd; the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> may</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Romes</hi> proud Gates with eaſe be driv'n away,</l>
                  <l>Provided ſome bold <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul come,</l>
                  <l>And take <hi>Cybele</hi>'s Statue into <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99965:65"/>
                  <l>Which by <hi>Pompilius</hi> was no ſooner done,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Scipio Affrica</hi> a Conqueſt wone;</l>
                  <l>And by ſix Thouſand <hi>Carthaginians</hi> fall,</l>
                  <l>Forc'd them to ſend for Conquering <hi>Hanibal.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>After the Conquering <hi>Romans</hi> rais'd her Fame,</l>
                  <l>(Both <hi>Vesta</hi> and <hi>Cybele</hi> b'ing the ſame)</l>
                  <l>And her with ſtrange and endleſs Fire ador'd,</l>
                  <l>To whom inſtead of Sprites they did afford</l>
                  <l>A Flock of Virgins, who alternate came</l>
                  <l>To watch and manage that Aeternal Flame.</l>
                  <l>A Fire ſo ſtrange, it curiouſly would try</l>
                  <l>That Virgin, who had ſtain'd her Chaſtity:</l>
                  <l>Who ever after, if ſhe dare to come</l>
                  <l>To ſtir thoſe Embers, they would her conſume.</l>
                  <l>Some Antient Poets in their Books diſcover,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cybele</hi> was the Gods great Grand-mother.</l>
                  <l>Who when Eternity had grunting layn</l>
                  <l>So long, till ſhe was brought to Bed of Time.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cybele</hi> too in torturing Pangs was hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>Lab'ring in Travel of an unborn VVorld:</l>
                  <l>From whoſe large Soul deriv'd in after time,</l>
                  <l>VVere all thoſe Deities they term'd Divine.</l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:99965:66"/>
                  <l>As Miſtreſs of the Earth ſhe now Infuſes</l>
                  <l>That genial heat which Hearbs and Flow'rs produces,</l>
                  <l>And by the Suns imbraces, yet does bring</l>
                  <l>Into the world each Year a luſty Spring;</l>
                  <l>For which the grateful Painters do beſtow</l>
                  <l>Small Towns, like Lawrels, circling round her Brow.</l>
                  <l>In a low Vale a fertil Hill does riſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Fruit does bound the Proſpect of her Eyes;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt in a ſtately Chariot ſhe o'relooks</l>
                  <l>Fair Landskips Lac'd with glittering Silver Brooks,</l>
                  <l>Which 'twixt their flowry Banks do gently fly,</l>
                  <l>Rend'ring their Beauty double to the Eye:</l>
                  <l>Thus was this Reverend Goddeſs uſe to Ride,</l>
                  <l>With crouds of Shepheards Lacquing by her ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:66"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:67"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>PLUTO</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:99965:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Pluto.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEyond the utmoſt Limits of the Earth,</l>
                  <l>In a vaſt ſpace which gave young <hi>Time</hi> its Birth;</l>
                  <l>Where dancing Atoms ſilently do Mourn,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they cannot Jumble into Form.</l>
                  <l>A piece of that old <hi>Vacuum</hi> or Shade,</l>
                  <l>Where Eldeſt Spirits their firſt Revels made,</l>
                  <l>And frisking <hi>Demons</hi> afterwards were hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>Free from the croudings of this Bulky <hi>World,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which puſh'd and ſhov'd 'em up to leſſer Room,</l>
                  <l>Making incroachments on their <hi>Vacuum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There wrapt in Flames a dreadful Throne does ſtand,</l>
                  <l>O're which Infernal <hi>Pluto</hi> bears command,</l>
                  <l>Stretching his Firy Scepter out ſo far,</l>
                  <l>As loudly ſpeaks him <hi>Hells</hi> great <hi>Emperor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Burning Grannadoes 'ſtead of Jems appear,</l>
                  <l>Like blazing ſtudds on his ſupported Chair,</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:99965:68"/>
                  <l>VVhich o're remoter ſhades large proſpects takes</l>
                  <l>From the ſtrong <hi>Atlas</hi> of grim Spirits backs:</l>
                  <l>His ſhrill Command the ſilent <hi>Grott</hi> invades,</l>
                  <l>Which caught by Eccho's, bandy'd through the ſhades</l>
                  <l>Till ſtartled Ghoſts from out their Buſhes run,</l>
                  <l>Like frighted Hares about the <hi>Elyzium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And fleſhleſs <hi>Skeletons</hi> ſurprized ſo,</l>
                  <l>They leave their Brakes, and wrattle as they go.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Departing Souls to this Infernal Court,</l>
                  <l>VVhen they forſake their lifeleſs Trunks reſort,</l>
                  <l>VVhere correſpondent toth' deeds they have done,</l>
                  <l>They trembling ſit to hear deſerved doom,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Minos, Radamanthus,</hi> and the reſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe ſpotleſs Lives deſerv'd that power beſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhom to that Office <hi>Pluto</hi> did prefer</l>
                  <l>For their unbyas'd Juſtice practic'd here.</l>
                  <l>At the poor Souls approach, the Judges call</l>
                  <l>For their Diurnal, or that hideous Scrall</l>
                  <l>Carefully kept in Heav'ns great Capital,</l>
                  <l>All to be daub'd with wretched Sinners names,</l>
                  <l>VVhich all their cloſe and open Sins proclaims,</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99965:68"/>
                  <l>In Letters Capital, ſo plain toth' Eye,</l>
                  <l>That when the trembling Sinner comes to die,</l>
                  <l>Like Boys in <hi>Horn-Books,</hi> h'reads em through the Skie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Judgment according to their Crimes b'ing paſt,</l>
                  <l>The wicked Souls to <hi>Tartarus</hi> were caſt;</l>
                  <l>That by a certain time of ſuffring there,</l>
                  <l>They might Attone thoſe Sins they acted here.</l>
                  <l>The firſt thing there, the amazed Souls beheld,</l>
                  <l>VVas mighty Gyants, under Mountains quel'd;</l>
                  <l>Down to hot flames, becauſe before they ſtrove</l>
                  <l>From Heav'ns bright <hi>Throne,</hi> to pull the Pow'rs above.</l>
                  <l>The next which beg'd attention from the Eye</l>
                  <l>VVas wretched <hi>Ixion,</hi> whoſe Love ſoar'd ſo high,</l>
                  <l>To court compliance in ſtern <hi>Juno</hi>'s will,</l>
                  <l>For which attempt ſhe bound him to a wheel,</l>
                  <l>VVhich in a ſwift unſeaſant pace did move,</l>
                  <l>To give him Torture for his ſaucy Love.</l>
                  <l>But that which admiration moſt obtains,</l>
                  <l>VVas <hi>Syſiphus</hi> his unſucceſsful pains</l>
                  <l>Condemn'd for Theft, to Roll a mighty Stone</l>
                  <l>Up a ſteep Hill, which faſter tumbled down,</l>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:99965:69"/>
                  <l>And by the force of it's prevailing weight,</l>
                  <l>Renders him hopeleſs of a milder Fate.</l>
                  <l>In helliſh <hi>Tartarus</hi> to ſtay their Times,</l>
                  <l>Appointed were according to their Crimes;</l>
                  <l>Some ſmall, ſome great, which ſoon as e're expir'd,</l>
                  <l>The now confined Soul with joy retir'd</l>
                  <l>To thoſe cool ſhades, where laviſh Bleſſings run</l>
                  <l>Frequent as Air, and make <hi>Elyzium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſhape of Ghoſts they now retain no more,</l>
                  <l>But each reſumes his Form as heretofore.</l>
                  <l>There Lovers, which this peeviſh World deny'd</l>
                  <l>Their wiſht Conjunction, happily reſide,</l>
                  <l>Free from diſturbance 'mongſt thoſe ſhady Groves,</l>
                  <l>Reaping the utmoſt wiſhes of their Loves.</l>
                  <l>Some waſt their happy Minutes, to declare</l>
                  <l>Th' affronts and croſſes which they meet with here;</l>
                  <l>And then with thoughts renew'd, thoſe griefs deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Pond'ring the freedom which they now enjoy.</l>
                  <l>Here mighty Love does all his charms diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Friends,</hi> nor <hi>Law,</hi> nor <hi>Im'reſt</hi> interpoſe,</l>
                  <l>But ev'ry Lover to his Mate is giv'n,</l>
                  <l>With whom he lives, and makes a perfect <hi>Heav'n.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99965:69"/>
                  <l>Here lovely <hi>Chen</hi>—! when th' obliging <hi>Gods</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall call us to them in theſe Green aboads,</l>
                  <l>Beneath ſome penſive Willow, thou and I,</l>
                  <l>Condemned here, alas! to Gaze and Sigh,</l>
                  <l>Shall their thoſe Pow'rs themſelves to Envy move,</l>
                  <l>VVhen we com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leat our long ſuſpended Love.</l>
                  <l>Gods will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their Eſſences, and wiſh</l>
                  <l>To be like us, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they behold our Bliſs.</l>
                  <l>And envious Lovers at their Fates repine,</l>
                  <l>When thy warm Arms ſhall cling as cloſe as mine:</l>
                  <l>VVhen of thy Beauties I ſhall be poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>And Love and Youth make up an endleſs Feaſt;</l>
                  <l>And if at any time our fervour ſhall</l>
                  <l>Admit an hour or two of Interval,</l>
                  <l>Reſembling Recreation I ſhall find,</l>
                  <l>VVhen I contemplate thy Illuſtrious mind;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a Soul ſo noble, and refin'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſo tranſcending ſilly VVoman kind!</l>
                  <l>That when in bleſt <hi>Elyzium</hi> it appears,</l>
                  <l>The wond'ring <hi>Gods</hi> will think it one of their;</l>
                  <l>Treat it accordingly, till I do prove</l>
                  <l>Thee mine alone, by Tenure of my Love.</l>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99965:70"/>
                  <l>Ah! whilſt I think on thee, my Pen does write</l>
                  <l>VVith ſo much ſatisfaction and delight,</l>
                  <l>That common Lovers, in their ſweeteſt Joys,</l>
                  <l>May wiſh my Pleaſures, whilſt I write thy Praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Pardon great <hi>Pluto,</hi> that ſo long I Rove,</l>
                  <l>I left my <hi>Theme</hi> a while to meet my Love:</l>
                  <l>So once with Amorous thoughts thy Breaſt did ſwell,</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Proſerpina</hi> thou Redeemd'ſt from Hell.</l>
                  <l>Furies nor Fire, could not then remove</l>
                  <l>The wild Excurſion of thy Frantick Love.</l>
                  <l>But thou to Heav'n, through both, did'ſt her convey,</l>
                  <l>As Old <hi>Archiſes</hi> rid through Flames of <hi>Troy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:70"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:71"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>PROSERPINA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:99965:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Proſperpina</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat Mighty Mines of hidden Magick lie</l>
                  <l>In the ſmall Circle of a Womans Eye;</l>
                  <l>VVhen Statemens Policies, and Heroes Arms,</l>
                  <l>Are fain to ſtoop to its prevailing Charms,</l>
                  <l>And on this ſcore concede to mighty Love,</l>
                  <l>[VVhat conquer'd them has done the ſame by <hi>Jove]</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho firſt his God-head as a Victim lays</l>
                  <l>Down to the Mercy of <hi>Latona</hi>'s Eys,</l>
                  <l>And then diveſts himſelf of all his Power</l>
                  <l>To young <hi>Denae</hi> in the Brazen Tower;</l>
                  <l>To tell the various Intrigues of his Love,</l>
                  <l>VVould but a <hi>Herculean</hi> labour prove:</l>
                  <l>It is enough the Courteous Reader knows,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Jove</hi> at length to <hi>Ceres</hi> Beauty bows,</l>
                  <l>On whom his Promiſes ſuch Credence gain,</l>
                  <l>She yields the <hi>Fort</hi> which ne're before was tane;</l>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:99965:72"/>
                  <l>And <hi>Proſerpina,</hi> (Heav'ns Imperial Queen)</l>
                  <l>Her being owes to the Laſcivious Sin;</l>
                  <l>The dauning Glories of whoſe Morning years,</l>
                  <l>A Prodigee to neighbouring Gods appears;</l>
                  <l>VVho by thoſe Seeds of Beauty fate had ſow'n</l>
                  <l>In her fair cheeks, preſag'd the Cropp when grown.</l>
                  <l>Each Amorous Deity attempts t'engage</l>
                  <l>In Youth her Love, againſt ſhe comes to Age,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt ſhe as coyly does their Flames diſown,</l>
                  <l>And ſcorns a Preſent leſſer than a Crown.</l>
                  <l>Her Native <hi>Grandure,</hi> and her Courtlike <hi>Meen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſpos'd her only fit to be a <hi>Queen;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor can in Heav'n her young Ambition find</l>
                  <l>Ought but a Throne to ſtop her greedy Mind.</l>
                  <l>VVhen ripe Maturity had Crown'd her years,</l>
                  <l>And warm'd her Brain with ſtrange ambitious cares.</l>
                  <l>Her envious Eyes to Heav'ns bright Thrown ſhe caſt,</l>
                  <l>And mourn'd to ſee that Seat before poſſeſt.</l>
                  <l>Then with a haughty and Imperious Eye,</l>
                  <l>She view'd and ſcorn'd Earths brittle <hi>Sov'raignty.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere Men o're night like Demi-Gods appear,</l>
                  <l>And in the Morning want a Sepulcher.</l>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99965:72"/>
                  <l>Next to great Neptunes Throne her thoughts did ſoar,</l>
                  <l>But he was furniſht with a <hi>Queen</hi> before;</l>
                  <l>So that at laſt ſhe knew not where to find</l>
                  <l>An empty <hi>Throne</hi> to ſatisfie her Mind;</l>
                  <l>Juſt at this juncture, <hi>Pluto,</hi> whoſe grim Face,</l>
                  <l>Had formerly procur'd him much diſgrace</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt other <hi>Goddeſses,</hi> who view'd with ſcorn</l>
                  <l>Th'Infernal King, by reaſon of his Form.</l>
                  <l>Great flaming Eyes, with Skin as dark as Night,</l>
                  <l>And bloated Cheeks, made not to tempt, but fright:</l>
                  <l>The dreadful Horror of his looks, did move</l>
                  <l>The Heav'nly <hi>Goddeſses</hi> to Fear, not Love.</l>
                  <l>At whoſe approach, they always us'd to fly</l>
                  <l>His Helliſh Courtſhip, and his company:</l>
                  <l>Fearful from Hell, that he was rather ſent,</l>
                  <l>Not as a Courtier, but a Puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>But when untam'd Ambition gapes for Pow'r,</l>
                  <l>VVhat nauceous <hi>Goblets</hi> will it not devour?</l>
                  <l>Trampling o're all the Paſſions of the Mind</l>
                  <l>VVith as much eaſe, as wind through Chaff does find.</l>
                  <l>Fear and diſtruſt, their Trepidations ſhun,</l>
                  <l>Thruſt by Ambition, both to Courage Run.</l>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:99965:73"/>
                  <l>Unmanly Cowardice, and dark Diſpair;</l>
                  <l>Leave the low Rooms, and to the Heart repair,</l>
                  <l>VVhere finding cloſe <hi>Caballs</hi> of Paſſions met,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ambitions</hi> grand deſign to Propagate;</l>
                  <l>They frankly cloſe, and as they had forgot</l>
                  <l>Their Names, become the deſperat'ſt in the <hi>Plot.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhilſt <hi>Envy, Anger,</hi> with bold courage ty'd,</l>
                  <l>And all the leſſer Faculties beſide;</l>
                  <l>VVith all the Pow'r, and art they have, conſpire</l>
                  <l>The ſure compleatment of the wild deſire;</l>
                  <l>Nay, mighty Love, which will no homage own,</l>
                  <l>To ought inferiour, ſtoops unto a Crown;</l>
                  <l>And will by Proxy of a Picture Gueſs,</l>
                  <l>(In hopes of that) at other happineſs.</l>
                  <l>The Bait of a Monarchick fate appears</l>
                  <l>So charming to the Ambitious Purchaſers.</l>
                  <l>(To whom the inlay'd troubles of a Crown</l>
                  <l>B'ing Hiv'd in Gold, are utterly unknown,)</l>
                  <l>That they the grounds of Love but light eſteem,</l>
                  <l>VVhen it oppoſes hopes of <hi>Diadem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Proſerpina, Pluto</hi>'s Love do's own,</l>
                  <l>She over looks his Face, to ſee his Crown;</l>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:99965:73"/>
                  <l>From whoſe bright Pearls, ſuch glittering dawns ariſe,</l>
                  <l>As drown'd the Horror of her Lovers Eyes.</l>
                  <l>She not at him, but at his Throne does gaze,</l>
                  <l>Runs to his Arms, but ne're beholds his Face;</l>
                  <l>VVhere lockt in forc'd Imbraces, ſhe derives</l>
                  <l>Not Loves warm joys, but thoſe Ambition gives;</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt thoughts of glory do that loſs redeem,</l>
                  <l>As ſubtle VVomen think on other Men.—</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Aetna</hi>'s Flaming Mountain <hi>Pluto</hi> brought</l>
                  <l>Th' Ambitious Goddeſs, where with care he ſought</l>
                  <l>In Loves great management, to ſhew ſuch skill,</l>
                  <l>By VVit and Language, as might gain her will.</l>
                  <l>But both b'ing ineffectual, he was fain</l>
                  <l>By force to Raviſh what he beg'd in vain.</l>
                  <l>VVe moſt Everſion find in willing Mis—</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe feign'd reſiſtance but indears the Bliſs;</l>
                  <l>VVhich elſe by Fooliſh Lovers would be thought</l>
                  <l>Not worth injoying, 'twas ſo cheaply bought.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pluto</hi> the gloomy Emperor of <hi>Hell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Behav'd himſelf in Loves Careſs ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Proſerpina</hi> now inſults no more,</l>
                  <l>But ſeems to Sigh, ſhe did not yield before.</l>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99965:74"/>
                  <l>Such ſtrange unlanguag'd Joys does Love diſpence,</l>
                  <l>It makes the Lover hate his Continence:</l>
                  <l>And (where Religions wanting) hugg the Sin</l>
                  <l>To which he grieves he launcht no ſooner in.</l>
                  <l>Thus mighty <hi>Pluto,</hi> ſcal'd the Virgin Fort,</l>
                  <l>And now he thinks he need no longer Court:</l>
                  <l>VVhen that's once loſt, the Woman Raigns no more,</l>
                  <l>But Courts the Man, as he did her before:</l>
                  <l>VVithout more words, ſhe Vows to be his Queen,</l>
                  <l>And down hot <hi>Aetna</hi>'s Entrils follows him,</l>
                  <l>To thoſe dull Shades where injur'd Lovers keep:</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Pluto</hi> Crown'd her Empreſs of the Deep.</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Story thus much of her Sex does tell,</l>
                  <l>They will be Ruling, though it be in Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:74"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:75"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>HERCULES</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99965:75"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Hercules.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen we diſcourſe of brave <hi>Alcides</hi> Fame,</l>
                  <l>Wonders grow common, &amp; forget their name!</l>
                  <l>Faith can't comprize thoſe Truths the Author tells,</l>
                  <l>And Reaſon ſtartles at the <hi>Miracles:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our Modern <hi>Hero</hi>'s of the beſt eſteem,</l>
                  <l>Seem Dwarfiſh Infants when compar'd with him;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe tall <hi>Gigantick</hi> Worth, their pitch out flew,</l>
                  <l>And is too great for moſt of them to View.</l>
                  <l>VVhen to his heighth, the largeſt thought's ſublim'd,</l>
                  <l>It finds no room for Glory left behind:</l>
                  <l>But like the curious ſearches of the Eye,</l>
                  <l>Returns, and Settles, bounded by the Sky.</l>
                  <l>As were his Actions of Unvalu'd worth,</l>
                  <l>So, wondrous was the manner of his Birth;</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Jupiter Al'mena</hi> to Enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Three Nights conjoyn'd without a Glimp's of Day,</l>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99965:76"/>
                  <l>That in her Husbands Shape he might (by ſtealth)</l>
                  <l>Beget a <hi>Hero</hi> worthy of himſelf.</l>
                  <l>But jealous <hi>Juno</hi> who with rage was fild,</l>
                  <l>At the preſageing Beauties of the Child.</l>
                  <l>A pair of Dreadful Serpents ſent to be,</l>
                  <l>Of his new Life the ſad Cataſtrophe.</l>
                  <l>Then with unuſual Courage he aſſails,</l>
                  <l>And by his Infant ſtrength ſo far prevails;</l>
                  <l>That by the Early conqueſt, men begun</l>
                  <l>To Gheſs what Race his Valour was to run.</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt <hi>Alimena</hi> in Travel went with him,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mycene</hi>'s VVife was Big at the ſame time;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Jupiter</hi> had Swore that which of them</l>
                  <l>Firſt ſhould be born, ſhould wear the <hi>Diadem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And o're the other bare entire Command.</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſoon as <hi>Juno</hi> came to underſtand,</l>
                  <l>Two Moneths before the uſual time of Birth,</l>
                  <l>She caus'd young <hi>Euriſtheus</hi> to come forth,</l>
                  <l>And leave the dangerous Lodging of the VVomb,</l>
                  <l>To be ſucceſſor to his Fathers <hi>Throne.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhilſt ſlumb'ring there, did young <hi>Alcides</hi> lye,</l>
                  <l>Little ſuſpecting the Captivity,</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:99965:76"/>
                  <l>And Vaſſalage he was to undergo,</l>
                  <l>VVhen jealous <hi>Euriſtheus</hi> came to know</l>
                  <l>That dangerous Valour which adorn'd his mind,</l>
                  <l>Of ſtout <hi>Alcides,</hi> who to Arms inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Did his green Youth with ſuch brave Actions Crown,</l>
                  <l>As no contempor'ry Monarch dar'd to own,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Euriſtheus</hi> forc'd, by ſuch commands,</l>
                  <l>As ſcorn'd accompliſhment by other hands,</l>
                  <l>In dire full tasks of Valour to expoſe</l>
                  <l>That Life, which ſcar'd him more than all his Foes.</l>
                  <l>But all the toyls this <hi>Tyrant</hi> could invent,</l>
                  <l>Serv'd but <hi>Alcides</hi> Glory to augment.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe dauntleſs Courage near his Strength forſook,</l>
                  <l>And pow'r accompliſht what he undertook.</l>
                  <l>To whom the greateſt Perils ſeem'd but ſmall,</l>
                  <l>And common dangers lookt like none at all.</l>
                  <l>Both which he grappl'd with Victorious hands,</l>
                  <l>And wearied <hi>Euriſtheus</hi>'s harſh cammands.</l>
                  <l>From whom he would have parted; but the pow'rs,</l>
                  <l>VVho oft offlict this wretched Life of ours.</l>
                  <l>Proclaim'd by Oracle it was the will,</l>
                  <l>Of all the <hi>Gods</hi> that he ſhould ſerve him ſtill.</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:99965:77"/>
                  <l>Till his bright fame by twelve brave Actions more,</l>
                  <l>VVere made more glorious than it was before.</l>
                  <l>Which thus ſucceſſively the youth Obeys,</l>
                  <l>And crown'd his labour with Immortal prays.</l>
                  <l>Out of the hollow Conclave of the <hi>Moon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Nemea</hi>'s gloomy Forreſt tumbling down;</l>
                  <l>A mighty Lyon came, who ſeeking out</l>
                  <l>For Pray, Devour'd the Country round about.</l>
                  <l>Him, brave <hi>Alcides,</hi> in his Den Surpriz'd,</l>
                  <l>And with ſtrong hands, his knotty wind-pipe ſeiz'd</l>
                  <l>With ſuch ſucceſſive ſtrength, that wanting Breath,</l>
                  <l>The Lyon paid his valour with his Death.</l>
                  <l>Then from his back, his ponderous skin he tore,</l>
                  <l>And wore it himſelf in ſign of Conquerour.</l>
                  <l>Next he was ſent to <hi>Lerna</hi>'s fulſome <hi>Lake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The many headed <hi>Hydra</hi> to attaque;</l>
                  <l>Who looſing one, its wondrous Nature was,</l>
                  <l>To ſprout out many others in the place;</l>
                  <l>Nor likely was Mortallity to know,</l>
                  <l>If all were not diſſected at one Blow:</l>
                  <l>And afterwards his hateful Body burn'd,</l>
                  <l>Both which <hi>Alcides</hi> happily perform'd.</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:99965:77"/>
                  <l>About that time, the huge <hi>Arcadian</hi> Boar,</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Erimanthus</hi> Mountain did appear;</l>
                  <l>Which young <hi>Alcides</hi> took, and out of Sport,</l>
                  <l>Drag'd him along to <hi>Euryſtheus</hi> Court;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſhape was horrid, and ſo prone to fright,</l>
                  <l>The timerous <hi>Tyrant</hi> Swooned at the ſight.</l>
                  <l>He Vanquiſht <hi>Menalus</hi>'s Stagg in Fight,</l>
                  <l>And after put <hi>Stymphalus</hi> Birds to Flight;</l>
                  <l>But that which moſt his peerleſs Valour Crowns,</l>
                  <l>Was Conqueſt o're the <hi>Scythian Amazons.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When joyn'd with <hi>Theſeus</hi> in that Glorious ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>(To whom he gave <hi>Hypolite</hi> for Wife)</l>
                  <l>The next Injunction which enhaunc't his Fame,</l>
                  <l>Was, making King <hi>Augias</hi> Stables Clean;</l>
                  <l>Forcing old <hi>Alpleus</hi> to forget her Stream,</l>
                  <l>And drive her Channel through the midſt of them;</l>
                  <l>And ſo perform'd his promiſe, in one day,</l>
                  <l>Cleanſing of Dung, ten Thouſand Tuns away.</l>
                  <l>From thence the <hi>Thracian Tyrant</hi> he perſu'd,</l>
                  <l>(Grim <hi>Diomedes</hi>) with a mind endu'd.</l>
                  <l>So Barbarous, and full of Cruelty,</l>
                  <l>That by wild Horſes, he made ſtrangers Dye.</l>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99965:78"/>
                  <l>Him brave <hi>Alcides</hi> by exceſs of pow'r,</l>
                  <l>Forc't to that Fate which he impos'd before.</l>
                  <l>And made the ſtrange Three-body'd <hi>Gerion</hi> feel,</l>
                  <l>The fatal weight of his Victorious Steel.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alcides</hi> in his next adventure Kil'd</l>
                  <l>The horrid Gardian of th' <hi>Heſperian</hi> Feild;</l>
                  <l>Though ſome ſay <hi>Atlas</hi> eas'd him of that Toyl;</l>
                  <l>And left him ſhouldring up the VVorld the while.</l>
                  <l>But that which brought the largeſt ſhare of Fame</l>
                  <l>To make immortal his <hi>Heroick Name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVas when with unreſiſted ſtrength he Fell</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Cerberus</hi> and drag'd him out of Hell,</l>
                  <l>And ſet young <hi>Theſeus</hi> (there impriſon'd) Free</l>
                  <l>From the vaſt Pains of Hells Captivitie.</l>
                  <l>This Chain of brave Atcheivments mov'd the Gods</l>
                  <l>To take him to them in their bleſt Aboads,</l>
                  <l>And 'twas no doubt, for ſuch bright Acts as theſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi>'s <hi>Prieſt</hi> Surnam'd him <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:78"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:79"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>HEBE</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99965:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Hebe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke Murders, breaches of the Marriage Bed,</l>
                  <l>May ſleep a while, but cannot long ly hid.</l>
                  <l>Let the moſt ſubtle <hi>Letcher,</hi> wrapt in Night,</l>
                  <l>Tread nere ſo ſoftly to his Damm'd delight;</l>
                  <l>Find out the privat'ſt Allies, ſecret'ſt ways,</l>
                  <l>To creep obſcurely to his brutiſh joys;</l>
                  <l>Himſelf disfigure, in a Cloak or Gown</l>
                  <l>So ſtrangely that he thinks he can't be known:</l>
                  <l>The blazing Sin appears through all theſe ſhrow'ds</l>
                  <l>As perfectly, as does the Sun through Clouds.</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſecret <hi>Jupiter</hi> in ſilence had</l>
                  <l>Enjoy'd the pleaſures of <hi>Latonas</hi> Bed.</l>
                  <l>Though he appear'd moſt innocent in ſhew,</l>
                  <l>He quickly found this Maxim very True.</l>
                  <l>'Like Gunpowder, thoſe lowd Adulterate joys,</l>
                  <l>'Bear with them ſtill a hid and ſudden Noys;</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:99965:80"/>
                  <l>For <hi>Jupiter</hi> had hardly done the Sin,</l>
                  <l>But Curſed <hi>Juno</hi> twits him with the Crime;</l>
                  <l>Upbraids him 'fore the Gods, and threats to be</l>
                  <l>No more confin'd to the Marriage-bed than he,</l>
                  <l>Which when vext women ſwear, we need not doubt</l>
                  <l>To ſave their Souls, they'l ſurely bring about.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neptune</hi> the nick obſerv'd, and did invite</l>
                  <l>The diſcontented <hi>Juno</hi> to delight</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf by walking to a Neighbouring Field,</l>
                  <l>Which wholſome hearbs, &amp; fragrant flowers did yield.</l>
                  <l>But moſt of all to treat her curious Pallate,</l>
                  <l>VVith the ſmall Preſent of a ſav'ry Sallet.</l>
                  <l>To tell you what the Poets ſaid of old,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from a treat ſo unnouriſhing and cold,</l>
                  <l>VVould but impoſe upon your better Sences,</l>
                  <l>VVho purchaſe knowledg by your large expences.</l>
                  <l>And yet are forc't to bribe the Nimph y'have wone,</l>
                  <l>Not to declare how faintly you have done.</l>
                  <l>Yet thus thoſe Poets ſay, that <hi>Juno,</hi> fil'd</l>
                  <l>VVith that ſtrange Sallet, after prov'd with Child;</l>
                  <l>And Modern Authors for a truth relate,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Hebe</hi> was begotten by the Treat.</l>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:99965:80"/>
                  <l>VVhoſe Beauty did prefer her to the Care</l>
                  <l>Of her believing Father <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By whoſe decree, ſhe was each meal to ſtand,</l>
                  <l>VVith flowing Bowls of wine at his Right hand.</l>
                  <l>Ready for other Gods, at his expreſs,</l>
                  <l>To fill full Cups to drink his Happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor was ſhe grac't by <hi>Jupiter</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>VVho, as his Darling, kept her near his Throne.</l>
                  <l>But Heav'n throughout her pratling beauty fled,</l>
                  <l>And here on Earth her Name was honoured.</l>
                  <l>The Learn'd <hi>Athenians</hi> whoſe great parts beſt knew</l>
                  <l>VVhat Homage to <hi>Joves</hi> Cup-bearer was due:</l>
                  <l>Her perfect beauty, and her pow'r did prize</l>
                  <l>Above the Rate of common Deities:</l>
                  <l>Terming her <hi>Youths Fair Goddeſs,</hi> and each Year</l>
                  <l>About her ſpacious Temple did appear</l>
                  <l>The flow'r of all their beauteous Virgins; who</l>
                  <l>To her guilt Alter for ſucceſs did ſue</l>
                  <l>In chooſing Husbands; wiſe and aptly bred,</l>
                  <l>To reap the Pleaſures of their happy bed;</l>
                  <l>Some a young <hi>Chicken,</hi> ſome a <hi>Kid</hi> would bring,</l>
                  <l>And ſome a <hi>Pullet</hi> for their <hi>Offering.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99965:81"/>
                  <l>Some a ſtreakt Apple, newly pluckt from Tree,</l>
                  <l>The Ruddy Emblem of Virginitie.</l>
                  <l>Some who were poorer, by their wits would try</l>
                  <l>To frame ſuch ſports as pleas'd their Deity.</l>
                  <l>Some to the <hi>Ball</hi> would run, ſome th' <hi>Hays,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some to the <hi>Keets,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Priſon-beys.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVaſting the day with ſports which Youth delight</l>
                  <l>And then with Rev'rence wiſht her all,—<hi>Goodnight.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Hebe</hi> buoy'd by a reſpect from <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVas prais'd by men, and Lov'd by thoſe above.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſo with Men; when <hi>Royal</hi> Beams diſpence,</l>
                  <l>On humble ſhrubs their powerful Influence.</l>
                  <l>How ſoon they ſprout? and up t'wards Heav'n do ſoar</l>
                  <l>VVho mingled were with common Trees before!</l>
                  <l>How faſt they grow? how far their branches ſtretch?</l>
                  <l>How ſoon they ſcorn their former Dwarfiſh pitch?</l>
                  <l>VVith what contempt does their exalted bow,</l>
                  <l>Look down and ſcorn their fellow ſhrubs below?</l>
                  <l>How proudly wave they their ſurmounted heads?</l>
                  <l>Benighting all the woods with Gloomy ſhades.</l>
                  <l>VVhich wond'ring at their greatneſs, murm'ring ſtays</l>
                  <l>At it's old ſtature, wanting thoſe warm Rays.—</l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:99965:81"/>
                  <l>But when the Tempeſt of a <hi>Monarchs</hi> Frown,</l>
                  <l>VVhat he had rais'd, deſigns to tumble down:</l>
                  <l>VVhen he retracts thoſe Beams, whoſe friendly heat</l>
                  <l>Has warm'd and nurſt them to that dangerous ſate;</l>
                  <l>And from their tottering heads his help recalls,</l>
                  <l>Their deſperate heighth adds tortures to their falls.</l>
                  <l>Makes the bruiſe worſe, and their degraded power,</l>
                  <l>By them is ſcorn'd whom it had ſcar'd before.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hebe</hi> ſupported by the Smiles of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Receiv'd from Gods and Men reſpect and Love.</l>
                  <l>But when the ſad diſaſter of a fall,</l>
                  <l>Before the Gods where ſhe diſcover'd all—</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Naked beauties whoſe ſtrange natures be,</l>
                  <l>To make Men bluſh, and yet deſire to ſee.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fertil ſmiles converted to a frown,</l>
                  <l>The temporizing Gods their love diſown.</l>
                  <l>Grudg th' aſſiſtance of a worded breath,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak to <hi>Jove,</hi> who hurld her to the Earth;</l>
                  <l>VVhere brave <hi>Alcides</hi> whoſe large Soul well knew</l>
                  <l>VVhat dangerous falls the <hi>Great</hi> are ſubject to.</l>
                  <l>And could diſcern through all the Clouds of Fate,</l>
                  <l>Untainted Vertue in its low eſtate;</l>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:99965:82"/>
                  <l>Intreats her Love, and his great Vertue ſped</l>
                  <l>So well, that ſhe admits him to her bed.</l>
                  <l>From whoſe glad Nuptials (much for <hi>Revel's</hi> fam'd)</l>
                  <l>Youths Frollick ſports are yet <hi>Hebetria</hi> Nam'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:82"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:83"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>IASON</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:99965:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Jaſon.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw many Evils <hi>Humane Life</hi> ſurround,</l>
                  <l>When 'ſides thoſe common ones by all men found,</l>
                  <l>Each man within himſelf does bear about</l>
                  <l>Far greater Miſchiefs than he fights without.</l>
                  <l>In all the Pop'lous <hi>Land,</hi> from fartheſt <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To the Remoter Iſlands of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Find me but one, who certainly do's know,</l>
                  <l>VVhat's truely Good, from what is ſo in ſhow;</l>
                  <l>VVithout miſtake, for what is't we deſire,</l>
                  <l>Or fear diſcreetly? what would we require</l>
                  <l>To make us bleſt? but ever as we ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Repentance ſeals the very Act and Deed.</l>
                  <l>The eaſy <hi>Gods</hi> mov'd by no other ſate,</l>
                  <l>Than our own Pray'rs, whole Kingdoms Ruinate.</l>
                  <l>VVith things diſtructive we would oft be bleſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſo grow wretched by our own requeſt.</l>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:99965:84"/>
                  <l>When by falſe reaſons Man's affections mov'd,</l>
                  <l>No wonder that he hates the thing he Lov'd;</l>
                  <l>And through the Vail, the Cheat b'ing underſtood,</l>
                  <l>Perceives an Evil, where he hop'd for Good.</l>
                  <l>Thus the <hi>Theſſalian</hi> Monarch <hi>Pelius,</hi> drawn</l>
                  <l>(In <hi>Jaſons</hi> mind when he beheld the Dawn</l>
                  <l>Of morning Valour, which did dayly ſwell,</l>
                  <l>And threaten'd to become remarkable)</l>
                  <l>To dotage; whilſt his <hi>Nephews</hi> youth did laſt,</l>
                  <l>Nothing was wanting, or, for Care, or Coſt.</l>
                  <l>No art which did <hi>Heroick</hi> tempers ſuit,</l>
                  <l>But's Nephew <hi>Jaſon</hi> muſt be train'd up t' it.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Athens</hi> was not to dear, nor <hi>Greece</hi> too far,</l>
                  <l>To learn him all the <hi>Stratagem,</hi> of War.</l>
                  <l>Nor all the Learning either did afford,</l>
                  <l>To teach him Rule, as well as weild the Sword.</l>
                  <l>But when this prodigy of Valour had,</l>
                  <l>I'th School of VVar a fair progreſſion made;</l>
                  <l>Leaving his Fellows by a brisk advance,</l>
                  <l>To praiſe his Skill, and Curſe their Ignorance.</l>
                  <l>VVhen in the Fields by ſingle Combats he,</l>
                  <l>Had tould the VVorld what he deſign'd to be;</l>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:99965:84"/>
                  <l>And all who had for Vertue an eſteem,</l>
                  <l>As her Diſciple 'gan to honour him.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Pelias</hi> whom the wondering world believ'd,</l>
                  <l>VVould have with joy his Kinſmans fame receiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Suffer'd his Love to make a cold retreat,</l>
                  <l>And heard his prays with jealouſy, and hate,</l>
                  <l>Which in his mind a ſecret longing bred,</l>
                  <l>To blaſt that worth which he had foſtered</l>
                  <l>VVith ſo much Pain, and Coſt, and aching Cares,</l>
                  <l>It ſeem'd the buſineſs of his latter Years.</l>
                  <l>Thus blind mortality, who wiſh by gheſs,</l>
                  <l>VVith Sweaty Brows attain unhappineſs.</l>
                  <l>Which wrapt in ſpacious Colours does remain,</l>
                  <l>Unknown to them until they feel the pain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſon</hi> had ſuch undoubted <hi>Valour</hi> ſhown,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pelias</hi> grows ſuſpicious of his Thrown:</l>
                  <l>Feels himſelf totter in the Regal ſeat,</l>
                  <l>Till's Nephew's Ruin has ſecur'd his fate,</l>
                  <l>And as a means to work that black deſign,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Colchos</hi> famous Kingdom orders him</l>
                  <l>With an injunction not t' return to <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But with the Conqueſt of the <hi>Golden Fleece;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:99965:85"/>
                  <l>Which <hi>Phrixus</hi> to that Antient City brought,</l>
                  <l>When ſhelter from his Mothers rage he ſought</l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>Aeetha, Colchos</hi> mighty King,</l>
                  <l>VVho tender of ſo rich and rare a thing,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Mars</hi> his Guarden lodg'd it; where a guard</l>
                  <l>Of dreadful Beaſts from Men approach debar'd,</l>
                  <l>Strange ſulpherous <hi>Bulls</hi> with legs of hardned <hi>Braſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whoſe hot Noſtrils dreadful Flames did paſs:</l>
                  <l>VVith Dragons, ſuch as great <hi>Alcides</hi> ſlew,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe large Tuſhes mighty Armies grew:</l>
                  <l>VVere the oppoſers daign'd to be of him</l>
                  <l>VVho that Rich Conqueſt made his bold deſign.</l>
                  <l>Undaunted <hi>Jaſon</hi> had no ſooner heard</l>
                  <l>The news; but for the Voyage ſtraight prepar'd:</l>
                  <l>Of firm <hi>Dodonean</hi> wood, a Ship both ſtrong;</l>
                  <l>(And could diſcourſe him as ſhe rid a long.)</l>
                  <l>Nor were the youth of <hi>Greece</hi> ſo ſtupid grown</l>
                  <l>But that they thurſted likewiſe for Renown;</l>
                  <l>Each Fathers blood did in his Son create</l>
                  <l>Deſire to ſhare with <hi>Jaſon</hi> in his Fate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſeus</hi> nor <hi>Caſtor</hi> could not ſit at home</l>
                  <l>Whilſt his Young youth Minopoliz'd renown;</l>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:99965:85"/>
                  <l>But <hi>Pollux, Orpheus, Lynceus,</hi> and a Score</l>
                  <l>Of young Ambitious Valiant <hi>Grecians</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>Who would no opportunity decline</l>
                  <l>Of gaining Honour, went along with him.</l>
                  <l>To dauntleſs mindes, which Dangerous Glory court,</l>
                  <l>The turbulent fury of the Waves were ſport;</l>
                  <l>They only learnt by Calms, and Storms, to know</l>
                  <l>The various Fate the Great muſt undergo.</l>
                  <l>Thus whilſt <hi>Heroick</hi> thoughts had entertain'd</l>
                  <l>Their Minds; the fleeting Ship had <hi>Colchos</hi> gain'd;</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Jaſon</hi> by a Viſit made at Court,</l>
                  <l>To Fair <hi>Medea</hi> parted with his Heart,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe above her own ſo far prefers,</l>
                  <l>That in exchange, ſhe kindly ſent him hers;</l>
                  <l>Which fair return of Love did help to bring</l>
                  <l>To quick perfection <hi>Jaſons</hi> grand deſign.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Medea</hi> skil'd in Magick Art did prove,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Jaſon</hi> ſoon obliged by his Love:</l>
                  <l>Her ſire <hi>Eetha</hi>'s Int'reſt to diſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>When it in competition ſtood with his;</l>
                  <l>By Virtue of her Art, he caus'd her keep</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Horrid <hi>Bull;</hi> and <hi>Dragons</hi> faſt aſleep;</l>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:99965:86"/>
                  <l>Which bound in ſtrong <hi>Inchantments</hi> ſilent lay,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt a ſubtle <hi>Jaſon</hi> ſtole the Fleece away.</l>
                  <l>Which with <hi>Medea,</hi> (by the help of Night)</l>
                  <l>T'wards <hi>Theſſaly</hi> he made his haſty flight;</l>
                  <l>But was by <hi>Eetha</hi> perſu'd ſo far,</l>
                  <l>That Maugre both the Lovers ſpeed and care</l>
                  <l>They had been taken; had not <hi>Media</hi>'s Sin</l>
                  <l>By butchering his Son Prevented him:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe reeking Limbs, about the Road ſhe flung,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Eetha</hi> viewing as he ran along,</l>
                  <l>Gath'ring them up; bemoan'd the Infants Fate,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt both the Lovers made their ſafe retreat.</l>
                  <l>Thus what for <hi>Jaſons</hi> Ruin, <hi>Pelius</hi> ſought,</l>
                  <l>Has to his Fame immortal Glory brought.</l>
                  <l>'The Man whoſe Actions Virtue recommends,</l>
                  <l>'Is more Obliged to his Foes, than Friends.</l>
                  <l>'Their Senſures force him to unuſual <hi>Good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'VVhilſt theſe imbrace him in the common Road.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:86"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:87"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>THESEUS</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:99965:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Theſeus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>REnouned <hi>Theſeus</hi> of <hi>Aegeus</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>From whom th'<hi>Aegean</hi> Sea derives her Name.</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Theſeus</hi> came to age, the <hi>Athenian World</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He found, by Vices in Confuſion hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Great,</hi> (he ſaw) others goods did boaſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich their unequal ſtrength had rudely forc't</l>
                  <l>From helpleſs ſubjects; who were fain to Lye</l>
                  <l>Silent beneath their pond'rous Tyranny.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of Vertue, black Injuſtice Raign'd,</l>
                  <l>And rude Extortion overſpread the Land.</l>
                  <l>Princes turn'd Robers, and then greatneſs priz'd,</l>
                  <l>According as they had the poor diſpiz'd.</l>
                  <l>The Widdows crys <hi>Choruſt</hi> with <hi>Orphans</hi> Tears,</l>
                  <l>VVas the beſt Muſick could ſalute their Ears;</l>
                  <l>And him the Lawrel others did bequeath,</l>
                  <l>VVho to his Subjects gave the painful'ſt Death.</l>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99965:88"/>
                  <l>But when young <hi>Theſeus</hi> came to underſtand</l>
                  <l>The Sins and Horrors which beſmeer'd the Land,</l>
                  <l>His Virtuous anger did no courage lack</l>
                  <l>To give their Tyranies an harſh attaque.</l>
                  <l>The brutiſh <hi>Scyron</hi> who with grateful care,</l>
                  <l>Did plung into the Sea Each paſſenger;</l>
                  <l>Was the firſt victim glory did afford</l>
                  <l>To this young Princes unexperienc'd Sword.</l>
                  <l>The next <hi>Procruſtes</hi> was, who took delight,</l>
                  <l>With's Knife, his ſubjects Limbs to diſunite,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe happy Death too, did ſuch ſame afford,</l>
                  <l>As double gilded Conqu'ring <hi>Theſeus</hi>'s Sword.</l>
                  <l>But that which fil'd the Sails of Fame more full,</l>
                  <l>Was the Diſtruction of <hi>Marathons</hi> Bull;</l>
                  <l>Which with the aſſiſtance of a mighty Boar,</l>
                  <l>Had vanquiſhed <hi>Meleager</hi> juſt before.</l>
                  <l>But that which through the world did fartheſt fly,</l>
                  <l>And gave his Sword the deepeſt Purple Dye,</l>
                  <l>VVas that immortal honour he obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>When Conqueſt o're the Monitor he gain'd.</l>
                  <l>The manner thus. King <hi>Minos</hi> having loſt</l>
                  <l>His Son <hi>Androgius</hi> on the <hi>Attick</hi> Coaſt;</l>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:99965:88"/>
                  <l>(Who as he to his Native Country Fled,</l>
                  <l>VVas by thoſe Natives baſely Maſſacred)</l>
                  <l>Bears his proud Standarts 'fore <hi>Megara</hi>'s walls,</l>
                  <l>And there for ſatisfaction loudly calls:</l>
                  <l>Threatens, if once deny'd, that noyſe to change,</l>
                  <l>And make his Cannons Bellow hot revenge.</l>
                  <l>The Tremb'ling <hi>Megarites</hi> affraid appear,</l>
                  <l>And by no means will bear the brunts of war:</l>
                  <l>But rather than their ang'ry Foe withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Proffer him Peace upon his own demand.</l>
                  <l>VVhich was to this effect, th' <hi>Athenians</hi> were</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Men to ſend him every year;</l>
                  <l>VVhich by the Kings command were deſtin'd for</l>
                  <l>To be devour'd by this huge <hi>Monitor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(VVhom <hi>Paſiphea, Minos</hi> Luſtful wife,</l>
                  <l>By the imbraces of a Bull gave Life)</l>
                  <l>Amongſt thoſe Youths, who this hard fate did run,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſeus</hi> intreats th' <hi>Athenians</hi> to be one;</l>
                  <l>That from that ſtrange inhuman tribute he,</l>
                  <l>Might be the means to ſet his Country free;</l>
                  <l>Ingageing he the Nation would Exempt</l>
                  <l>From that ſad Debt, or Periſh i'th' attempt.</l>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:99965:89"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aegeus</hi> and his States-Men both profeſt,</l>
                  <l>VVith much remorſe they granted his requeſt.</l>
                  <l>And caus'd his Ship in Sable Flags to Mourn,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak their Sorrow till his ſafe Return.</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Theſeus</hi> promis'd to ſupply with VVhite,</l>
                  <l>If Conqueſt Crown'd him i'th' unequal Fight.</l>
                  <l>But if with wind thoſe gloomy Sails were Fil'd,</l>
                  <l>In her return, they might conclude him Kil'd,</l>
                  <l>VVith this adiew, they cut the Liquid main,</l>
                  <l>And with ſucceſs the Iſle of <hi>Crete</hi> obtain;</l>
                  <l>At whoſe arrival, <hi>Mino</hi>'s ſeems o're joy'd,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Athenians</hi> had ſo brave a tribute pay'd</l>
                  <l>Of Luſty Youths, whom he ſecured for</l>
                  <l>The dayly Viends of his <hi>Monitor;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich monſtrous Creature <hi>Mino</hi>'s had beſtow'd,</l>
                  <l>(As the moſt inacceſſable aboad)</l>
                  <l>In fam'd <hi>Dadalus</hi> Laberinth; which did</l>
                  <l>VVith various windings all return forbid</l>
                  <l>To thoſe whom buſineſs or diverſion led,</l>
                  <l>Th' elaborate turnings of the Maze to tread.</l>
                  <l>But nature <hi>Theſeus</hi> ſuch attractments lent,</l>
                  <l>As he with eaſe, this danger did prevent:</l>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:99965:89"/>
                  <l>By his good features he familiar grew</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Ariadne</hi> who retain'd the Clew,</l>
                  <l>VVhich to the hideous Monſter gave acceſs,</l>
                  <l>And free'd th' invader from the fatal Maze.</l>
                  <l>On promiſe <hi>Theſeus</hi> would this fair one VVed,</l>
                  <l>She kindly lent him the aſſiſting Thred;</l>
                  <l>By which conducted to the Monitor,</l>
                  <l>VVhom he attempted with ſuch art and pow'r,</l>
                  <l>That all the indulgence <hi>Theſeus</hi> could afford,</l>
                  <l>VVas, that he dy'd by ſo Renoun'd a Sword.</l>
                  <l>VVhen the brave Conqueſt <hi>Theſeus</hi> had obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>VVhich nobly drew him from his Native Land;</l>
                  <l>And no atchievment elſe was left, which cou'd,</l>
                  <l>By his attempting do his Country Good.</l>
                  <l>He fled with <hi>Ariadne</hi> to that Shore,</l>
                  <l>Where he had Landed not a week before;</l>
                  <l>And where his Fellows, with his Ship had lain</l>
                  <l>VVith much impatience, ſince expecting him,</l>
                  <l>VVho when they Loaded, ſaw with that fair prize</l>
                  <l>Unuſual Joy their drooping ſpirits ſeize,</l>
                  <l>They then no longer doubted his ſucceſs,</l>
                  <l>Conqueſt ſate ſmileing in his princely Face;</l>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:99965:90"/>
                  <l>Beſides, his beautious Plunder lookt ſo fair,</l>
                  <l>They knew ſhe was the juſt reward of war;</l>
                  <l>Nothing but Valour could ſuch Riches buy,</l>
                  <l>Beauty's a prize for glorious Victory;</l>
                  <l>VVith joyful Tryumph, they their Sails diſplay,</l>
                  <l>And with ſtrong Oars aſſiſt the Leaſy Sea —</l>
                  <l>But diſmal grief ſhall o're their joy prevail;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſeus</hi> forgets to ſhift the Gloomy Sail,</l>
                  <l>VVhich as a ſign of Death <hi>Egeus</hi> View'd</l>
                  <l>From off the Shoar, and jumpt into the Flood.</l>
                  <l>So careful of his Fame the Monarch was,</l>
                  <l>He wou'd not live to hear his Sons diſgrace;</l>
                  <l>But left him on his error to reflect,</l>
                  <l>VVho loſt a Father by his groſs neglect.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:90"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:91"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>CERES</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:99965:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Ceres.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat ſtrange <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s in the time to come,</l>
                  <l>Does man conceit, to drag him to his doom.</l>
                  <l>VVho could he but his certain <hi>Ills</hi> diſcry,</l>
                  <l>VVould baulk his <hi>Fate,</hi> and bravely chooſe to dye.</l>
                  <l>In humane Life it is as <hi>Seas</hi> decreed,</l>
                  <l>The frequent Storms do much the Calmes exceed.</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Griefs,</hi> continu'd as the Earth appear,</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt <hi>Muſhroom joys</hi> ſprout out but here and there.</l>
                  <l>And by their <hi>Fetch-fire</hi> Stay, ſo uſeleſs grow,</l>
                  <l>Like Ghoſts they leave us, and we know not how:</l>
                  <l>As well in his ſhort <hi>Graſp</hi> may man ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe flaſhes Thunder frightens from the Skyes,</l>
                  <l>Lay hold of Light'ning, and ſay here it is,</l>
                  <l>As, <hi>here's an hour of undiſturbed Bliſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And yet this ſilly, huffing, Creature <hi>Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho ſtartles the Creation with his Name.</l>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:99965:92"/>
                  <l>VVhoſe unjuſt force, ſpoyls Natures <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Feeding on Creatures happier than himſelf,</l>
                  <l>VVho only wanting Reaſons, helps to guide</l>
                  <l>Their Nobler parts, lie ſubject to his Pride;</l>
                  <l>This ſilly thing, I ſay, who hectors here,</l>
                  <l>And will admit of no Competitor,</l>
                  <l>Nor holds with other Creatures kind commerce,</l>
                  <l>But Proudly <hi>Lords</hi> it o're the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How tame and baſely does he bear the weight</l>
                  <l>And groſs affronts of his Injurious Fate!</l>
                  <l>How like a ſordid <hi>Aſs</hi> he groaning Lies,</l>
                  <l>Under the Burthen of his Miſeries!</l>
                  <l>How unconcern'd the wonderous <hi>Thing</hi> appears,</l>
                  <l>Maugre the influence of his envious Stars!</l>
                  <l>Fate, like a Hectoring <hi>Gamſter</hi> gives the wrong,</l>
                  <l>And after Kicks him till he holds his tongue.</l>
                  <l>Silent as Night, the reaſoning <hi>Bubble</hi> ſtands,</l>
                  <l>And mildly takes the <hi>Buffets</hi> at her Hands:</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Sans</hi> Reſiſtance he does ſtill ſuſtain,</l>
                  <l>Blinded by hope ſhee'l let him play again;</l>
                  <l>Then with a diſtant <hi>Joy</hi> ſhe charmes his Eies,</l>
                  <l>Which, like his Shadow, he perſuing flies,</l>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:99965:92"/>
                  <l>As diſtant <hi>Foggs</hi> which 'fore us thick appear,</l>
                  <l>But vaniſh when we travel where they are.</l>
                  <l>Thus whilſt in queſt of <hi>Bliſs</hi> he vainly ſtays,</l>
                  <l>She rudely cheats him of his Youth, and days.</l>
                  <l>And after all his Lifetime b'ing her ſlave,</l>
                  <l>Sends him a <hi>Bonkrupt</hi> to his Dampiſh Grave.</l>
                  <l>Ah! who (that wares his Paſtport by his ſide)</l>
                  <l>Would thus be ſubject to her boundleſs Pride;</l>
                  <l>That had but <hi>Wit,</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> enough to try,</l>
                  <l>To thwart her <hi>Rage,</hi> and bravely chooſe to Dye;</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Alps</hi> of <hi>Ills</hi> ſhe makes him melt his way</l>
                  <l>Through, to obtain but one poor glimps of joy;</l>
                  <l>And then what <hi>Wells</hi> of Grief he falls into,</l>
                  <l>Looſing the pleaſure which he did perſue.</l>
                  <l>Thus careful <hi>Ceres,</hi> her propoſed bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Plac't in her wilful Daughters happineſs.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Proſerpina</hi>'s Beauty ſeem'd t'ingage</l>
                  <l>Her Mothers wiſhes when ſhe came to Age.</l>
                  <l>Th' admiting Gods, with all their cunning, ſtrove</l>
                  <l>VVho ſhould be moſt officious in his Love:</l>
                  <l>VVhilſt her perfections Guarded by her Pride,</l>
                  <l>Firſt bid them ſue, and then their fuit deny'd.</l>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:99965:93"/>
                  <l>Each Heav'nly Lover by his gheſſes ſought,</l>
                  <l>VVho could anticipate her happy thought.</l>
                  <l>And put into accepted Act the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Before her words had given it any Name;</l>
                  <l>Nor common Gods alone, but mighty <hi>Jove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As well as they, adorn'd her with his Love;</l>
                  <l>And all the other <hi>Deities</hi> by him,</l>
                  <l>Takeing example, gave her great eſteem.</l>
                  <l>VVhereat contented <hi>Ceres</hi> ſimp'ring ſate,</l>
                  <l>Almoſt aſſured of her Daughters Fate;</l>
                  <l>That it muſt glorious be ſince a reſpect</l>
                  <l>So great as hers wou'd brook no ill effect;</l>
                  <l>But whoſe preſages can foretel the hit,</l>
                  <l>VVhich often happens 'twixt the <hi>Cup</hi> and <hi>Lip.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or who ſo prudent is to truely Gheſs,</l>
                  <l>In threat'ning <hi>Goods,</hi> or <hi>Ills,</hi> their right ſucceſs.</l>
                  <l>In whoſe is it, but mighty <hi>Joves</hi> great power?</l>
                  <l>To tell the product of a ſhort liv'd Hour;</l>
                  <l>Or when big belly'd <hi>Time</hi> affords a Birth,</l>
                  <l>To one poor <hi>Minute</hi> what it ſhall bring forth?</l>
                  <l>Alaſs! our ſhort Inſpections are confin'd,</l>
                  <l>VVe judg the Apple by its glorious Rhind,</l>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:99965:93"/>
                  <l>Pleas'd with the outſide, we no farther look,</l>
                  <l>VVe only read the Cover of the Book,</l>
                  <l>VVhich if but wrapt up in a gaudy skin,</l>
                  <l>We think it Good and mind not what's within.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fate,</hi> like a Curious <hi>Clock-work</hi> we diſcern,</l>
                  <l>The motion we behold, but cannot learn</l>
                  <l>The manner how it makes its wound'rous flight,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Working-Springs</hi> alaſs! are barr'd our ſight,</l>
                  <l>By its paſt motion we ſuppoſe it will</l>
                  <l>Run on, and keep it ſelf in Action ſtill;</l>
                  <l>But then the wiſeſt of us does not know</l>
                  <l>The pace it tends to, whither faſt, or ſlow,</l>
                  <l>Our earneſt wiſhes can't its ſtay perſwade,</l>
                  <l>It may ſtand ſtill for <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> or Retrograde.</l>
                  <l>As well the VVeather, we may hope controul;</l>
                  <l>VVe muſt indure it whether Fair, or Foul —</l>
                  <l>But when Injurious <hi>Fate</hi> deſigns to ſhow</l>
                  <l>How great the Ills are which ſhe can beſtow;</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſhe grows wanton, and intends to be</l>
                  <l>Eſteemed witty by her Cruelty.</l>
                  <l>Up to the higheſt Hill of Hope ſhe heaves</l>
                  <l>The poor condemned wretch, who thence perceives,</l>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:99965:94"/>
                  <l>Almoſt within his reach the wiſht for Joy,</l>
                  <l>VVhich as he goes to graſp—ſhe plucks away;</l>
                  <l>And from the ſummit of a hope ſo fair,</l>
                  <l>Tumbles him headlong into black diſpair.</l>
                  <l>Thus careful <hi>Ceres</hi> with glad Eies beheld,</l>
                  <l>The proſperous progreſs of her Beauteous Child:</l>
                  <l>From whoſe paſt Fortunes ſhe did more than Gheſs</l>
                  <l>At her dear Daughters future happineſs.</l>
                  <l>She now ſhakes hands with all her pains and Care,</l>
                  <l>And lets brisk <hi>Joy</hi> ſupply the place of fear.</l>
                  <l>But am'rous <hi>Pluto</hi> ſoon this Calm diſtroys,</l>
                  <l>He raviſht both her <hi>Daughter,</hi> and her <hi>Joys;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Teaching us all (at her exceſſive Coſt)</l>
                  <l>To make no Reconings there where <hi>Fate's</hi> the <hi>Hoſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:94"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:95"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>SALACIA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:99965:95"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Salacia.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO what wild Actions do our phancies Move,</l>
                  <l>VVhen toſt and hurry'd by a ſtorm of Love!</l>
                  <l>Hudwinckt by it, we take our full Carreer,</l>
                  <l>Leap at adventure, though we know not where;</l>
                  <l>Like Fear, it makes us Jump in ſo much haſt,</l>
                  <l>We mind no danger till 'tis fully paſt;</l>
                  <l>But in our calm return do wond'ring find,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe mighty Ditches which we left behind:</l>
                  <l>VVe then amazed ſtand to ſee Loves Pow'r,</l>
                  <l>And ſtart at what we undertook before.</l>
                  <l>When Love like ſome great <hi>Monarch,</hi> is inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To ſit at <hi>Helm</hi> and ſteer the Lab'ring Mind;</l>
                  <l>VVhether he guides the Veſſel right, or wrong,</l>
                  <l>The other paſſions almoſt hold their Tongue.</l>
                  <l>Like common <hi>Sea-men</hi> they muſt all ſtand ſtill,</l>
                  <l>To be conducted by his potent will.</l>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:99965:96"/>
                  <l>Though Heav'n does know how oft on Rocks we ſplit,</l>
                  <l>VVhen Love's the <hi>Pilot</hi> of our Creaſie Ship,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes to Northern Coaſts he makes his way,</l>
                  <l>And Freezes Lovers in an <hi>Icy</hi> Sea</l>
                  <l>Of deep diſpair, where they complaining lye,</l>
                  <l>Till Death Redeems them from the ſlavery.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes on <hi>Calmy Seas</hi> he ſeems to float,</l>
                  <l>And Ruins Lovers in the midſt of Hope.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes t'ward <hi>Home</hi> he kindly does reſort,</l>
                  <l>And gives 'um Shipwrack in their wiſht for Port;</l>
                  <l>Such various Ruins hapleſs Lovers weight,</l>
                  <l>'Twould reel an <hi>Atlaſs</hi> to ſuſtain their Fate,</l>
                  <l>And make him think (could he their ſorrows view)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>World</hi> the lighter burden of the two,</l>
                  <l>Miſterious <hi>Love</hi> his ſubjects do's ingage</l>
                  <l>To run to miſeries themſelves preſage,</l>
                  <l>Their Minds like his, with frantick valor fill'd,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſtabs himſelf for fear of being kill'd.</l>
                  <l>Thus fair <hi>Salacia</hi> having ſeen what grace</l>
                  <l>And God like luſter ſhown in <hi>Neptunes</hi> face,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Reaſons</hi> help endeavour'd to refrain</l>
                  <l>From that fierce Love which ſhe oppos'd in Vain;</l>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:99965:96"/>
                  <l>But blinking <hi>Cupid</hi> ſtruck the fiery Dart</l>
                  <l>With ſo much force in her unguarded Heart,</l>
                  <l>That ſtartled Reaſon, her Old ſtage forſook,</l>
                  <l>Fearing to bear the burden — of the ſhock.</l>
                  <l>And in her abſence mighty <hi>Love</hi> poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>The happy <hi>Manſion</hi> of <hi>Salacia's</hi> Breſt.</l>
                  <l>Ah <hi>Love!</hi> how many ſleep-obſtructing <hi>Cares!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How many <hi>Tortures,</hi> bloody <hi>Maſſacres!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How many dauncing Tides, of <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How many <hi>Groans!</hi> what Gulphs of deep diſpair!</l>
                  <l>May that unhappy wretch expect to bear,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe warm breaſt thou ſit'ſt as Emperior.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Salacia's</hi> diſmal ſtory will diſcry</l>
                  <l>In part the Rigor of thy <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The beautious Maid unable to ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>The frequent preſſures of her growing flame,</l>
                  <l>Repair'd with ſpeed to thoſe Cool ſhady bowers,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Neptune</hi> ſpent his Melancholly hours.</l>
                  <l>When freindly Calms had kindly ſet him free,</l>
                  <l>From the tuition of the Rageing <hi>Sea,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cover'd with bluſhes, there <hi>Salatia</hi> ſpoke</l>
                  <l>To ſurly <hi>Neptune,</hi> whom ſhe did invoke</l>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:99965:97"/>
                  <l>(By all thoſe deareſt things poor Lovers name)</l>
                  <l>To mind and pitty her increaſing flame.</l>
                  <l>She told him how at firſt the pleaſing ſight</l>
                  <l>Of his perfection gave her great delight,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe had often ſtole to that bleſt place,</l>
                  <l>And worn out evenings, Gazing at his face:</l>
                  <l>From whence ſhe did behold ſuch glories come,</l>
                  <l>As do's through Boughs, invaded by the Sun.</l>
                  <l>When ſhivering Leaves the warm aſſaults abide,</l>
                  <l>And make a <hi>Checquer</hi> on the other ſide.</l>
                  <l>She told him that from looking, her ſtrange thought</l>
                  <l>To <hi>likeing</hi> firſt, and thence to <hi>Love</hi> was brought:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Love</hi> did all her former quiet ſeize,</l>
                  <l>Before ſhe could immagine what he was.</l>
                  <l>He robb'd her days of buſineſs, and Delights,</l>
                  <l>Of ſleep, ſhe ſaid, he rudely robb'd her Nights:</l>
                  <l>And now of late ſo inſolent was grown,</l>
                  <l>He often ſpoyl'd her high <hi>Devotion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She told him farther that ſhe once deſign'd</l>
                  <l>To blow the Embers of her reſtleſs mind,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a ſcorching blaze as might conſume,</l>
                  <l>The Oyl of life, and ſo prevent her doom.</l>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:99965:97"/>
                  <l>Before the ſtory of her love ſhould fly</l>
                  <l>About the World, to Preach her infamy.</l>
                  <l>Laſtly ſhe told him (and a Pearly Due</l>
                  <l>Of trickling Tears affirm'd it to be true)</l>
                  <l>That that ſame inſtant he contemn'd her Love,</l>
                  <l>She wou'd to ſome unheard of Deſart rove,</l>
                  <l>There to remain, till ſtrong Corroding greif</l>
                  <l>Should put a period to her wretched life.</l>
                  <l>Th' imperious <hi>God,</hi> ſwel'd with that vaſt renown,</l>
                  <l>VVhich he derived from his watry Throne,</l>
                  <l>VVith thoughts of <hi>Glory</hi> ſo his mind imploy'd,</l>
                  <l>That there was room for nothing elſe beſide.</l>
                  <l>The pitteous ſtory from the <hi>Nymph</hi> he heard,</l>
                  <l>With ſome ſmall ſilence, but much leſs reguard.</l>
                  <l>And then as unconcern'd made haſty way</l>
                  <l>To his old home, and Jumpt into the Sea.</l>
                  <l>Ah <hi>Love!</hi> what wond'rous dangers doſt thou make,</l>
                  <l>Thy poor neglected <hi>Captives</hi> undertake!</l>
                  <l>Diſdainful <hi>Neptune,</hi> could not make ſuch haſt</l>
                  <l>But greiv'd <hi>Salatia</hi> could perſue as faſt.</l>
                  <l>And from the very banck where on he ſtood</l>
                  <l>When he jumpt off, ſhe leapt into the flood,</l>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:99965:98"/>
                  <l>Where, from her beauties, ſuch bright beams did ſcatter,</l>
                  <l>As do from Glittering torches under water.</l>
                  <l>The joyful fiſh about the ſolſtice play,</l>
                  <l>Thinking the Sun is dropt into the Sea. —</l>
                  <l>At length a freindly <hi>Dolphin,</hi> who with greif,</l>
                  <l>Had ſeen what pains <hi>Salacia</hi> took for life;</l>
                  <l>Preſents his ſcaly Back, whereon the Maid,</l>
                  <l>By his aſſiſtance, and her own convey'd;</l>
                  <l>Is born to <hi>Neptunes</hi> Court: the wond'ring King,</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd and troubled at her ſuffering,</l>
                  <l>Admits a noble Gratitude, to find</l>
                  <l>Afair reception in his Princely Mind.</l>
                  <l>VVhich made him all his former pride diſown,</l>
                  <l>And Crown her <hi>Empreſs</hi> of his watry <hi>Throne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:98"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:99"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>VULCAN</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:99965:99"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Vulcan.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> what raſh Pen dare ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To attribute their juſt prerogative.</l>
                  <l>In things <hi>inanimate</hi> they charm as well,</l>
                  <l>As in Thoſe <hi>Rational,</hi> or <hi>ſenſible.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beauty</hi> ſtill pleaſes, and retains its force,</l>
                  <l>Though Laviſh nature waſts it on a <hi>Horſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich oft ſhe does, on every Limb throughout,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Hump-Back</hi> Mortals murmuring, go without.</l>
                  <l>But it's <hi>Antipodes Monſtroſity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Contracts a hateful Glance from ev'ry Eye.</l>
                  <l>VVe ſee it often ſuch an <hi>Odium</hi> draws,</l>
                  <l>As interrupts the Courſe of Natures Laws.</l>
                  <l>Makes ſtartled <hi>Fathers</hi> from their Children run,</l>
                  <l>The trembling <hi>Mother</hi> curſe her teeming VVomb.</l>
                  <l>Makes bluſhing <hi>Gods</hi> from their dear Iſſue fly,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Goddeſſes</hi> diſown their Progeny.</l>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:99965:100"/>
                  <l>It made great <hi>Jupiter</hi> from his high Thrown,</l>
                  <l>To Earths Low ſeat, caſt homely <hi>Vulcan</hi> down.</l>
                  <l>Nature with all her wheedlings could not make,</l>
                  <l>A full attonement for his ugly ſhape.</l>
                  <l>Though with her uſual preſſures ſhe could plead,</l>
                  <l>He was the off-ſpring of his Marriage Bed.</l>
                  <l>And helpleſs Infancy one would have thought,</l>
                  <l>Might in a Father much Compaſſion wrought,</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe were arguments too weak t'engage</l>
                  <l>The angry Father, to ſuſpend his Rage;</l>
                  <l>VVho by a fall ſo great as from his Thrown,</l>
                  <l>Thought to have ended his detaſted Son.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Juno</hi> to God <hi>Aeolus</hi> did call</l>
                  <l>To raiſe ſuch winds, as might abate his fall:</l>
                  <l>VVhich interpoſſing 'twixt the Earth and him,</l>
                  <l>Hinder'd his Father of his harſh deſign.</l>
                  <l>Born on the downy back of ſome ſoft Gale,</l>
                  <l>Secur'd of Life, the tumbling Infant fell</l>
                  <l>VVith one Leg under him, which being two ſmall</l>
                  <l>To bear his weight, was broken in the fall;</l>
                  <l>Of which he after Limpt, But by the fame</l>
                  <l>VVhich by his parts th'abuſed Child did gain;</l>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:99965:100"/>
                  <l>VVhen Manly years, like the approaching day,</l>
                  <l>Had Chac'd his <hi>Night</hi> of Infancy away:</l>
                  <l>I'de have the Reader and my ſelf beware</l>
                  <l>Of ſlighting Noble parts, where e're they are.</l>
                  <l>VVhat if unburniſht walls thy Soul imbrace,</l>
                  <l>Thy Glittering mind will lighten all the Caſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhat though thy Body's in a Suit that's torn,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf neglected, and thy ſtate forlorn;</l>
                  <l>VVhat if misfortunes hurry thee to dwell</l>
                  <l>In ſome low Cottage, or ſome mouldy Cell;</l>
                  <l>VVit like the pureſt mettels which are found,</l>
                  <l>VVill ſtill keep precious, though 't be under ground.</l>
                  <l>And time may come, when they thy parts may crave,</l>
                  <l>VVho now deride thee whilſt thou'rt Fortunes ſlave.</l>
                  <l>VVhat though the killing thunder, from a brow</l>
                  <l>Of ſome Great <hi>Monarch,</hi> ſtoop to cut thee low,</l>
                  <l>Thou mayſt with ſaftey (if thou'rt truly wiſe,)</l>
                  <l>Th' obſtreperous buſsle of the ſtorm diſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>Stay till its o're —; and thou ſhalt ſurely find,</l>
                  <l>VVhen threatning dangers do infeſt his mind.</l>
                  <l>He will revoke his rage, and Court thee more</l>
                  <l>Than he diſdain'd, or envy'd the before.</l>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:99965:101"/>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Jove,</hi> whilſt Rowling in a peace ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Could not the preſence of his Son indure.</l>
                  <l>But cauſe he homly ſeem'd, muſt him abhor:</l>
                  <l>(A fault the child might thank his Parents for.)</l>
                  <l>VVhen proſperous Greatneſs ſwells the faded mind,</l>
                  <l>In things moſt perfect, men will errors find.</l>
                  <l>But when misfortune makes her Rude aſſaults,</l>
                  <l>They choſe the good, and over look the faults.</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Tytans</hi> Injur'd ſeed did take up Arms,</l>
                  <l>And frighted <hi>Heaven</hi> with their loud Allarms.</l>
                  <l>Threw Hills, on Hills, till Mountains grew ſo high,</l>
                  <l>That thence they reacht the <hi>Rampiers</hi> of the Sky.</l>
                  <l>And urg'd by <hi>wrongs,</hi> ſo inſolent were grown,</l>
                  <l>To threaten <hi>Jove,</hi> to pull him from his Thrown.</l>
                  <l>The Heav'nly <hi>Emperor</hi> his rage to ſhow,</l>
                  <l>At firſt Salutes them with a frowning brow,</l>
                  <l>But that Alas! was in ſignif'cant now.</l>
                  <l>Then haſtily he calls the other <hi>Gods,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But they were frighted to their dark abodes,</l>
                  <l>And from their <hi>Monarch</hi> in his danger run,</l>
                  <l>Then he bethinks him of his injur'd Son:</l>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:99965:101"/>
                  <l>VVho readily to his aſſiſtance flyes,</l>
                  <l>And drives the threatning <hi>Gyants</hi> from the skyes.</l>
                  <l>Rallies the Timerous Gods, and chides them ſo,</l>
                  <l>He made 'em Valiant if they wou'd or no.</l>
                  <l>Thus from a private ſword a <hi>Prince</hi> may gain</l>
                  <l>The help he hopes from's <hi>General</hi> in vain.</l>
                  <l>A poor <hi>D'Amboys</hi> with a noble Soul,</l>
                  <l>Could all the factious men in <hi>France</hi> Controul.</l>
                  <l>And from her threatn'd <hi>Crown,</hi> thoſe dangers Chace,</l>
                  <l>VVhich boldly ſtar'd whole <hi>Armies</hi> in the face.</l>
                  <l>This brave aſſault neglected <hi>Vulcan</hi> gave</l>
                  <l>The Dairing <hi>Gyants,</hi> made the <hi>Gods</hi> perceive</l>
                  <l>Through the Dark Lanthorne of his gloomy skin,</l>
                  <l>A brave <hi>Heroick</hi> ſpirit lodg'd within.</l>
                  <l>Such as not only VVarlike actions Grace,</l>
                  <l>But might be uſeful in the time of Peace.</l>
                  <l>To dangerous <hi>Valour</hi> needful <hi>Art</hi> conjoyn'd,</l>
                  <l>To the compleating of his noble mind;</l>
                  <l>VVhich made great <hi>Jove</hi> (when bold <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſtole</l>
                  <l>From Heav'ns warm Alter; the immortal Coal;</l>
                  <l>To move his <hi>forms,</hi> which wanted but a Soul.</l>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:99965:102"/>
                  <l>Great <hi>Vulcan</hi> in the puniſhment imploy,</l>
                  <l>VVho by his <hi>Black-Smiths</hi> art found out away</l>
                  <l>On top of <hi>Mount Caucaſus</hi> bleakiſh Rift,</l>
                  <l>To bind him faſt, for his ambitious Thieft.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Gods</hi> to <hi>Vulcan</hi> now gave great regard,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe hot forge their Armour was prepar'd:</l>
                  <l>But that which gave Heav'ns <hi>Black-ſmith</hi> moſt renown,</l>
                  <l>He forg'd the Glittering Charriot of the Sun:</l>
                  <l>VVith his own hands he wrought that wondrous ſteel,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhut out Death from all parts but the heel.</l>
                  <l>Temper'd by him with ſo much care and Art,</l>
                  <l>It ſcorn'd the fury of Strong <hi>Hectors</hi> Dart.</l>
                  <l>And made the wond'ring <hi>Trojans</hi> Stare to ſee,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Grecian</hi> clad in <hi>Immortality.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:102"/>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99965:103"/>
               <head type="engraving">
                  <figure>
                     <head>VESTA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:99965:103"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Poetical Hiſtory of</hi> Veſta.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS tis with <hi>Salvage</hi> Nations, who deſcent</l>
                  <l>Amongſt themſelves, for want of Government:</l>
                  <l>Some Learned <hi>Heathen</hi> wiſer then the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Greiving to fee his native Land oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Urg'd by a gen'rous inclination, tryes</l>
                  <l>To heal the <hi>Breach,</hi> by firm lay'd Policies.</l>
                  <l>Which to effect, he from the Crowd withdraws,</l>
                  <l>And there Invents ſuch ſound and wholſome Laws,</l>
                  <l>As by obſervance, probably might be,</l>
                  <l>The certain means to their proſperity.</l>
                  <l>VVhich when h' has done, he tells them that he finds</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Monarchick</hi> Government beſt ſuits their minds.</l>
                  <l>VVhich in ambitions Road too high do ſoar,</l>
                  <l>T' admit of more than one Superior.</l>
                  <l>The Gaping crow'd with patience thus far hear;</l>
                  <l>But when he comes to a particular,</l>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:99965:104"/>
                  <l>And ask them who of all the Land they 'ſteem</l>
                  <l>Worthy'ſt to wear the Royal <hi>Diadem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A thouſand different votes invade the air,</l>
                  <l>Some for reſpect do chooſe, and ſome for fear.</l>
                  <l>Some Glittering <hi>Intereſt</hi> makes to vote a lowd,</l>
                  <l>And others only bawl amongſt the Crowd.</l>
                  <l>Till by a Differing ſtrange Confuſed cry,</l>
                  <l>They quite confound their dull layd <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So he who Backward caſts his careful eye.</l>
                  <l>And traces Atheiſm to its infancy:</l>
                  <l>Who by the ſtrength of boundleſs phancy, can</l>
                  <l>Conceipt he ſees the world as it began.</l>
                  <l>I mean thoſe parts of it, which yet had layn</l>
                  <l>Barren for want of great <hi>Jehovahs</hi> Name)</l>
                  <l>May well immagine e're their firſt advance</l>
                  <l>From Atheiſm, and bruitiſh Ignorance,</l>
                  <l>How ſordidly, and like the common Herd,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wretches liv'd, without the leaſt regard</l>
                  <l>To different good, or evil, which did lie</l>
                  <l>Obſcure from them, as thoughts of <hi>Deity;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till ſome brave <hi>Heathen,</hi> who with care had hurld,</l>
                  <l>His watchful eyes about this wondrous world;</l>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:99965:104"/>
                  <l>Veiw'd this well order'd Maſs of earth, and the</l>
                  <l>Reſtrained Limits of the threatning <hi>Sea.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſwift pac'd <hi>year,</hi> and the alternate courſe</l>
                  <l>Of Radient <hi>Day,</hi> and ſable <hi>Night,</hi> by force</l>
                  <l>Of ſome EXISTANCE, which refus'd t' appear,</l>
                  <l>But was indeed Dame <hi>Natures</hi> Taskmaſter.</l>
                  <l>Which he concluded muſt immortal Be,</l>
                  <l>Omnicient too, and ſo a Deity.</l>
                  <l>Which verdict after him the Brethren paſs,</l>
                  <l>Though none knew what, or who, or where he was.</l>
                  <l>So that for want of <hi>Scriptures</hi> faithful <hi>Clue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So they ador'd, they car'd not what, nor who.</l>
                  <l>Some as the only God, great <hi>Saturn</hi> follow,</l>
                  <l>Some worſhip <hi>Mars,</hi> and ſome Divine <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſome <hi>Venus</hi> moſt Eſteem,</l>
                  <l>And ſome the Horned <hi>Black-Smith</hi> took for him.</l>
                  <l>Nay ſome in fragrant Feilds, and Gardens ſeek,</l>
                  <l>In hopes to find them in their <hi>Rue,</hi> or <hi>Leek.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt others more remote, ador'd by fame,</l>
                  <l>And nicknam'd one God with anothers name.</l>
                  <l>Thus that high thought which firſt did nobly ſoar,</l>
                  <l>In eager queſt of the <hi>Aeternal pow'r,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:99965:105"/>
                  <l>Was clipt or Pinnion'd by the grovling crow'd:</l>
                  <l>Who nothing of its Vallew underſtood:</l>
                  <l>But ranckt in <hi>Sects,</hi> to ſuch confuſion fled,</l>
                  <l>As quite deſtroy'd their Deities indeed.</l>
                  <l>Leaving it difficult for us to give,</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>God</hi> or Goddeſs, juſt Derivetive.</l>
                  <l>Thus from great <hi>Saturn,</hi> and fair <hi>Rhea's</hi> womb,</l>
                  <l>The Goddeſs <hi>Veſta</hi> is deduc'd by ſome.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt others ſearching out her doubtful birth,</l>
                  <l>Mother to <hi>Saturn</hi> call'd her, and the Earth.</l>
                  <l>How e're the fame of her chaſt life was hurld</l>
                  <l>In that rude age, about the liſtening world.</l>
                  <l>And noble <hi>Romans</hi> (who with watchful Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Did mind young <hi>Virtue</hi> in her ſpring or riſe.</l>
                  <l>In Infant <hi>Veſta</hi> ſaw ſo larg a ſtore,</l>
                  <l>As made them fall from loving, to adore</l>
                  <l>Her peerleſs Chaſtitie, which did incline</l>
                  <l>Them to believe its owner was Divine.</l>
                  <l>Then in reſpect of beauty, wit, and birth,</l>
                  <l>They Goddeſs term'd her, both of fire and Earth.</l>
                  <l>And rais'd her ſuch a Temple, as did prove</l>
                  <l>The Romiſh Piety as well as Love:</l>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:99965:105"/>
                  <l>The glorious out-ſide of it did appear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> to ſight, in ſhape Orbicular.</l>
                  <l>The carved in-ſide Gorgious to behold;</l>
                  <l>The Pavement, marble Pillers, cloath'd in gold.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt glittering Flames her ſacred Alters Crown,</l>
                  <l>(Fir'd with no other Taper but the Sun.)</l>
                  <l>A thouſand untouch'd Virgins round her ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To hear the dictates of her chaſt command.</l>
                  <l>Which by a ſecret inſtinct they imbrace,</l>
                  <l>And by their beſt endeavours bring to paſs.</l>
                  <l>"Such charms are Coucht in real virtue, that</l>
                  <l>"It can at worſt command a happy fate.</l>
                  <l>"Men in the hot meridian of their Time,</l>
                  <l>"Bubbel'd by Hell, uncleanneſs may deſign.</l>
                  <l>"And urg'd by blood, and youth, together may,</l>
                  <l>"To their dear coſt that trivial bliſs enjoy.</l>
                  <l>"But when tyrannick age ſhall rudely throw</l>
                  <l>"Her hands abroad, and dredg their heads with ſnow;</l>
                  <l>"VVhen to their greif their ſtreaked Locks they ſee,</l>
                  <l>"(The ſtartling <hi>TOKENS</hi> of mortality.)</l>
                  <l>"A Strange remorſe ſhall ſtrike through all their Limbs</l>
                  <l>"Their quivering knees ſhall ſink beneath their ſins.</l>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:99965:106"/>
                  <l>"And they when 'tis too late be forc't to own,</l>
                  <l>"No lifes ſo happy as the Pious one.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99965:106"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
